<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="claim-check"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Claim Check</title>

  <section id="claim-check-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    In the earlier sections we've covered several Content Enricher type components that help you deal with situations where a 
    message is missing a piece of data. We also discussed Content Filtering which lets you remove data items from a message. 
    However there are times when we want to hide data temporarily. For example, in a distributed system we may receive a 
    Message with a very large payload. Some intermittent message processing steps may not need access to this payload and some may only 
    need to access certain headers, so carrying the large Message payload through each processing step may cause performance degradation,
    may produce a security risk, and may make debugging more difficult.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    The <link href="http://www.eaipatterns.com/StoreInLibrary.html">Claim Check</link> pattern describes a mechanism that allows you 
    to store data in a well known place while only maintaining a pointer (Claim Check) to where that data is located. You can pass that
    pointer around as a payload of a new Message thereby allowing any component within the message flow to get the actual data as soon as 
    it needs it. This approach is very similar to the Certified Mail process where you'll get a Claim Check in your mailbox and 
    would have to go to the Post Office to claim your actual package. Of course it's also the same idea as baggage-claim on a flight
    or in a hotel.
    </para>

    <para>
    Spring Integration provides two types of Claim Check transformers: <emphasis>Incoming Claim Check Transformer</emphasis> and 
    <emphasis>Outgoing Claim Check Transformer</emphasis>. Convenient namespace-based mechanisms are available to configure them.
    </para>
    
    <section id="claim-check-in">
    	<title>Incoming Claim Check Transformer</title>
    	
    	<para>
    	An <emphasis>Incoming Claim Check Transformer</emphasis> will transform an incoming Message by storing it in the Message Store 
    	identified by its <code>message-store</code> attribute.
    	
    	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:claim-check-in id="checkin"
        input-channel="checkinChannel"
        message-store="testMessageStore"
        output-channel="output"/>]]></programlisting>

		In the above configuration the Message that is received on the <code>input-channel</code> will be persisted to the 
		Message Store identified with the <code>message-store</code> attribute and indexed with generated ID. That ID is the
        Claim Check for that Message. 
		The Claim Check will also become the payload of the new (transformed) Message that will be sent to the <code>output-channel</code>. 
    	</para>
    	
    	<para>
    	Now, lets assume that at some point you do need access to the actual Message. You can of course access the Message Store 
    	manually and get the contents of the Message, or you can use the same approach as before except now you will be transforming 
    	the Claim Check to the actual Message by using an <emphasis>Outgoing Claim Check Transformer</emphasis>.
    	</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="claim-check-out">
    	<title>Outgoing Claim Check Transformer</title>
    	
    	<para>
    	An <emphasis>Outgoing Claim Check Transformer</emphasis> allows you to transform a Message with a Claim Check payload
    	into a Message with the original content as its payload.
    	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<claim-check-out id="checkout"
        input-channel="checkoutChannel"
        message-store="testMessageStore"
        output-channel="output"/>]]></programlisting>

		In the above configuration, the Message that is received on the <code>input-channel</code> should have a Claim Check as its payload 
		and the <emphasis>Outgoing Claim Check Transformer</emphasis> will transform it into a Message with the original payload by simply
		querying the Message store for a Message identified by the provided Claim Check. It then sends the newly checked-out Message to the
		<code>output-channel</code>.
    	</para>
    	<para><emphasis>Claim Once</emphasis></para>
    	<para>
    	There are scenarios when a particular message must be claimed only once. Take the airplane luggage check-in/out process. 
    	Checking-in your luggage on the departure and and then claiming it on the arrival is a classic example of such scenario. 
    	Once the luggage was claimed it can no longer be claimed again without further check-in. To accommodate such cases we 
    	introduced <code>remove-message</code> boolean attribute on <code>claim-check-out</code> transformer. This attribute is 
    	set to <code>false</code> by default, however if set to <code>true</code>, the claimed Message will also be removed 
    	from the MessageStore and can no longer be claimed again.
    	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<claim-check-out id="checkout"
        input-channel="checkoutChannel"
        message-store="testMessageStore"
        output-channel="output"
        remove-message="true"/>]]></programlisting>
    	</para>
    </section>
    <para>
    Although we rarely care about the details of the claim checks as long as they work, it is still worth knowing that
    the current implementation of the actual Claim Check (the pointer) in Spring Integration is a UUID to ensure uniqueness.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    <emphasis>A word on Message Store</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    <classname>org.springframework.integration.store.MessageStore</classname> is a strategy interface for storing and retrieving messages. 
    Spring Integration provides two convenient implementations of it. <classname>SimpleMessageStore</classname>: an in-memory, Map-based 
    implementation (the default, good for testing) and <classname>JdbcMessageStore</classname>: an implementation that uses a relational
    database via JDBC.
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
