<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="groovy" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Groovy support</title>

  <para>With Spring Integration 2.0 we've added Groovy support allowing you to
  use the Groovy scripting language to provide the logic for
  various integration components similar to the way the Spring Expression Language
  (SpEL) is supported for routing, transformation and other integration
  concerns. For more information about Groovy please refer to the Groovy
  documentation which you can find
  on the <ulink url="http://groovy.codehaus.org">project website</ulink></para>

  <section id="groovy-config">
    <title>Groovy configuration</title>

    <para>Depending on the complexity of your integration requirements Groovy
    scripts could be provided inline as CDATA in XML configuration or as a
    reference to a file containing the Groovy script. To enable Groovy support
    Spring Integration defines a
    <classname>GroovyScriptExecutingMessageProcessor</classname> which will
    bind the  Message Payload as a
    <code>payload</code> variable and the Message Headers as a <code>headers</code>
    variable within the script execution context. All that is left for you to do is
    write a script that uses those
    variables. Below are a couple of sample configurations:</para>

    <para><emphasis>Filter</emphasis> <programlisting language="xml">&lt;int:filter input-channel="referencedScriptInput"&gt;
   &lt;int-groovy:script location="some/path/to/groovy/file/GroovyFilterTests.groovy"/&gt;
&lt;/int:filter&gt;

&lt;int:filter input-channel="inlineScriptInput"&gt;
     &lt;int-groovy:script&gt;&lt;![CDATA[
     return payload == 'good'
   ]]&gt;&lt;/int-groovy:script&gt;
&lt;/int:filter&gt;</programlisting>

    Here, you see that the script can be included inline
    or via the <code>location</code> attribute using the groovy namespace
    support.</para>

    <para>Other supported elements are <emphasis>router, service-activator,
    transformer, and splitter. The configuration would look identical to that
    above other than the main element's name.</emphasis></para>

    <para>Another interesting aspect of using Groovy support is the framework's
    ability to update (reload) scripts without restarting the Application
    Context. To accomplish this, all you need to do is specify
    the <code>refresh-check-delay</code> attribute on the <emphasis>script</emphasis>
    element.

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;int-groovy:script location="..." refresh-check-delay="5000"/&gt;</programlisting>

    In the above example any invocations that occur within the 5 seconds immediately following the
    updating of the script would still be using the old script. However, any invocation that occurs
    after those 5 seconds have elapsed will
    result in execution of the new script. This is a good example where 'near real
    time' is acceptable.

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;int-groovy:script location="..." refresh-check-delay="0"/&gt;</programlisting>

    In the above example the context will be updated with any script modifications
    as soon as such modification occurs. Basically this is an example of
    'real-time' configuration and might not be the most efficient option (but could be useful during development).

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;int-groovy:script location="..." refresh-check-delay="-1"/&gt;</programlisting>

    Any negative number value means the script will never be refreshed after
    initial initialization of the application context. This is the default behavior.
    In this case, the "dynamic" aspect of Groovy is not being used, but the syntax
    might be the primary reason that Groovy has been chosen in the first place.
    <important>Inline defined scripts can not be reloaded.</important></para>
    
    <para><emphasis>Custom bindings</emphasis> </para>
    
    <para>
    You already know that by default, 'payload' and 'headers' will be bound as Groovy binding variables.
	However, some times in order to take the most out of Groovy you may want to customize Groovy bindings 
	(e.g., include extra variables pointing to some scalar values or bind some beans as variables).
   To support this requirement we have defined a simple strategy: ScriptVariableGenerator.
  <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface ScriptVariableGenerator {
	
	Map<String, Object> generateScriptVariables(Message<?> message);
	
}]]></programlisting>

	As you can see the only method to implement is <code>generateScriptVariables(Message)</code>. It takes the Message
	as an argument. That allows you to use data available in the Message payload and/or headers. The return value is
	the Map of variables that will be bound to the script's evaluation context. This method will be called every time
	the script is executed, corresponding to the processing of that particular Message. We also provide a
	default implementation and namespace based configuration for simple bindings via &lt;variable&gt; sub-elements (see below):
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<groovy:script location="foo/bar/MyScript.groovy">
	<groovy:variable name="foo" value="foo"/>
	<groovy:variable name="bar" value="bar"/>
	<groovy:variable name="date" ref="date"/>
</groovy:script>]]></programlisting>

	As you can see similar to other constructs in Spring, when binding each of these variables you can either provide a
	scalar value or reference another bean in the Application Context.
    </para>
    <para>
     If you need more control over how a particular variable is generated, then all you need to do is 
     provide your own implementation of ScriptVariableGenerator and reference it with the <code>script-variable-generator</code>
	attribute:
   <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-groovy:script location="foo/bar/MyScript.groovy"
				script-variable-generator="variableGenerator"/>

<bean id="variableGenerator" class="foo.bar.MyScriptVariableGenerator"/>]]></programlisting>
	
	  <important>
	  The <code>script-variable-generator</code> attribute and &lt;variable&gt; sub-element(s) are mutually exclusive. 
	  You can use at most one of them. Also, the <code>script-variable-generator</code> and &lt;variable&gt; sub-elements
	  cannot be used with an inline script, but rather only when pointing to the script via the <code>location</code> attribute.
	  </important>
	  
	  If you need to customize the Groovy object itself, beyond setting variables, you can reference
	  a bean that implementats <code>org.springframework.scripting.groovy.GroovyObjectCustomizer</code> via the
	  <code>customizer</code> attribute. For example, this might be useful if you want to configure a domain-specific
	  language (DSL) by modifying the MetaClass and registering functions to be available within the script.
	  
	   <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:service-activator input-channel="groovyChannel">
    <int-groovy:script location="foo/SomeScript.groovy" customizer="groovyCustomizer"/>
</int:service-activator>

<beans:bean id="groovyCustomizer" class="org.foo.MyGroovyObjectCustomizer"/>]]></programlisting>

	  Setting a custom GroovyObjectCustomizer is not mutually exclusive with &lt;variable&gt; sub-elements or
	  the <code>script-variable-generator</code> attribute. It can also be provided when defining an inline script.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="groovy-control-bus">
    <title>Control Bus</title>

    <para>As described in (<ulink
    url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/ControlBus.html">EIP</ulink>), the idea
    behind the Control Bus is that the same messaging system can be used for
    monitoring and managing the components within the framework as is used for
    "application-level" messaging. In Spring Integration we build upon the
    adapters described above so that it's possible to send Messages as a means
    of invoking exposed operations. One option for those operations is Groovy scripts.
    <programlisting language="xml"> &lt;int-groovy:control-bus input-channel="operationChannel"/&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>The Control Bus has an input channel that can be accessed for
    invoking operations on the beans in the application context.</para>

    <para>The Groovy Control Bus executes messages on the input channel as
    Groovy scripts. It takes a message, compiles the body to a Script,
    customizes it with a GroovyObjectCustomizer, and then executes it. The
    Control Bus' customizer exposes all the beans in the application context
    that are annotated with @ManagedResource, implement Spring's
    Lifecycle interface or extend Spring's CustomizableThreadCreator base class
    (e.g. several of the TaskExecutor and TaskScheduler implementations).</para>
    
    <para>
     If you need to further customize the Groovy objects, you can also provide a reference to a bean
     that implements <code>org.springframework.scripting.groovy.GroovyObjectCustomizer</code> via
     the <code>customizer</code> attribute.
	  
	   <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-groovy:control-bus input-channel="input"
        output-channel="output"
        customizer="groovyCustomizer"/>
				   
<beans:bean id="groovyCustomizer" class="org.foo.MyGroovyObjectCustomizer"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
