<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="router"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Router</title>

  <section id="router-implementations">
    <title>Router Implementations</title>
    <para>
      Since content-based routing often requires some domain-specific logic, most use-cases will require
      Spring Integration's options for delegating to POJOs using the XML namespace support and/or Annotations.
      Both of these are discussed below, but first we present a couple implementations that are available
      out-of-the-box since they fulfill common requirements.
    </para>
    <section id="router-implementations-payloadtyperouter">
      <title>PayloadTypeRouter</title>
      <para>
        A <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname> will send Messages to the channel as defined by payload-type
        mappings.
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="payloadTypeRouter" class="org.springframework.integration.router.PayloadTypeRouter">
    <property name="channelIdentifierMap">
        <map>
            <entry key="java.lang.String" value-ref="stringChannel"/>
            <entry key="java.lang.Integer" value-ref="integerChannel"/>
        </map>
    </property>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
      Configuration of the <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname> is also supported via the namespace provided by Spring Integration (see <xref linkend="configuration-namespace"/>),
      which essentially simplifies configuration by combining the <code>&lt;router/&gt;</code> configuration and its corresponding implementation
      defined using a <code>&lt;bean/&gt;</code> element
      into a single and more concise configuration element.
      The example below demonstrates a <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname> configuration which is equivalent to the one above using the namespace support:
      </para>
      <para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<payload-type-router input-channel="routingChannel">
  <mapping type="java.lang.String" channel="stringChannel" />
  <mapping type="java.lang.Integer" channel="integerChannel" />
</payload-type-router>]]></programlisting>
  </para>
    </section>
    <section id="router-implementations-headervaluerouter">
      <title>HeaderValueRouter</title>
      <para>
        A <classname>HeaderValueRouter</classname> will send Messages to the channel based on the individual header value mappings.
        When a <code>HeaderValueRouter</code> is created it is initialized with the <emphasis>name</emphasis> of the header to be evaluated.
        The <emphasis>value</emphasis> of the header could be one of two things:</para>
      <para>
        1. Arbitrary value
     </para>
     <para>
        2. Channel name
     </para>
     <para>
      If arbitrary then additional mappings for these header values to channel names is required, otherwise no additional configuration is needed.
      </para>
      <para>
      Spring Integration provides a simple namespace-based XML configuration to configure a <classname>HeaderValueRouter</classname>.
      The example below demonstrates two types of namespace-based configuration for the <classname>HeaderValueRouter</classname>.
      </para>
      <para><emphasis>1. Configuration where mapping of header values to channels is required</emphasis> </para>
      <para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<header-value-router input-channel="routingChannel" header-name="testHeader">
  <mapping value="someHeaderValue" channel="channelA" />
  <mapping value="someOtherHeaderValue" channel="channelB" />
</header-value-router>]]></programlisting>
  </para>
  <para>
  During the resolution process this router may encounter channel resolution failures, causing an
  exception. If you want to suppress such exceptions and send unresolved messages to the default output channel 
  (identified with the <code>default-output-channel</code> attribute) set <code>ignore-channel-name-resolution-failures</code> to true. 
  Normally, messages for which the header value is not explicitly mapped to a channel will be sent to the <code>default-output-channel</code>.
  However, in cases where the header value is mapped to a channel name but the channel cannot be resolved, setting
  the <code>ignore-channel-name-resolution-failures</code>
  attribute to true will result in routing such messages to the <code>default-output-channel</code>.
  </para>
  
  <para> <emphasis>2. Configuration where mapping of header values to channel names 
  is not required since header values themselves represent channel names</emphasis> </para>
      <para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<header-value-router input-channel="routingChannel" header-name="testHeader"/>]]></programlisting>
  </para>
  
  <note>
      The two router implementations shown above share some common attributes, such as <code>default-output-channel</code> and <code>resolution-required</code>.
      If <code>resolution-required</code> is set to true, and the router is unable to determine a target channel (e.g. there is
      no matching payload for a PayloadTypeRouter and no <code>default-output-channel</code> has been specified), then an Exception
      will be thrown.
    </note>
    </section>
    
    
    
    <section id="router-implementations-recipientlistrouter">
      <title>RecipientListRouter</title>
      <para>
        A <classname>RecipientListRouter</classname> will send each received Message to a statically defined
        list of Message Channels:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="recipientListRouter" class="org.springframework.integration.router.RecipientListRouter">
    <property name="channels">
        <list>
            <ref bean="channel1"/>
            <ref bean="channel2"/>
            <ref bean="channel3"/>
        </list>
    </property>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
     <para>
     Spring Integration also provides namespace support for the <classname>RecipientListRouter</classname> configuration (see <xref linkend="configuration-namespace"/>)
      as the example below demonstrates.
      </para>
      <para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<recipient-list-router id="customRouter" input-channel="routingChannel"
        timeout="1234"
        ignore-send-failures="true"
        apply-sequence="true">
  <recipient channel="channel1"/>
  <recipient channel="channel2"/>
</recipient-list-router>]]></programlisting>
  </para>
  <note>
      The 'apply-sequence' flag here has the same effect as it does for a publish-subscribe-channel,
      and like a publish-subscribe-channel, it is disabled by default on the recipient-list-router. Refer to
      <xref linkend="channel-configuration-pubsubchannel"/> for more information.
  </note>
  
  <para>
  Another convenient option when configuring a <classname>RecipientListRouter</classname> is to use Spring Expression Language (SpEL) support
  as selectors for individual recipient channels. This is similar to using a Filter at the beginning of 'chain' to act as a "Selective Consumer".
  However, in this case, it's all combined rather concisely into the router's configuration.
  
  <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:recipient-list-router id="customRouter" input-channel="routingChannel">
	<int:recipient channel="channel1" selector-expression="payload.equals('foo')"/>
	<int:recipient channel="channel2" selector-expression="headers.contains('bar')"/>
</int:recipient-list-router>]]></programlisting>

	In the above configuration a SpEL expression identified by the <code>selector-expression</code> attribute will be evaluated to determine if this recipient 
 	should be included in the recipient list for a given input Message. The evaluation result of the expression must be a boolean. If this 
 	attribute is not defined, the channel will always be among the list of recipients.
  </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="router-implementations-exception-router">
  	<title>Routing and Error handling</title>
  
  	<para>
  	Spring Integration also provides a special type router <classname>ErrorMessageExceptionTypeRouter</classname>  for routing 
  	Error Messages (a Message with <code>payload</code> of type <classname>Throwable</classname>).
    <classname>ErrorMessageExceptionTypeRouter</classname> is very similar to the <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname>. 
    In fact they are almost identical. The only difference is that while <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname> navigates 
    the instance hierarchy of an payload instance (e.g., <code>payload.getClass().getSuperclass()</code>) to find the most 
    specific type/channel mappings, the <classname>ErrorMessageExceptionTypeRouter</classname> navigates the hierarchy of 
    'exception causes' (e.g., <code>payload.getCause()</code>) to find the most specific <classname>Throwable</classname> type/channel mappings.
  	</para>
  	<para>
  	Below is a sample configuration for <classname>ErrorMessageExceptionTypeRouter</classname>
  	
  	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<router input-channel="errorChannel" default-output-channel="defaultErrorChannel">
	<mapping value="org.FooException" channel="fooChannel" />
	<mapping value="org.BarException" channel="barChannel" />
	<beans:bean class="org.springframework.integration.router.ErrorMessageExceptionTypeRouter"/>
</router>

<channel id="fooChannel" />
<channel id="barChannel" />]]></programlisting>
  	</para>
  	<para>
  	In the future we'll consider a more convenient namespace based support similar to 'header-value-router' and 'payload-type-router'
  	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="router-namespace">
  	<title>Configuring Router</title>
  	<section>
    <title>Configuring a Content Based Router with XML</title>
    <para>
    The "router" element provides a simple way to connect a router to an input channel and also accepts the
      optional <code>default-output-channel</code> attribute. The <code>ref</code> attribute references the bean name of a custom Router implementation
      (extending <classname>AbstractMessageRouter</classname>):
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<router ref="payloadTypeRouter" input-channel="input1" default-output-channel="defaultOutput1"/>

<router ref="recipientListRouter" input-channel="input2" default-output-channel="defaultOutput2"/>

<router ref="customRouter" input-channel="input3" default-output-channel="defaultOutput3"/>

<beans:bean id="customRouterBean class="org.foo.MyCustomRouter"/>]]></programlisting>

      Alternatively, <code>ref</code> may point to a simple POJO that contains the @Router annotation (see below), or the
      <code>ref</code> may be combined with an explicit <code>method</code> name. Specifying a <code>method</code> applies the same behavior 
      described in the @Router annotation section below.
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<router input-channel="input" ref="somePojo" method="someMethod"/>]]></programlisting>
      Using a <code>ref</code> attribute is generally recommended if the custom router implementation is referenced in other
      <code>&lt;router&gt;</code> definitions. However if the custom router implementation should be scoped to a
      single definition of the <code>&lt;router&gt;</code>, you may provide an inner bean definition:
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<router method="someMethod" input-channel="input3" default-output-channel="defaultOutput3">
  <beans:bean class="org.foo.MyCustomRouter"/>
</router>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Using both the <code>ref</code> attribute and an inner handler definition in the same <code>&lt;router&gt;</code> configuration
        is not allowed, as it creates an ambiguous condition, and an Exception will be thrown.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
    	<emphasis>Routers and the Spring Expression Language (SpEL)</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    Sometimes the routing logic may be simple and writing a separate class for it and configuring it as a bean may seem 
    like overkill. As of Spring Integration 2.0 we offer an alternative where you can now use 
    <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/expressions.htm">SpEL</ulink> 
    to implement simple computations that previously required a custom POJO router.
    
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:router input-channel="inChannel" expression="payload + 'Channel'"/>]]></programlisting>
    In the above configuration the result channel will be computed by the SpEL expression which simply concatenates the value 
    of the <code>payload</code> with the literal String 'Channel'.  
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Another value of SpEL for configuring routers is that an expression can actually return a <classname>Collection</classname>, 
    effectively making every <code>&lt;router&gt;</code> a <emphasis>Recipient List Router</emphasis>. Whenever the expression returns 
    multiple channel values the Message will be forwarded to each channel.
    
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:router input-channel="inChannel" expression="headers.channels"/>]]></programlisting>
    
    In the above configuration, if the Message includes a header with the name 'channels' the value of which is a 
    <classname>List</classname> of channel names then the Message will be sent to each channel in the list.
    
    You may also find <emphasis>Collection Projection</emphasis> and <emphasis>Collection Selection</emphasis> 
    expressions useful to select multiple channels. 
    See <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/expressions.html#d0e12084">"http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/expressions.html#d0e12084"</ulink>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="router-annotation">
    <title>Configuring a Router with Annotations</title>
    <para>
      When using <interfacename>@Router</interfacename> to annotate a method, the method may return either a
      <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> or <classname>String</classname> type. In the latter case,
      the endpoint will resolve the channel name as it does for the default output channel. Additionally, the method may return
      either a single value or a collection. If a collection is returned, the reply message will be sent to multiple
      channels. To summarize, the following method signatures are all valid.
      <programlisting language="java">@Router
public MessageChannel route(Message message) {...}

@Router
public List&lt;MessageChannel&gt; route(Message message) {...}

@Router
public String route(Foo payload) {...}

@Router
public List&lt;String&gt; route(Foo payload) {...}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to payload-based routing, a Message may be routed based on metadata available within the
      message header as either a property or attribute. In this case, a method annotated with <interfacename>@Router</interfacename>
      may include a parameter annotated with <interfacename>@Header</interfacename> which is mapped to a header value as illustrated 
      below and documented in <xref linkend="annotations"/>.
       
      <programlisting language="java">@Router
public List&lt;String&gt; route(@Header("orderStatus") OrderStatus status)</programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
  	
  </section>
  
  
  <note>
    For routing of XML-based Messages, including XPath support, see <xref linkend="xml"/>.
  </note>

  <section id="dynamic-routers">
    <title>Dynamic Routers</title>
    <para>
    So as you can see, Spring Integration provides quite a few different router configurations for common
    <emphasis>content-based routing</emphasis> use cases as well as the option of implementing custom routers as POJOs.
    For example <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname> provides a simple way to configure a router which computes <code>channels</code>
    based on the <code>payload type</code> of the incoming Message while <classname>HeaderValueRouter</classname> provides the
    same convenience in configuring a router which computes <code>channels</code> by evaluating the value
    of a particular Message Header. There are also <emphasis>expression-based</emphasis> (SpEL) routers where the <code>channel</code>
    is determined based on evaluating an expression. Thus, these type of routers exhibit some dynamic characteristics.
    </para>
    <para>
    However these routers all require <emphasis>static configuration</emphasis>. Even in the case of
    expression-based routers, the expression itself is defined as part of the router configuration which means that
    <emphasis>the same expression operating on the same value will always result in the computation of the same channel</emphasis>.
    This is acceptable in most cases since such routes are well defined and therefore predictable. But there are times when we
    need to change router configurations dynamically so message flows may be routed to a different channel.
    </para>
    <para> <emphasis>Example:</emphasis> </para>
    <para>
    You might want to bring down some part of your system for maintenance and temporarily re-reroute
    messages to a different message flow. Or you may want to introduce more granularity to your message flow by adding another
    route to handle a more concrete type of java.lang.Number (in the case of <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname>).
    </para>
    <para>
    Unfortunately with static router configuration to accomplish this you would have to bring down your entire application,
    change the configuration of the router (change routes) and bring it back up. This is obviously not the solution.
    </para>
    <para> 
    The <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/DynamicRouter.html">Dynamic Router</ulink> 
    pattern describes the mechanisms by which one can change/configure routers dynamically without
    bringing down the system or individual routers. 
    </para>
    <para>
    Before we get into the specifics of how this is accomplished in Spring Integration let's quickly summarize the
    typical flow of the router, which consists of 3 simple steps:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 1</emphasis> - Compute <code>channel identifier</code> which is a value calculated by the
          router once it receives the Message. Typically it is a <classname>String</classname> or and instance of the actual
          <classname>MessageChannel</classname>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 2</emphasis> - Resolve <code>channel identifier</code> to <code>channel name</code>. We'll describe
          specifics of this process in a moment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 3</emphasis> - Resolve <code>channel name</code> to the actual <classname>MessageChannel</classname> </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
    There is not much that can be done with regard to dynamic routing if Step 1 results in the actual instance of the
    <classname>MessageChannel</classname> simply because the <classname>MessageChannel</classname> is the <emphasis>final product</emphasis> of any
    router's job. However, if Step 1 results in a <code>channel identifier</code> that is not an instance of <classname>MessageChannel</classname>,
    then there are quite a few possibilities to influence the process of deriving the <classname>Message Channel</classname>.
    Lets look at couple of the examples in the context of the 3 steps mentioned above: 
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Payload Type Router</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<payload-type-router input-channel="routingChannel">
  <mapping type="java.lang.String" channel="channel1" />
  <mapping type="java.lang.Integer" channel="channel2" />
</payload-type-router>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
    Within the context of the Payload Type Router the 3 steps mentioned above would be realized as:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 1</emphasis> - Compute <code>channel identifier</code> which is the fully qualified name of the payload type
          (e.g., java.lang.String).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 2</emphasis> - Resolve <code>channel identifier</code> to <code>channel name</code> where
           the result of the previous step is used to select the appropriate value from the <emphasis>payload type mapping</emphasis>
           defined via <code>mapping</code> element.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 3</emphasis> - Resolve <code>channel name</code> to the actual instance of the
          <classname>MessageChannel</classname> where using <classname>ChannelResolver</classname>, the router will obtain a
          reference to a bean (which is hopefully a <classname>MessageChannel</classname>) identified by the result of the
          previous step.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      In other words each step feeds the next step until the process completes.
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Header Value Router</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<header-value-router input-channel="inputChannel" header-name="testHeader">
  <mapping value="foo" channel="fooChannel" />
  <mapping value="bar" channel="barChannel" />
</header-value-router>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
    Similar to the PayloadTypeRouter:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 1</emphasis> - Compute <code>channel identifier</code> which is the value of the header identified by the
          <code>header-name</code> attribute.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 2</emphasis> - Resolve <code>channel identifier</code> to <code>channel name</code> where
           the result of the previous step is used to select the appropriate value from the <emphasis>general mapping</emphasis>
           defined via <code>mapping</code> element.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step 3</emphasis> - Resolve <code>channel name</code> to the actual instance of the
          <classname>MessageChannel</classname> where using <classname>ChannelResolver</classname>, the router will obtain a
          reference to a bean (which is hopefully a <classname>MessageChannel</classname>) identified by the result of the
          previous step.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    The above two configurations of two different router types look almost identical.
    However if we look at the alternate configuration of the <classname>HeaderValueRouter</classname> we clearly see that
    there is no <code>mapping</code> sub element:
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<header-value-router input-channel="inputChannel" header-name="testHeader">]]></programlisting>
    But the configuration is still perfectly valid. So the natural question is what about the mapping in the Step 2?
    </para>
    <para>
    What this means is that Step 2 is now an optional step. If mapping is not defined then the <code>channel identifier</code>
    value computed in Step 1 will automatically be treated as the <code>channel name</code> which will now be resolved to the
    actual <classname>MessageChannel</classname> in the Step 3. What it also means is that Step 2 is one of the key steps to
    provide dynamic characteristics to the routers, since it introduces a process which
    <emphasis>allows you to change the way 'channel identifier' resolves to 'channel name'</emphasis>,
    thus influencing the process of determining the final instance of the <classname>MessageChannel</classname> from the initial
    <code>channel identifier</code>. 
    </para>
    <para><emphasis>For Example:</emphasis> </para>
    <para>
    In the above configuration let's assume that the <code>testHeader</code> value is 'kermit' which is now a <code>channel identifier</code>
     (Step 1). Since there is no mapping in this router, resolving this <code>channel identifier</code> to a <code>channel name</code>
     (Step 2) is impossible and this <code>channel identifier</code> is now treated as <code>channel name</code>. However what if
     there was a mapping but for a different value? The end result would still be the same and that is:
     <emphasis>if new value cannot be determined through the process of resolving the 'channel identifier' to a 'channel name',
     such 'channel identifier' becomes 'channel name'.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    So all that is left is for Step 3 to resolve the <code>channel name</code> ('kermit') to an actual instance of the
    <classname>MessageChannel</classname> identified by this name. That will be done via the default
    <interface>ChannelResolver</interface> implementation which is a <classname>BeanFactoryChannelResolver</classname>. It
    basically does a bean lookup for the name provided. So now all messages which contain the header/value pair as <code>testHeader=kermit</code>
    are going to be routed to a <classname>MessageChannel</classname> whose bean name (id) is 'kermit'.
    </para>
    <para>
    But what if you want to route these messages to the 'simpson' channel? Obviously changing a static configuration will work,
    but will also require bringing your system down. However if you had access to the <code>channel identifier</code> map, then you
    could just introduce a new mapping where the header/value pair is now <code>kermit=simpson</code>, thus allowing Step 2 to treat
    'kermit' as a <code>channel identifier</code> while resolving it to 'simpson' as the <code>channel name</code> .
    </para>
    <para>
    The same obviously applies for <classname>PayloadTypeRouter</classname>  where you can now remap or remove a particular <emphasis>payload type
    mapping</emphasis>. In fact, it applies to every other router including <emphasis>expression-based</emphasis> routers since their computed values
    will now have a chance to go through Step 2 to be additionally resolved to the actual <code>channel name</code>.
    </para>
    <para>
    In Spring Integration 2.0 the routers hierarchy underwent significant refactoring so that now any router that is a subclass of the
    <classname>AbstractMessageRouter</classname> (which includes all framework defined routers) is a Dynamic Router simply because the
    <code>channelIdentiferMap</code> is defined at the <classname>AbstractMessageRouter</classname> level. That map's setter method is
    exposed as a public method along with 'setChannelMapping' and 'removeChannelMapping' methods. These allow you to change/add/remove
    router mappings at runtime as long as you have a reference to the router itself. It also means that you could expose these same
    configuration options via JMX (see <xref linkend="jmx"/>) or the Spring Integration ControlBus (see <xref linkend="control-bus"/>) functionality. 
    </para>

    <para>
    <emphasis>Control Bus</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    One way to manage the router mappings is through the <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/ControlBus.html">Control Bus</ulink>
    pattern which exposes a Control Channel where you can send
    control messages to manage and monitor Spring Integration components, including routers.
    For more information about the Control Bus see <xref linkend="control-bus"/>. Typically you would send a control message asking to invoke a
    particular operation on a particular managed component (e.g., router). The two managed operations (methods) that are
     specific to changing the router resolution process are:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>public void setChannelMapping(String channelIdentifier, String channelName)</code> -
          will allow you to add a new or modify an existing mapping between <code>channel identifier</code> and <code>channel name</code></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>public void removeChannelMapping(String channelIdentifier)</code> -
          will allow you to remove a particular channel mapping, thus disconnecting the relationship between
          <code>channel identifier</code> and <code>channel name</code> </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
    You can also expose a router instance with Spring's JMS support and then use your favorite JMX client (e.g., JConsole) to
    manage those operations (methods) for changing the router's configuration. For more information on Spring Integration
    management and monitoring please visit <xref linkend="jmx"/>.
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
