<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="aggregator"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Aggregator</title>

  <section id="aggregator-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Basically a mirror-image of the Splitter, the Aggregator is a type
    of Message Handler that receives multiple Messages and combines them into
    a single Message. In fact, an Aggregator is often a downstream consumer in a
    pipeline that includes a Splitter.</para>

    <para>Technically, the Aggregator is more complex than a Splitter, because
    it is stateful as it must hold the Messages to be aggregated and determine
    when the complete group of Messages is ready to be aggregated. In order to do
    this it requires a <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-functionality">
    <title>Functionality</title>

    <para>The Aggregator combines a group of related messages, by correlating
    and storing them, until the group is deemed complete. At that point, the
    Aggregator will create a single message by processing the whole group, and
    will send the aggregated message as output.</para>

    <para>Implementing an Aggregator requires providing the logic
    to perform the aggregation (i.e., the creation of a single message
    from many). Two related concepts are correlation and
    release.</para>

    <para>Correlation determines how messages are grouped for aggregation.
    In Spring Integration correlation is done by default based on the
    <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.CORRELATION_ID</code> message
    header. Messages with the same <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.CORRELATION_ID</code> will be grouped
    together. However, the correlation strategy may be customized to allow
    other ways of specifying how the messages should be grouped together by
    implementing a <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename> (see below).</para>

    <para>To determine the point at which a group of messages is ready to be processed, a
    <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> is consulted.
    The default release strategy for the Aggregator will release a group when all
    messages included in a sequence are present, based on the
    <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.SEQUENCE_SIZE</code> header.
    This default strategy may be overridden by providing a reference to a
    custom <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> implementation.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-api">
    <title>Programming model</title>

    <para>The Aggregation API consists of a number of classes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The interface <interfacename>MessageGroupProcessor</interfacename>, and
        its subclasses:
        <classname>MethodInvokingAggregatingMessageGroupProcessor</classname> and
        <classname>ExpressionEvaluatingMessageGroupProcessor</classname></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> interface and its default
        implementation <classname>SequenceSizeReleaseStrategy</classname></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename> interface and its default
        implementation <classname>HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy</classname></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>AggregatingMessageHandler</title>

      <para>The <classname>AggregatingMessageHandler</classname> (subclass of
      <classname>AbstractCorrelatingMessageHandler</classname>) is a
      <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> implementation, encapsulating the common
      functionalities of an Aggregator (and other correlating use cases),
      which are: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>correlating messages into a group to be aggregated</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>maintaining those messages in a <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename> until the group
            can be released</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>deciding when the group can be released</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>aggregating the released group into a single message</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>recognizing and responding to an expired group</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> The responsibility of deciding how the messages should
      be grouped together is delegated to a <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename>
      instance. The responsibility of deciding whether the message group can
      be released is delegated to a <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename>
      instance.</para>

      <para>Here is a brief highlight of the base
      <classname>AbstractAggregatingMessageGroupProcessor</classname> (the
      responsibility of implementing the <code>aggregatePayloads</code> method is left to
      the developer):</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public abstract class AbstractAggregatingMessageGroupProcessor
              implements MessageGroupProcessor {

    protected Map<String, Object> aggregateHeaders(MessageGroup group) {
        // default implementation exists
    }

    protected abstract Object aggregatePayloads(MessageGroup group, Map<String, Object> defaultHeaders);

}]]></programlisting>

       The <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename> is owned by the

      <classname>AbstractCorrelatingMessageHandler</classname>

       and it has a default value based on the <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.CORRELATION_ID</code> message header:

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public AbstractCorrelatingMessageHandler(MessageGroupProcessor processor, MessageGroupStore store,
        CorrelationStrategy correlationStrategy, ReleaseStrategy releaseStrategy) {
    ...
    this.correlationStrategy = correlationStrategy == null ?
        new HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy(IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.CORRELATION_ID) : correlationStrategy;
    this.releaseStrategy = releaseStrategy == null ? new SequenceSizeReleaseStrategy() : releaseStrategy;
    ...
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>As for actual processing of the message group, the default implementation is the
      <classname>DefaultAggregatingMessageGroupProcessor</classname>. It creates a
      single Message whose payload is a List of the payloads received for a
      given group. This works well for simple Scatter Gather implementations with either a Splitter, Publish
      Subscribe Channel, or Recipient List Router upstream.</para>

      <note>
        <para>When using a Publish Subscribe Channel or Recipient List Router
        in this type of scenario, be sure to enable the flag to
        <code>apply-sequence</code>. That will add the necessary
        headers (CORRELATION_ID, SEQUENCE_NUMBER and SEQUENCE_SIZE). That
        behavior is enabled by default for Splitters in Spring Integration,
        but it is not enabled for the Publish Subscribe Channel or Recipient
        List Router because those components may be used in a variety of
        contexts in which these headers are not necessary.</para>
      </note>

      <para>When implementing a specific aggregator strategy for an application,
      a developer can extend
      <classname>AbstractAggregatingMessageGroupProcessor</classname> and implement the
      <code>aggregatePayloads</code> method. However, there are better solutions, less
      coupled to the API, for implementing the aggregation logic which can be configured easily
      either through XML or through annotations.</para>

      <para>In general, any POJO can implement the
      aggregation algorithm if it provides a method that
      accepts a single <interfacename>java.util.List</interfacename> as an argument
      (parameterized lists are supported as well). This method will be invoked for aggregating
      messages as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a <interfacename>java.util.List&lt;T&gt;</interfacename>, and the
          parameter type T is assignable to <interfacename>Message</interfacename>, then the whole list of
          messages accumulated for aggregation will be sent to the aggregator</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a non-parameterized <interfacename>java.util.List</interfacename> or the
          parameter type is not assignable to <interfacename>Message</interfacename>, then the method will
          receive the payloads of the accumulated messages</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if the return type is not assignable to <interfacename>Message</interfacename>, then it will
          be treated as the payload for a Message that will be created
          automatically by the framework.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>In the interest of code simplicity, and promoting best practices
        such as low coupling, testability, etc., the preferred way of
        implementing the aggregation logic is through a POJO, and using the
        XML or annotation support for configuring it in the application.</para>
      </note>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>ReleaseStrategy</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> interface is defined as
      follows:</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface ReleaseStrategy {

  boolean canRelease(MessageGroup group);

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>In general, any POJO can implement the
      completion decision logic if it provides a method that accepts a single
      <interfacename>java.util.List</interfacename> as an argument (parameterized lists
      are supported as well), and returns a boolean value. This method will be
      invoked after the arrival of each new message, to decide whether the group
      is complete or not, as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a <interfacename>java.util.List&lt;T&gt;</interfacename>, and the
          parameter type T is assignable to <interfacename>Message</interfacename>, then the whole list of
          messages accumulated in the group will be sent to the method</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a non-parametrized <interfacename>java.util.List</interfacename> or the
          parameter type is not assignable to <interfacename>Message</interfacename>, then the method will
          receive the payloads of the accumulated messages</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the method must return true if the message group is ready for
          aggregation, and false otherwise.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      For example:

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class MyReleaseStrategy {

    @ReleaseStrategy
    public boolean canMessagesBeReleased(List<Message<?>>) {...}
}]]></programlisting>

<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class MyReleaseStrategy {

    @ReleaseStrategy
    public boolean canMessagesBeReleased(List<String>) {...}
}]]></programlisting>

<para>
As you can see based on the above signatures, the POJO-based Release Strategy will be passed a
<classname>Collection</classname> of not-yet-released Messages
(if you need access to the whole <classname>Message</classname>) or a <classname>Collection</classname> of payload objects
(if the type parameter is
anything other than <classname>Message</classname>). Typically this would satisfy the majority of use cases. However if,
for some reason, you need to access the full <classname>MessageGroup</classname>
then you should simply provide an implementation of the <classname>ReleaseStrategy</classname> interface.
</para>
<caution>
	<para>
	When handling potentially large groups, it is important to understand how these methods are invoked because the release
	strategy may be invoked multiple times before the group is released. The most efficient is an implementation of
	<interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> because the aggregator can invoke it directly. The second most
	efficient is a POJO method with a <code>Collection&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt;</code> parameter type. The least efficient
	is a POJO method with a <code>Collection&lt;Foo&gt;</code> type - the framework has to copy the payloads from the messages
	in the group into a new collection (and possibly attempt conversion on the payloads to <code>Foo</code>) every time the
	release strategy is called. <code>Collection&lt;?&gt;</code> avoids the conversion but still requires creating the
	new <interfacename>Collection</interfacename>.
	</para>
	<para>
	<emphasis role="bold">For these reasons, for large groups, it is recommended that you implement
	<interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename>.</emphasis>
</para>
</caution>
      <para>When the group is released for aggregation, all its not-yet-released
      messages are processed and removed from the group.
      If the group is also complete (i.e. if all messages from a
      sequence have arrived or if there is no sequence defined), then the group
      is marked as complete. Any new messages for this group will be sent to the discard channel
      (if defined). Setting <code>expire-groups-upon-completion</code> to <code>true</code> (default
      is <code>false</code>) removes the entire group and any new messages, with the same correlation id
      as the removed group, will form a new group.
      Partial sequences can be released by using a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>
      together with <code>send-partial-result-on-expiry</code> being set to <code>true</code>.</para>

      <important>To facilitate discarding of late-arriving messages, the aggregator must maintain state about
      the group after it has been released. This can eventually cause out of memory conditions.
      To avoid such situations, you should consider configuring a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>
      to remove the group metadata; the expiry parameters should be set to expire groups after it is not
      expected that late messages will arrive. For information about configuring a reaper, see
      <xref linkend="reaper"/>.</important>

      <para>Spring Integration provides an out-of-the box implementation for
      <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename>, the
      <classname>SequenceSizeReleaseStrategy</classname>. This implementation consults the
      SEQUENCE_NUMBER and SEQUENCE_SIZE headers of each arriving message to decide
      when a message group is complete and ready to be aggregated. As shown
      above, it is also the default strategy.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CorrelationStrategy</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename> interface is defined as
      follows:</para>

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface CorrelationStrategy {

  Object getCorrelationKey(Message<?> message);

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>The method returns an Object which represents the correlation key
      used for associating the message with a message group. The key must satisfy the
      criteria used for a key in a Map with respect to the implementation of
      equals() and hashCode().</para>

      <para>In general, any POJO can implement the
      correlation logic, and the rules for mapping a message to a
      method's argument (or arguments) are the same as for a
      <interfacename>ServiceActivator</interfacename> (including support for @Header
      annotations). The method must return a value, and the value must not be
      <code>null</code>.</para>

      <para>Spring Integration provides an out-of-the box implementation for
      <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename>, the
      <classname>HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy</classname>. This implementation
      returns the value of one of the message headers (whose name is specified
      by a constructor argument) as the correlation key. By default, the
      correlation strategy is a <classname>HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy</classname> returning
      the value of the CORRELATION_ID header attribute. If you have a custom header name
      you would like to use for correlation, then simply configure that on an instance of
      <classname>HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy</classname> and provide that as a
      reference for the Aggregator's correlation-strategy.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-config">
    <title>Configuring an Aggregator</title>
	<section id="aggregator-xml">
      <title>Configuring an Aggregator with XML</title>

      <para>Spring Integration supports the configuration of an aggregator via
      XML through the <code>&lt;aggregator/&gt;</code> element. Below you can see an example
      of an aggregator.</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="inputChannel"/>

<int:aggregator id=""myAggregator" ]]><co id="aggxml01" linkends="aggxml01-txt" /><![CDATA[
		auto-startup="true" ]]><co id="aggxml02" linkends="aggxml02-txt" /><![CDATA[
		input-channel="inputChannel" ]]><co id="aggxml03" linkends="aggxml03-txt" /><![CDATA[
		output-channel="outputChannel" ]]><co id="aggxml04" linkends="aggxml04-txt" /><![CDATA[
		discard-channel="throwAwayChannel" ]]><co id="aggxml05" linkends="aggxml05-txt" /><![CDATA[
		message-store="persistentMessageStore" ]]><co id="aggxml06" linkends="aggxml06-txt" /><![CDATA[
		order="1" ]]><co id="aggxml07" linkends="aggxml07-txt" /><![CDATA[
		send-partial-result-on-expiry="false" ]]><co id="aggxml08" linkends="aggxml08-txt" /><![CDATA[
		send-timeout="1000" ]]><co id="aggxml09" linkends="aggxml09-txt" /><![CDATA[

		correlation-strategy="correlationStrategyBean" ]]><co id="aggxml10" linkends="aggxml10-txt" /><![CDATA[
		correlation-strategy-method="correlate" ]]><co id="aggxml11" linkends="aggxml11-txt" /><![CDATA[
		correlation-strategy-expression="headers['foo']" ]]><co id="aggxml12" linkends="aggxml12-txt" /><![CDATA[

		ref="aggregatorBean" ]]><co id="aggxml13" linkends="aggxml13-txt" /><![CDATA[
		method="aggregate" ]]><co id="aggxml14" linkends="aggxml14-txt" /><![CDATA[

		release-strategy="releaseStrategyBean" ]]><co id="aggxml15" linkends="aggxml15-txt" /><![CDATA[
		release-strategy-method="release" ]]><co id="aggxml16" linkends="aggxml16-txt" /><![CDATA[
		release-strategy-expression="size() == 5" ]]><co id="aggxml17" linkends="aggxml17-txt" /><![CDATA[

		expire-groups-upon-completion="false" ]]><co id="aggxml18" linkends="aggxml18-txt" /><![CDATA[
		empty-group-min-timeout="60000" ]]><co id="aggxml19" linkends="aggxml19-txt" /><![CDATA[

		lock-registry="lockRegistry" ]]><co id="aggxml191" linkends="aggxml191-txt" /><![CDATA[

		group-timeout="60000" ]]><co id="aggxml20" linkends="aggxml20-txt" /><![CDATA[
		group-timeout-expression="size() ge 2 ? 100 : -1" ]]><co id="aggxml21" linkends="aggxml21-txt" /><![CDATA[
		expire-groups-on-timeout="true" ]]><co id="aggxml22" linkends="aggxml22-txt" /><![CDATA[

		scheduler="taskScheduler" /> ]]><co id="aggxml23" linkends="aggxml23-txt" /><![CDATA[

<int:channel id="outputChannel"/>

<int:channel id="throwAwayChannel"/>

<bean id="persistentMessageStore" class="org.springframework.integration.jdbc.JdbcMessageStore">
	<constructor-arg ref="dataSource"/>
</bean>

<bean id="aggregatorBean" class="sample.PojoAggregator"/>

<bean id="releaseStrategyBean" class="sample.PojoReleaseStrategy"/>

<bean id="correlationStrategyBean" class="sample.PojoCorrelationStrategy"/>]]></programlisting>

    <calloutlist>
      <callout arearefs="aggxml01" id="aggxml01-txt">
        <para>The id of the aggregator is
        <emphasis>0ptional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml02" id="aggxml02-txt">
        <para>Lifecycle attribute signaling if aggregator should be started during Application Context startup.
        <emphasis>Optional (default is 'true')</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml03" id="aggxml03-txt">
        <para>The channel from which where aggregator will receive messages.
        <emphasis>Required</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml04" id="aggxml04-txt">
        <para>The channel to which the aggregator will send the aggregation
        results. <emphasis>Optional (because incoming messages can specify a
        reply channel themselves via 'replyChannel' Message Header)</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml05" id="aggxml05-txt">
        <para>The channel to which the aggregator will send the messages that
        timed out (if <code>send-partial-result-on-expiry</code> is
        <emphasis>false</emphasis>). <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml06" id="aggxml06-txt">
        <para>A reference to a <code>MessageGroupStore</code> used
        to store groups of messages under their correlation key until they are
        complete. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>, by default a volatile
        in-memory store.</para>
      </callout>

       <callout arearefs="aggxml07" id="aggxml07-txt">
        <para>Order of this aggregator when more than one handle is subscribed to the same DirectChannel
        (use for load balancing purposes).
        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml08" id="aggxml08-txt">
        <para>
        Indicates that expired messages should be aggregated and sent to the 'output-channel' or 'replyChannel'
		once their containing <classname>MessageGroup</classname> is expired (see <code>MessageGroupStore.expireMessageGroups(long)</code>).
		One way of expiring <classname>MessageGroup</classname>s is by configuring a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>.
		However <classname>MessageGroup</classname>s can alternatively be expired by simply calling
		<code>MessageGroupStore.expireMessageGroup(groupId)</code>. That could be accomplished via a Control Bus operation
		or by simply invoking that method if you have a reference to the <classname>MessageGroupStore</classname> instance.
		Otherwise by itself this attribute has no behavior. It only serves as an indicator of what to do (discard or send to the output/reply
		channel) with Messages that are still in the <classname>MessageGroup</classname> that is about to be expired.
        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>. <emphasis>Default - 'false'</emphasis>.
        <note>
          This attribute is more properly 'send-partial-result-on-timeout' because the group may not actually expire
          if <code>expire-groups-on-timeout</code> is set to <code>false</code>.
        </note>
        </para>
      </callout>

       <callout arearefs="aggxml09" id="aggxml09-txt">
        <para>The timeout interval for sending the aggregated messages to the output or
        reply channel. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

       <callout arearefs="aggxml10" id="aggxml10-txt">
        <para>A reference to a bean that implements the message correlation (grouping)
        algorithm. The bean can be an implementation of the <interfacename>CorrelationStrategy</interfacename>
        interface or a POJO. In the latter case the correlation-strategy-method attribute must be defined
        as well. <emphasis>Optional (by default, the aggregator will use
        the <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.CORRELATION_ID</code> header) </emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml11" id="aggxml11-txt">
        <para>A method defined on the bean referenced by
        <code>correlation-strategy</code>, that implements the
        correlation decision algorithm. <emphasis>Optional, with
        restrictions (requires <code>correlation-strategy</code> to be
        present).</emphasis></para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml12" id="aggxml12-txt">
        <para>A SpEL expression representing the correlation strategy.
        Example: <code>"headers['foo']"</code>. Only one of
        <code>correlation-strategy</code>
        or <code>correlation-strategy-expression</code> is allowed.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml13" id="aggxml13-txt">
        <para>A reference to a bean defined in the application context. The bean must implement the aggregation logic
    as described above. <emphasis>Optional (by default the list of aggregated Messages will become a
    payload of the output message).</emphasis></para>
      </callout>
      <callout arearefs="aggxml14" id="aggxml14-txt">
        <para>A method defined on the bean referenced by <code>ref</code>,
        that implements the message aggregation
        algorithm. <emphasis>Optional, depends on <code>ref</code> attribute being defined.</emphasis></para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml15" id="aggxml15-txt">
        <para>A reference to a bean that implements the release strategy.
        The bean can be an implementation of the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> interface
        or a POJO. In the latter case the release-strategy-method
        attribute must be defined as well. <emphasis>Optional (by default, the
        aggregator will use the <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.SEQUENCE_SIZE</code> header attribute)</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml16" id="aggxml16-txt">
        <para>A method defined on the bean referenced by
        <code>release-strategy</code>, that implements the
        completion decision algorithm. <emphasis>Optional, with
        restrictions (requires <code>release-strategy</code> to be
        present).</emphasis></para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml17" id="aggxml17-txt">
        <para>A SpEL expression representing the release strategy; the root object for the
        expression is a <code>Collection</code> of <code>Message</code>s.
        Example: <code>"size() == 5"</code>. Only one of
        <code>release-strategy</code>
        or <code>release-strategy-expression</code> is allowed.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml18" id="aggxml18-txt">
        <para>When set to true (default false), completed groups are
        removed from the message store, allowing subsequent messages with
        the same correlation to form a new group. The default behavior
        is to send messages with the same correlation as a completed
        group to the <emphasis>discard-channel</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml19" id="aggxml19-txt">
        <para>Only applies if a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> is configured
        for the <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code>'s <classname>MessageStore</classname>.
        By default, when a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> is configured to expire partial
        groups, empty groups are also removed. Empty groups exist after a group
        is released normally. This is to enable the detection and discarding of
        late-arriving messages. If you wish to expire empty groups on a longer
        schedule than expiring partial groups, set this property. Empty groups will
        then not be removed from the <classname>MessageStore</classname> until they have not been modified
        for at least this number of milliseconds. Note that the actual time to expire an
        empty group will also be affected by the reaper's <emphasis>timeout</emphasis>
        property and it could be as much as this value plus the timeout.</para>
      </callout>

	  <callout arearefs="aggxml191" id="aggxml191-txt">
        <para>
			A reference to a <interfacename>org.springframework.integration.util.LockRegistry</interfacename> bean;
			used to obtain a <interfacename>Lock</interfacename> based on the <code>groupId</code> for
			concurrent operations on the
			<code>MessageGroup</code>. By default, an internal <classname>DefaultLockRegistry</classname> is used.
			Use of a distributed <interfacename>LockRegistry</interfacename>, such as the <classname
			>RedisLockRegistry</classname>, ensures only one instance of the aggregator will operate
			on a group concurrently. See <xref linkend="redis-lock-registry"/> for more information.
        </para>
      </callout>

	  <callout arearefs="aggxml20" id="aggxml20-txt">
        <para>
			A timeout in milliseconds to force the <code>MessageGroup</code> complete,
			when the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> doesn't <emphasis>release</emphasis>
			the group when the current Message arrives.
			This attribute provides a built-in <emphasis>Time-base Release Strategy</emphasis> for the aggregator,
			when there is a need to emit a partial result (or discard the group), if a new Message does not arrive
			for the <code>MessageGroup</code> within the timeout.
			When a new Message arrives at the aggregator, any existing <interfacename>ScheduledFuture&lt;?&gt;</interfacename>
			for its <code>MessageGroup</code> is canceled. If the
			<interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename>
			returns <code>false</code> (don't release) and the <code>groupTimeout &gt; 0</code> a new task will be
			scheduled to expire the group.
			Setting this attribute to zero is not advised because it will effectively disable the aggregator because every
			message group will be immediately completed. It is possible, however to conditionally set it to zero using an
			expression; see <code>group-timeout-expression</code> for information.
			The action taken during the completion depends on the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> and the
			<code>send-partial-group-on-expiry</code> attribute. See <xref linkend="agg-and-group-to"/> for
			more information.
			Mutually exclusive with 'group-timeout-expression' attribute.
        </para>
      </callout>
	  <callout arearefs="aggxml21" id="aggxml21-txt">
			<para>
				The SpEL expression that evaluates to a <code>groupTimeout</code> with the <code>MessageGroup</code>
				as the <code>#root</code> evaluation context object. Used for scheduling the <code>MessageGroup</code> to
				be forced complete. If the expression evaluates to null or <code>&lt; 0</code>, the
				completion is not scheduled. If it evaluates to zero, the group is completed immediately on
				the current thread. In effect, this provides a dynamic <code>group-timeout</code> property.
				See <code>group-timeout</code> for more information.
				Mutually exclusive with 'group-timeout' attribute.
			</para>
	  </callout>
	  <callout arearefs="aggxml22" id="aggxml22-txt">
			<para>
				When a group is completed due to a timeout (or by a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>), the group
				is expired (completely removed) by default. Late arriving messages will start a new group. Set this
				to <code>false</code> to complete the group but have its metadata remain so that late
				arriving messages will be discarded. Empty groups can be expired later using a
				<classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> together with the <code>empty-group-min-timeout</code>
				attribute. Default: 'true'.
			</para>
	  </callout>
	  <callout arearefs="aggxml23" id="aggxml23-txt">
			<para>
				A <interfacename>TaskScheduler</interfacename> bean reference to schedule
				the <code>MessageGroup</code> to be forced complete
				if no new message arrives for the <code>MessageGroup</code>
				within the <code>groupTimeout</code>.
				If not provided, the default scheduler <code>taskScheduler</code>,
				registered in the <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename> (<classname>ThreadPoolTaskScheduler</classname>)
				will be used. This attribute does not apply if <code>group-timeout</code> or
				<code>group-timeout-expression</code> is not specified.
			</para>
	  </callout>

    </calloutlist>

	<important>
		<title>Expiring Groups</title>
		<para>
			There are two attributes related to expiring (completely removing) groups. When a group
			is expired, there is no record of it and if a new message arrives with the same correlation,
			a new group is started. When a group is completed (without expiry), the empty group remains
			and late arriving messages are discarded. Empty groups can be removed later using a
			<classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> in combination with the
			<code>empty-group-min-timeout</code> attribute.
		</para>
		<para>
			<code>expire-groups-upon-completion</code> relates to "normal" completion - when the
			<interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> releases the group. This defaults to
			<code>false</code>.
		</para>
		<para>
			If a group is not completed normally, but is released or discarded because of a timeout,
			the group is normally expired. Since <emphasis>version 4.1</emphasis>, you can now control
			this behavior using <code>expire-groups-upon-timeout</code>; this defaults to
			<code>true</code> for backwards compatibility.
		</para>
		<note>
			When a group is timed out, the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> is given
			one more opportunity to release the group; if it does so, and
			<code>expire-groups-upon-timeout</code> is false,
			then expiration is controlled
			by <code>expire-groups-upon-completion</code>. If the group is not released by the release
			strategy during timeout, then the expiration is controlled by the
			<code>expire-groups-upon-timeout</code>. Timed-out groups are either discarded, or a
			partial release occurs (based on <code>send-partial-result-on-expiry</code>).
		</note>
	</important>

    <para>Using a <code>ref</code> attribute is generally recommended if a custom
    aggregator handler implementation may be referenced in other
    <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code> definitions. However if a custom
    aggregator implementation is only being used by a single
    definition of the <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code>, you can use an inner
    bean definition (starting with version 1.0.3) to configure the aggregation
    POJO within the <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code> element:
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<aggregator input-channel="input" method="sum" output-channel="output">
    <beans:bean class="org.foo.PojoAggregator"/>
</aggregator>]]></programlisting></para>

    <note>
      <para>Using both a <code>ref</code> attribute and an inner bean definition in the
      same <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code> configuration is not allowed, as it
      creates an ambiguous condition. In such cases, an Exception will be
      thrown.</para>
    </note>

    <para>An example implementation of the aggregator bean looks as
    follows:</para>

    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class PojoAggregator {

  public Long add(List<Long> results) {
    long total = 0l;
    for (long partialResult: results) {
      total += partialResult;
    }
    return total;
  }

}]]></programlisting>

    <para>An implementation of the completion strategy bean for the example
    above may be as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class PojoReleaseStrategy {
...
  public boolean canRelease(List<Long> numbers) {
    int sum = 0;
    for (long number: numbers) {
      sum += number;
    }
    return sum >= maxValue;
  }
}]]></programlisting> <note>
        <para>Wherever it makes sense, the release strategy method and the
        aggregator method can be combined in a single bean.</para>
      </note></para>

    <para>An implementation of the correlation strategy bean for the example
    above may be as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class PojoCorrelationStrategy {
...
  public Long groupNumbersByLastDigit(Long number) {
    return number % 10;
  }
}]]></programlisting></para>

    <para>For example, this aggregator would group numbers by some criterion
    (in our case the remainder after dividing by 10) and will hold the group
    until the sum of the numbers provided by the payloads exceeds a
    certain value.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Wherever it makes sense, the release strategy method, correlation
      strategy method and the aggregator method can be combined in a single
      bean (all of them or any two).</para>
    </note>

    <para>
    	<emphasis>Aggregators and Spring Expression Language (SpEL)</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
    Since Spring Integration 2.0, the various strategies (correlation, release, and aggregation) may be handled with
    <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/expressions.html">SpEL</ulink>
    which is recommended if the logic behind such <emphasis>release strategy</emphasis> is relatively simple.
    Let's say you have a legacy component that was designed to receive an array of objects. We know that the default release
    strategy will assemble all aggregated messages in the List. So now we have two problems. First we need to extract
    individual messages from the list, and then we need to extract the payload of each message and assemble
    the array of objects (see code below).
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public String[] processRelease(List<Message<String>> messages){
    List<String> stringList = new ArrayList<String>();
    for (Message<String> message : messages) {
        stringList.add(message.getPayload());
    }
    return stringList.toArray(new String[]{});
}]]></programlisting>
	<para>
	However, with SpEL such a requirement could actually be handled relatively easily with a
	one-line expression, thus sparing you from writing a custom class and configuring it as a bean.
	</para>
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:aggregator input-channel="aggChannel"
    output-channel="replyChannel"
    expression="#this.![payload].toArray()"/>]]></programlisting>
	<para>
	In the above configuration we are using a <ulink
	url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/expressions.html#d0e12113">Collection Projection</ulink> expression
	to assemble a new collection from the payloads of all messages in the list and then transforming it to an Array, thus
	achieving the same result as the java code above.
    </para>

    <para>
    The same expression-based approach can be applied when dealing with custom <emphasis>Release</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>Correlation</emphasis> strategies.
    </para>
    <para>
	Instead of defining a bean for a custom <classname>CorrelationStrategy</classname> via
    the <code>correlation-strategy</code> attribute, you can implement your simple correlation logic
    via a SpEL expression and configure it via the <code>correlation-strategy-expression</code> attribute.
	</para>
	<para>
	For example:

	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[correlation-strategy-expression="payload.person.id"]]></programlisting>

	In the above example it is assumed that the payload has an attribute <code>person</code> with an <code>id</code>
	which is going to be used to correlate messages.
	</para>
	<para>
    Likewise, for the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> you can implement your release logic as
    a SpEL expression and configure it via the <code>release-strategy-expression</code> attribute.
    The only difference is that since ReleaseStrategy is passed the List of Messages, the root object in the SpEL
    evaluation context is the List itself. That List can be referenced as <code>#this</code> within the expression.
	</para>
	<para>
	For example:

	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[release-strategy-expression="#this.size() gt 5"]]></programlisting>

	In this example the root object of the SpEL Evaluation Context is the
    <interfacename>MessageGroup</interfacename> itself, and you are simply stating
    that as soon as there are more than 5 messages in this group, it should be released.
    </para>

	<section id="agg-and-group-to">
		<title>Aggregator and Group Timeout</title>

	<para>
		Starting with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, two new mutually exclusive attributes have been introduced:
		<code>group-timeout</code> and <code>group-timeout-expression</code> (see the description above). There are some
		cases where it is needed to emit the aggregator result (or discard the group) after a timeout
		if the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename>
		doesn't <emphasis>release</emphasis> when the current Message arrives.
		For this purpose the <code>groupTimeout</code> option allows scheduling the <code>MessageGroup</code> to
		be forced complete:
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<aggregator input-channel="input" output-channel="output"
		send-partial-result-on-expiry="true"
		group-timeout-expression="size() ge 2 ? 10000 : -1"
		release-strategy-expression="[0].headers.sequenceNumber == [0].headers.sequenceSize"/>]]></programlisting>
		With this example, the normal <emphasis>release</emphasis> will be possible if the aggregator receives the last message
		in sequence as defined by the <code>release-strategy-expression</code>. If that specific message does not arrive,
		the <code>groupTimeout</code> will force the group complete after 10 seconds as long as the group contains at least 2 Messages.
    </para>
    <para>
		The results of forcing the group complete depends on the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> and
		the <code>send-partial-result-on-expiry</code>.
		First, the release strategy is again consulted to see if a <emphasis>normal</emphasis> release is to be made - while the
		group won't have changed, the <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename> can decide to release the group at this time. If the
		release strategy still does not release the group, it will be expired.
		If <code>send-partial-result-on-expiry</code> is <code>true</code>,
		existing messages in the (partial) <code>MessageGroup</code> will be released as a normal aggregator reply Message to the
		<code>output-channel</code>, otherwise it will be discarded.
    </para>
	<para>
		There is a difference between <code>groupTimeout</code> behavior and <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>
		(see <xref linkend="aggregator-config"/>). The reaper initiates forced completion for all <code>MessageGroup</code>s
		in the <code>MessageGroupStore</code> periodically. The <code>groupTimeout</code> does it for each <code>MessageGroup</code>
		individually, if a new Message doesn't arrive during the <code>groupTimeout</code>. Also, the reaper can be used to
		remove empty groups (empty groups are retained in order to discard late messages,
		if <code>expire-groups-upon-completion</code> is false).
	</para>
	</section>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-annotations">
    <title>Configuring an Aggregator with Annotations</title>

    <para>An aggregator configured using annotations would look like this.</para>

    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class Waiter {
  ...

  @Aggregator ]]><co id="aggann" /><![CDATA[
  public Delivery aggregatingMethod(List<OrderItem> items) {
    ...
  }

  @ReleaseStrategy ]]><co id="agganncs" /><![CDATA[
  public boolean releaseChecker(List<Message<?>> messages) {
    ...
  }

  @CorrelationStrategy ]]><co id="agganncorrs" /><![CDATA[
  public String correlateBy(OrderItem item) {
    ...
  }

}]]></programlisting>

    <calloutlist>
      <callout arearefs="aggann">
        <para>An annotation indicating that this method shall be used as an
        aggregator. Must be specified if this class will be used as an
        aggregator.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="agganncs">
        <para id="aggann2">An annotation indicating that this method shall be
        used as the release strategy of an aggregator. If not present on any
        method, the aggregator will use the
        SequenceSizeReleaseStrategy.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="agganncorrs">
        <para id="agann3">An annotation indicating that this method shall be
        used as the correlation strategy of an aggregator. If no correlation
        strategy is indicated, the aggregator will use the
        HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy based on CORRELATION_ID.</para>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

    <para>All of the configuration options provided by the xml element are
    also available for the @Aggregator annotation.</para>

    <para>The aggregator can be either referenced explicitly from XML or, if
    the @MessageEndpoint is defined on the class, detected automatically
    through classpath scanning.</para>
  </section>

	</section>

  <section id="reaper">
    <title id="reaper">Managing State in an Aggregator:
    MessageGroupStore</title>

    <para>Aggregator (and some other patterns in Spring Integration) is a
    stateful pattern that requires decisions to be made based on a group of
    messages that have arrived over a period of time, all with the same
    correlation key. The design of the interfaces in the stateful patterns
    (e.g. <interfacename>ReleaseStrategy</interfacename>) is driven by the principle
    that the components (whether defined by the framework or a user) should be able to remain stateless.
    All state is carried by the <interfacename>MessageGroup</interfacename> and its
    management is delegated to the
    <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename>.


    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface MessageGroupStore {
    int getMessageCountForAllMessageGroups();

    int getMarkedMessageCountForAllMessageGroups();

    int getMessageGroupCount();

    MessageGroup getMessageGroup(Object groupId);

    MessageGroup addMessageToGroup(Object groupId, Message<?> message);

    MessageGroup markMessageGroup(MessageGroup group);

    MessageGroup removeMessageFromGroup(Object key, Message<?> messageToRemove);

    MessageGroup markMessageFromGroup(Object key, Message<?> messageToMark);

    void removeMessageGroup(Object groupId);

    void registerMessageGroupExpiryCallback(MessageGroupCallback callback);

    int expireMessageGroups(long timeout);
}]]></programlisting>

    For more information please refer to the
    <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-integration/api/org/springframework/integration/store/MessageGroupStore.html">JavaDoc</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>The <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename> accumulates state
    information in <interfacename>MessageGroups</interfacename> while waiting for
    a release strategy to be triggered, and that event might not ever happen.
    So to prevent stale messages from lingering, and for volatile stores to
    provide a hook for cleaning up when the application shuts down, the
    <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename> allows the user to register
    callbacks to apply to its <interfacename>MessageGroups</interfacename> when they
    expire. The interface is very straightforward:</para>

    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface MessageGroupCallback {

    void execute(MessageGroupStore messageGroupStore, MessageGroup group);

}]]></programlisting>

    <para>The callback has direct access to the store and the message group
    so it can manage the persistent state (e.g. by removing the group from the
    store entirely).</para>

    <para>The <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename> maintains a list of these callbacks
    which it applies, on demand, to all messages whose timestamp is earlier than a time
    supplied as a parameter (see the <methodname>registerMessageGroupExpiryCallback(..)</methodname>
    and <methodname>expireMessageGroups(..)</methodname> methods above).</para>

    <para>The <code>expireMessageGroups</code> method can be called with a timeout value.
    Any message older than the current time minus this value will be expired,
    and have the callbacks applied. Thus it is the user of the store that
    defines what is meant by message group "expiry".</para>

    <para>As a convenience for users, Spring Integration provides a wrapper
    for the message expiry in the form of a
    <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="reaper" class="org...MessageGroupStoreReaper">
    <property name="messageGroupStore" ref="messageStore"/>
    <property name="timeout" value="30000"/>
</bean>

<task:scheduled-tasks scheduler="scheduler">
    <task:scheduled ref="reaper" method="run" fixed-rate="10000"/>
</task:scheduled-tasks>]]></programlisting>

    <para>The reaper is a <interfacename>Runnable</interfacename>, and all that is happening
    in the example above is that the message group store's expire method is being called
    once every 10 seconds. The timeout itself is 30 seconds.</para>

    <note>
    It is important to understand that the 'timeout' property of the <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> is an
    approximate value and is impacted by the  the rate of the task scheduler since this property will
    only be checked on the next scheduled execution of the <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> task. For example if
    the timeout is set for 10 min, but the <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> task is scheduled to run every 60 min
    and the last execution of the <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname> task happened 1 min before the timeout, the
    <classname>MessageGroup</classname>  will not expire for the next 59 min. So it is recommended to set the rate at least equal to the value of the timeout or shorter.
    </note>

    <para>In addition to the reaper, the expiry callbacks are invoked when the application
    shuts down via a lifecycle callback in the <classname>AbstractCorrelatingMessageHandler</classname>.
    </para>

    <para>The <classname>AbstractCorrelatingMessageHandler</classname> registers its
    own expiry callback, and this is the link with the boolean flag
    <code>send-partial-result-on-expiry</code> in the XML configuration of the
    aggregator. If the flag is set to true, then when the expiry callback is
    invoked, any unmarked messages in groups that are not yet released can
    be sent on to the output channel.</para>

    <important>
      <para>When using a <classname>MessageGroupStoreReaper</classname>, it is generally recommended to use a
      separate <classname>MessageStore</classname> for each correlating endpoint. Otherwise,
      unexpected results may occur because one endpoint may remove another endpoint's groups.</para>
      <para>Some <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename> implementations allow using the same physical
      resources, by partitioning the data; for example, the <classname>JdbcMessageStore</classname>
      has a <code>region</code> property;
      the <classname>MongoDbMessageStore</classname> has a <code>collectionName</code> property.</para>
      <para>For more information about <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename> interface
      and its implementations, please read <xref linkend="message-store"/>.</para>
    </important>
  </section>
</section>
