<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="chain"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Message Handler Chain</title>

  <section id="chain-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The <classname>MessageHandlerChain</classname> is an implementation of
      <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> that can be configured as a single Message Endpoint while
      actually delegating to a chain of other handlers, such as Filters, Transformers, Splitters, and so on.
      This can lead to a much simpler configuration when several handlers need to be connected in a fixed, linear
      progression. For example, it is fairly common to provide a Transformer before other components. Similarly, when
      providing a <emphasis>Filter</emphasis> before some other component in a chain, you are essentially creating a
      <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/MessageSelector.html">Selective Consumer</ulink>. In either case, the
      chain only requires a single <code>input-channel</code> and a single <code>output-channel</code> eliminating
      the need to define channels for each individual component.
      <tip>
        Spring Integration's <interfacename>Filter</interfacename> provides a boolean property <methodname>throwExceptionOnRejection</methodname>.
        When providing multiple Selective Consumers on the same point-to-point channel with different acceptance criteria,
        this value should be set to 'true' (the default is false) so that the dispatcher will know that the Message was
        rejected and as a result will attempt to pass the Message on to other subscribers. If the Exception were not
        thrown, then it would appear to the dispatcher as if the Message had been passed on successfully even though
        the Filter had <emphasis>dropped</emphasis> the Message to prevent further processing. If you do indeed want
        to "drop" the Messages, then the Filter's 'discard-channel' might be useful since it does give you a chance
        to perform some operation with the dropped message (e.g. send to a JMS queue or simply write to a log).
      </tip>
    </para>
    <para>
    The handler chain simplifies configuration while internally maintaining the same degree of loose coupling between
    components, and it is trivial to modify the configuration if at some point a non-linear arrangement is required.
    </para>
    <para>
    Internally, the chain will be expanded into a linear setup of the listed endpoints, separated by anonymous channels.
    The reply channel header will not be taken into account within the chain: only after the last handler is invoked
    will the resulting message be forwarded on to the reply channel or the chain's output channel. Because of this
    setup all handlers except the last required to implement the MessageProducer interface (which provides a
    'setOutputChannel()' method). The last handler only needs an output channel if the outputChannel on the
    MessageHandlerChain is set.
    <note>
      <para>
        As with other endpoints, the <code>output-channel</code> is optional. If there is a reply Message at the end of the
        chain, the output-channel takes precedence, but if not available, the chain handler will check for a
        reply channel header on the inbound Message as a fallback.
      </para>
    </note>
    </para>
    <para>
    In most cases there is no need to implement MessageHandlers yourself. The next section will focus on namespace
    support for the chain element. Most Spring Integration endpoints, like Service Activators and Transformers, are
    suitable for use within a <classname>MessageHandlerChain</classname>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="chain-namespace">
    <title>Configuring Chain</title>
    <para>
      The &lt;chain&gt; element provides an <code>input-channel</code> attribute, and if the last element in the chain is capable
      of producing reply messages (optional), it also supports an <code>output-channel</code> attribute. The sub-elements are then
      filters, transformers, splitters, and service-activators. The last element may also be a router or an outbound-channel-adapter.
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:chain input-channel="input" output-channel="output">
    <int:filter ref="someSelector" throw-exception-on-rejection="true"/>
    <int:header-enricher>
        <int:header name="foo" value="bar"/>
    </int:header-enricher>
    <int:service-activator ref="someService" method="someMethod"/>
</int:chain>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
  <para>
    The &lt;header-enricher&gt; element used in the above example will set a message header named "foo" with a value
    of "bar" on the message. A header enricher is a specialization of <interfacename>Transformer</interfacename>
    that touches only header values. You could obtain the same result by implementing a MessageHandler that did the
    header modifications and wiring that as a bean, but the header-enricher is obviously a simpler option.
  </para>
  <para>
    The &lt;chain&gt; can be configured as the last 'black-box' consumer of the message flow. For this solution it is
    enough to put at the end of the &lt;chain&gt; some &lt;outbound-channel-adapter&gt;:
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:chain input-channel="input">
    <si-xml:marshalling-transformer marshaller="marshaller" result-type="StringResult" />
    <int:service-activator ref="someService" method="someMethod"/>
    <int:header-enricher>
        <int:header name="foo" value="bar"/>
    </int:header-enricher>
    <int:logging-channel-adapter level="INFO" log-full-message="true"/>
</int:chain>]]></programlisting>
  </para>
	<para><emphasis>Disallowed Attributes and Elements</emphasis></para>
	<para>
		It is important to note that certain attributes, such as
		<emphasis role="bold">order</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">input-channel</emphasis>
		are not allowed to be specified on components used within a
		<emphasis>chain</emphasis>. The same is true for the <emphasis role="bold">poller</emphasis>
		sub-element.
	</para>
	<important>
		<para>
			For the <emphasis>Spring Integration</emphasis> core components, the
			XML Schema itself will enforce some of these constraints. However, for non-core
			components or your own custom components, these constraints are enforced
			by the XML namespace parser, not by the XML Schema.
		</para>
		<para>
			These XML namespace parser constraints were added with
			<emphasis>Spring Integration 2.2</emphasis>. The XML namespace parser
			will throw an <classname>BeanDefinitionParsingException</classname> if you try to use disallowed
			attributes and elements.
		</para>
	</important>
	<para>
		The <emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute, however, is allowed to be specified.
		Since Spring Integration 3.0 <emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute plays almost the same identification role
		as for root beans. Let's look at the example:
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:chain id="fooChain" input-channel="input">
    <int:service-activator id="fooService" ref="someService" method="someMethod"/>
    <int:object-to-json-transformer/>
</int:chain>]]></programlisting>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				The <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> root element has <emphasis>id</emphasis> 'fooChain'. So,
				<classname>AbstractEndpoint</classname> implementation (<classname>PollingConsumer</classname> or
				<classname>EventDrivenConsumer</classname>, depending on the <emphasis>input-channel</emphasis> type)
				bean takes this value as a root component.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The <classname>MessageHandlerChain</classname> bean acquires a bean alias 'fooChain.handler', which allows
				direct access to this bean from <interfacename>BeanFactory</interfacename>.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The <code>&lt;service-activator&gt;</code> doesn't provide Messaging Endpoint (<classname>PollingConsumer</classname>
				or <classname>EventDrivenConsumer</classname>) within <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> - it is just one of
				<interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename>s inside the <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> black box. So, in this case,
				'fooService' <emphasis>id</emphasis> with the <emphasis>id</emphasis> of the <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code>
				is involved in the generation of <classname>ServiceActivatingHandler</classname>'s
				<emphasis>beanName</emphasis> - 'fooChain$child.fooService.handler', to allow simplify identify this handler
				within <interfacename>BeanFactory</interfacename>.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			    The <emphasis>componentName</emphasis> of this <classname>ServiceActivatingHandler</classname> takes the
				same value, but without '.handler' suffix - 'fooChain$child.fooService'.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The last <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> sub-component, <code>&lt;object-to-json-transformer&gt;</code>, doesn't have
				an <emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute. However, it has precise <emphasis>order</emphasis>
				in the <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code>'s handler list. So, this order is involved in the generation of
				<classname>MessageTransformingHandler</classname>'s <emphasis>componentName</emphasis>.
				Here it looks like 'fooChain$child#1'. Note, this transformer isn't registered as a bean within application context,
				so, it doesn't get a <emphasis>beanName</emphasis>, however its <emphasis>componentName</emphasis> has
				a value within <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> black box.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		The <emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute for <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> sub-components allows them to be eligible for
		<link linkend='jmx-mbean-exporter'>JMX export</link> and they are trackable via <link linkend='message-history'>Message History</link>.
		By the bean alias, using suffix '.handler', <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code> sub-components <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename>s
		can be accessed from <interfacename>BeanFactory</interfacename>.
	</para>
	<important>
		<para>
			It is strongly recommended to provide an explicit <emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute on the <code>&lt;chain&gt;</code>
			to make easier identification of sub-components in logs, access to them within<interfacename>BeanFactory</interfacename> etc.
		</para>
	</important>
	<para><emphasis>Calling a Chain from within a Chain</emphasis></para>

	<para>
  Sometimes you need to make a nested call to another chain from within a chain and then come
  back and continue execution within the original chain.
    To accomplish this you can utilize a Messaging Gateway by including a &lt;gateway&gt; element.
    For example:
	</para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:chain id="main-chain" input-channel="in" output-channel="out">
    <int:header-enricher>
      <int:header name="name" value="Many" />
    </int:header-enricher>
    <int:service-activator>
      <bean class="org.foo.SampleService" />
    </int:service-activator>
    <int:gateway request-channel="inputA"/>  
</int:chain>

<int:chain id="nested-chain-a" input-channel="inputA">
    <int:header-enricher>
        <int:header name="name" value="Moe" />
    </int:header-enricher>
    <int:gateway request-channel="inputB"/> 
    <int:service-activator>
        <bean class="org.foo.SampleService" />
    </int:service-activator>
</int:chain>

<int:chain id="nested-chain-b" input-channel="inputB">
    <int:header-enricher>
        <int:header name="name" value="Jack" />
    </int:header-enricher>
    <int:service-activator>
        <bean class="org.foo.SampleService" />
    </int:service-activator>
</int:chain>]]></programlisting>
	<para>
    In the above example the <emphasis>nested-chain-a</emphasis> will be called at the end of
    <emphasis>main-chain</emphasis> processing by the 'gateway' element configured there. While in
    <emphasis>nested-chain-a</emphasis> a call to a <emphasis>nested-chain-b</emphasis> will be made
    after header enrichment and then it will come back to finish execution in <emphasis>nested-chain-b</emphasis>.
    Finally the flow returns to the <emphasis>main-chain</emphasis>. When the nested version of a &lt;gateway&gt;
    element is defined in the chain, it does not require the <code>service-interface</code> attribute.
    Instead, it simple takes the message in its current state and places it on the channel defined via
    the <code>request-channel</code> attribute. When the downstream flow initiated by that gateway completes,
    a <interfacename>Message</interfacename> will be returned to the gateway and continue its journey within
    the current chain.
  </para>
  </section>

</section>
