<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="endpoint"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Message Endpoints</title>
  <para>
    The first part of this chapter covers some background theory and reveals quite a bit about the underlying API
    that drives Spring Integration's various messaging components. This information can be helpful if you want to
    really understand what's going on behind the scenes. However, if you want to get up and running with the
    simplified namespace-based configuration of the various elements, feel free to skip ahead to
    <xref linkend="endpoint-namespace"/> for now.
  </para>
  <para>
    As mentioned in the overview, Message Endpoints are responsible for connecting the various messaging components to
    channels. Over the next several chapters, you will see a number of different components that consume Messages. Some
    of these are also capable of sending reply Messages. Sending Messages is quite straightforward. As shown above in
    <xref linkend="channel"/>, it's easy to <emphasis>send</emphasis> a Message to a Message Channel. However,
    receiving is a bit more complicated. The main reason is that there are two types of consumers:
    <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/PollingConsumer.html">Polling Consumers</ulink> and
    <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/EventDrivenConsumer.html">Event Driven Consumers</ulink>.
  </para>
  <para>
    Of the two, Event Driven Consumers are much simpler. Without any need to manage and schedule a separate poller
    thread, they are essentially just listeners with a callback method. When connecting to one of Spring Integration's
    subscribable Message Channels, this simple option works great. However, when connecting to a buffering, pollable
    Message Channel, some component has to schedule and manage the polling thread(s). Spring Integration provides
    two different endpoint implementations to accommodate these two types of consumers. Therefore, the consumers
    themselves can simply implement the callback interface. When polling is required, the endpoint acts as a
    <emphasis>container</emphasis> for the consumer instance. The benefit is similar to that of using a container for hosting
    Message Driven Beans, but since these consumers are simply Spring-managed Objects running within an
    ApplicationContext, it more closely resembles Spring's own MessageListener containers.
  </para>

  <section id="endpoint-handler">
    <title>Message Handler</title>
    <para>
      Spring Integration's <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> interface is implemented by many of the
      components within the framework. In other words, this is not part of the public API, and a developer would not
      typically implement <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> directly. Nevertheless, it is used by a Message
      Consumer for actually handling the consumed Messages, and so being aware of this strategy interface does help in
      terms of understanding the overall role of a consumer. The interface is defined as follows:
      <programlisting language="java">public interface MessageHandler {

    void handleMessage(Message&lt;?&gt; message);

}</programlisting>
      Despite its simplicity, this provides the foundation for most of the components that will be covered in the
      following chapters (Routers, Transformers, Splitters, Aggregators, Service Activators, etc). Those components
      each perform very different functionality with the Messages they handle, but the requirements for actually
      receiving a Message are the same, and the choice between polling and event-driven behavior is also the same.
      Spring Integration provides two endpoint implementations that <emphasis>host</emphasis> these callback-based handlers and allow
      them to be connected to Message Channels.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="endpoint-eventdrivenconsumer">
    <title>Event Driven Consumer</title>
    <para>
      Because it is the simpler of the two, we will cover the Event Driven Consumer endpoint first. You may recall that
      the <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename> interface provides a <methodname>subscribe()</methodname>
      method and that the method accepts a <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> parameter (as shown in
      <xref linkend="channel-interfaces-subscribablechannel"/>):
      <programlisting language="java">
subscribableChannel.subscribe(messageHandler);
</programlisting>
      Since a handler that is subscribed to a channel does not have to actively poll that channel, this is an
      Event Driven Consumer, and the implementation provided by Spring Integration accepts a
      a <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename> and a <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename>:
      <programlisting language="java">SubscribableChannel channel = context.getBean("subscribableChannel", SubscribableChannel.class);

EventDrivenConsumer consumer = new EventDrivenConsumer(channel, exampleHandler);</programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="endpoint-pollingconsumer">
    <title>Polling Consumer</title>
    <para>
      Spring Integration also provides a <classname>PollingConsumer</classname>, and it can be instantiated in
      the same way except that the channel must implement <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename>:
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java">PollableChannel channel = context.getBean("pollableChannel", PollableChannel.class);

PollingConsumer consumer = new PollingConsumer(channel, exampleHandler);</programlisting>

    <note>
        For more information regarding Polling Consumers, please also read
        <xref linkend="polling-consumer"/> as well as <xref linkend="channel-adapter"/>.
    </note>

	<para>
		There are many other configuration options for the Polling Consumer. For example, the trigger is a required property:
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java">PollingConsumer consumer = new PollingConsumer(channel, handler);

consumer.setTrigger(new IntervalTrigger(30, TimeUnit.SECONDS));</programlisting>
	<para>
      Spring Integration currently provides two implementations of the <interfacename>Trigger</interfacename>
      interface: <classname>IntervalTrigger</classname> and <classname>CronTrigger</classname>. The
      <classname>IntervalTrigger</classname> is typically defined with a simple interval (in milliseconds), but
      also supports an <emphasis>initialDelay</emphasis> property and a boolean <emphasis>fixedRate</emphasis> property (the default is false, i.e.
      fixed delay):
	</para>
      <programlisting language="java">IntervalTrigger trigger = new IntervalTrigger(1000);
trigger.setInitialDelay(5000);
trigger.setFixedRate(true);</programlisting>
	<para>
		The <classname>CronTrigger</classname> simply requires a valid cron
		expression (see the Javadoc for details):
	</para>
      <programlisting language="java">CronTrigger trigger = new CronTrigger("*/10 * * * * MON-FRI");</programlisting>
	<para>
		In addition to the trigger, several other polling-related configuration
		properties may be specified:
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java">PollingConsumer consumer = new PollingConsumer(channel, handler);

consumer.setMaxMessagesPerPoll(10);
consumer.setReceiveTimeout(5000);</programlisting>
    <para>
      The <emphasis>maxMessagesPerPoll</emphasis> property specifies the maximum number of messages to receive within a given poll
      operation. This means that the poller will continue calling receive() <emphasis>without waiting</emphasis>
      until either <code>null</code> is returned or that max is reached. For example, if a poller has a 10 second
      interval trigger and a <emphasis>maxMessagesPerPoll</emphasis> setting of 25, and it is polling a channel that has 100 messages
      in its queue, all 100 messages can be retrieved within 40 seconds. It grabs 25, waits 10 seconds, grabs the
      next 25, and so on.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <emphasis>receiveTimeout</emphasis> property specifies the amount of time the poller should wait if no messages are
      available when it invokes the receive operation. For example, consider two options that seem similar on
      the surface but are actually quite different: the first has an interval trigger of 5 seconds and a receive
      timeout of 50 milliseconds while the second has an interval trigger of 50 milliseconds and a receive timeout
      of 5 seconds. The first one may receive a message up to 4950 milliseconds later than it arrived on the channel
      (if that message arrived immediately after one of its poll calls returned). On the other hand, the second
      configuration will never miss a message by more than 50 milliseconds. The difference is that the second
      option requires a thread to wait, but as a result it is able to respond much more quickly to arriving messages.
      This technique, known as <emphasis>long polling</emphasis>, can be used to emulate event-driven behavior on a polled source.
    </para>
	<para>
		A Polling Consumer may also delegate to a Spring <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename>,
		as illustrated in the following example:
	</para>
	<programlisting language="java">PollingConsumer consumer = new PollingConsumer(channel, handler);

TaskExecutor taskExecutor = context.getBean("exampleExecutor", TaskExecutor.class);
consumer.setTaskExecutor(taskExecutor);</programlisting>
	<para>
		Furthermore, a <classname>PollingConsumer</classname> has a property called
		<emphasis>adviceChain</emphasis>. This property allows you to specify a
		<interfacename>List</interfacename> of AOP Advices for handling additional
		cross cutting concerns including transactions. These advices are applied
		around the <methodname>doPoll()</methodname> method. For more in-depth
		information, please see the sections <emphasis>AOP Advice chains</emphasis>
		and <emphasis>Transaction Support</emphasis> under <xref linkend="endpoint-namespace"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		The examples above show dependency lookups, but keep in mind that these
		consumers will most often be configured as Spring <emphasis>bean definitions</emphasis>.
		In fact, Spring Integration also provides a <interfacename>FactoryBean</interfacename>
		called <classname>ConsumerEndpointFactoryBean</classname> that creates
		the appropriate consumer type based on the type of channel, and there is
		full XML namespace support to even further hide those details. The
		namespace-based configuration will be featured as each component type is
		introduced.
	</para>
      <note>
		Many of the <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> implementations are also capable of generating reply
        Messages. As mentioned above, sending Messages is trivial when compared to the Message reception. Nevertheless,
        <emphasis>when</emphasis> and <emphasis>how many</emphasis> reply Messages are sent depends on the handler
        type. For example, an <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis> waits for a number of Messages to arrive and is often
        configured as a downstream consumer for a <emphasis>Splitter</emphasis> which may generate multiple
        replies for each Message it handles. When using the namespace configuration, you do not strictly need to know
        all of the details, but it still might be worth knowing that several of these components share a common base
        class, the <classname>AbstractReplyProducingMessageHandler</classname>, and it provides a
        <methodname>setOutputChannel(..)</methodname> method.
      </note>
  </section>

  <section id="endpoint-namespace">
    <title>Namespace Support</title>
    <para>
      Throughout the reference manual, you will see specific configuration examples for endpoint elements, such as
      router, transformer, service-activator, and so on. Most of these will support an <emphasis>input-channel</emphasis> attribute and
      many will support an <emphasis>output-channel</emphasis> attribute. After being parsed, these endpoint elements produce an instance
      of either the <classname>PollingConsumer</classname> or the
      <classname>EventDrivenConsumer</classname> depending on the type of the <emphasis>input-channel</emphasis> that is
      referenced: <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename> or <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename>
      respectively. When the channel is pollable, then the polling behavior is determined based on the endpoint
      element's <emphasis>poller</emphasis> sub-element and its attributes.
    </para>

    <emphasis>Configuration</emphasis>

    <para>Below you find a <emphasis>poller</emphasis> with all available configuration options:</para>

        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:poller cron=""                                 ]]><co id="poller-xml01-co" linkends="sp-gateway-xml01" /><![CDATA[
            default="false"                         ]]><co id="poller-xml02-co" linkends="poller-xml02" /><![CDATA[
            error-channel=""                        ]]><co id="poller-xml03-co" linkends="poller-xml03" /><![CDATA[
            fixed-delay=""                          ]]><co id="poller-xml04-co" linkends="poller-xml04" /><![CDATA[
            fixed-rate=""                           ]]><co id="poller-xml05-co" linkends="poller-xml05" /><![CDATA[
            id=""                                   ]]><co id="poller-xml06-co" linkends="poller-xml06" /><![CDATA[
            max-messages-per-poll=""                ]]><co id="poller-xml07-co" linkends="poller-xml07" /><![CDATA[
            receive-timeout=""                      ]]><co id="poller-xml08-co" linkends="poller-xml08" /><![CDATA[
            ref=""                                  ]]><co id="poller-xml09-co" linkends="poller-xml09" /><![CDATA[
            task-executor=""                        ]]><co id="poller-xml10-co" linkends="poller-xml10" /><![CDATA[
            time-unit="MILLISECONDS"                ]]><co id="poller-xml11-co" linkends="poller-xml11" /><![CDATA[
            trigger="">                             ]]><co id="poller-xml12-co" linkends="poller-xml12" /><![CDATA[
            <int:advice-chain />                    ]]><co id="poller-xml13-co" linkends="poller-xml13" /><![CDATA[
            <int:transactional />                   ]]><co id="poller-xml14-co" linkends="poller-xml14" /><![CDATA[
</int:poller>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            <calloutlist>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml01-co" id="poller-xml01">
                    <para>
                        Provides the ability to configure Pollers using Cron expressions.
                        The underlying implementation uses a
                        <classname>org.springframework.scheduling.support.CronTrigger</classname>.

                        If this attribute is set, none of the following attributes
                        must be specified: <code>fixed-delay</code>, <code>trigger</code>,
                        <code>fixed-rate</code>, <code>ref</code>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml02-co" id="poller-xml02">
                    <para>
                        By setting this attribute to <emphasis>true</emphasis>,
                        it is possible to define exactly one (1) global default
                        poller. An exception is raised if more than one default
                        poller is defined in the application context.

                        Any endpoints connected to a PollableChannel (PollingConsumer)
                        or any SourcePollingChannelAdapter that does not have any
                        explicitly configured poller will then use the global default
                        Poller.
                        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>. Defaults to <code>false</code>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml03-co" id="poller-xml03">
                    <para>
                        Identifies the channel which error messages will be sent to if
                        a failure occurs in this poller's invocation. To completely
                        suppress Exceptions, provide a reference to the
                        <code>nullChannel</code>. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml04-co" id="poller-xml04">
                    <para>
                        The fixed delay trigger uses a <classname>PeriodicTrigger</classname>
                        under the covers. If the <code>time-unit</code> attribute is
                        not used, the specified value is represented in milliseconds.

                        If this attribute is set, none of the following attributes
                        must be specified: <code>fixed-rate</code>, <code>trigger</code>,
                        <code>cron</code>, <code>ref</code>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml05-co" id="poller-xml05">
                    <para>
                        The fixed rate trigger uses a <classname>PeriodicTrigger</classname>
                        under the covers. If the <code>time-unit</code> attribute is
                        not used the specified value is represented in milliseconds.

                        If this attribute is set, none of the following attributes
                        must be specified: <code>fixed-delay</code>, <code>trigger</code>,
                        <code>cron</code>, <code>ref</code>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml06-co" id="poller-xml06">
                    <para>
                        The Id referring to the Poller's underlying bean-definition,
                        which is of type
                        <classname>org.springframework.integration.scheduling.PollerMetadata</classname>.
                            The <emphasis>id</emphasis> attribute is required for
                            a top-level poller element unless it is the default
                            poller (<code>default="true"</code>).
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml07-co" id="poller-xml07">
                    <para>
                        Please see <xref linkend="channel-adapter-namespace-inbound"/>
                        for more information. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>. If
                        not specified the default values used depends on the context.

                        If a <classname>PollingConsumer</classname> is used, this atribute
                        will default to <emphasis>-1</emphasis>. However, if a
                        <classname>SourcePollingChannelAdapter</classname> is used,
                        then the <code>max-messages-per-poll</code> attribute defaults to
                        <emphasis>1</emphasis>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml08-co" id="poller-xml08">
                    <para>
                        Value is set on the underlying class <classname>PollerMetadata</classname>
                        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>. If not specified it defaults
                        to 1000 (milliseconds).
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml09-co" id="poller-xml09">
                    <para>
                        Bean reference to another top-level poller. The <code>ref</code>
                        attribute must not be present on the top-level <code>poller</code>
                        element.

                        However, if this attribute is set, none of the following attributes
                        must be specified: <code>fixed-rate</code>, <code>trigger</code>,
                        <code>cron</code>, <code>fixed-deleay</code>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml10-co" id="poller-xml10">
                    <para>
                        Provides the ability to reference a custom <emphasis>task executor</emphasis>.
                        Please see the section below titled <emphasis>TaskExecutor Support</emphasis>
                        for further information. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml11-co" id="poller-xml11">
                    <para>
						This attribute specifies the <classname>java.util.concurrent.TimeUnit</classname>
						enum value on the underlying
						<classname>org.springframework.scheduling.support.PeriodicTrigger</classname>.
						Therefore, this attribute can <emphasis>ONLY</emphasis>
						be used in combination with the <code>fixed-delay</code>
						or <code>fixed-rate</code> attributes. If combined with
						either <code>cron</code> or a <code>trigger</code> reference
						attribute, it will cause a failure.
				    </para>
				    <para>
						The minimal supported granularity for a
						<classname>PeriodicTrigger</classname> is MILLISECONDS.
						Therefore, the only available options are MILLISECONDS and
						SECONDS. If this value is not provided, then any
						<code>fixed-delay</code> or <code>fixed-rate</code> value
						will be interpreted as MILLISECONDS by default.
				    </para>
				    <para>
				        Basically this enum provides a convenience for SECONDS-based
				        interval trigger values. For hourly, daily, and monthly
				        settings, consider using a <code>cron</code> trigger instead.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml12-co" id="poller-xml12">
                    <para>
                        Reference to any spring configured bean which implements
                        the <interfacename>org.springframework.scheduling.Trigger</interfacename>
                        interface.
                        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>. However, if this attribute
                        is set, none of the following attributes must be specified:
                        <code>fixed-delay</code>, <code>fixed-rate</code>,
                        <code>cron</code>, <code>ref</code>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml13-co" id="poller-xml13">
                    <para>
                        Allows to specify extra AOP Advices to handle additional
                        cross cutting concerns. Please see the section
                        below titled <emphasis>Transaction Support</emphasis>
                        for further information. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="poller-xml14-co" id="poller-xml14">
                    <para>
                        Pollers can be made transactional. Please see the section
                        below titled <emphasis>AOP Advice chains</emphasis>
                        for further information. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.
                    </para>
                </callout>
          </calloutlist>
      </para>

    <para>
        <emphasis>Examples</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
      For example, a simple interval-based poller with a 1-second interval would be
      configured like this: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:transformer input-channel="pollable"
    ref="transformer"
    output-channel="output">
    <int:poller fixed-rate="1000"/>
</int:transformer>]]></programlisting>
	  As an alternative to <emphasis>fixed-rate</emphasis> you can also use the <emphasis>fixed-delay</emphasis> attribute.
	  </para>
	  <para>
      For a poller based on a Cron expression, use the <emphasis>cron</emphasis> attribute instead:
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:transformer input-channel="pollable"
    ref="transformer"
    output-channel="output">
    <int:poller cron="*/10 * * * * MON-FRI"/>
</int:transformer>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      If the input channel is a <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename>, then the poller configuration is
      required. Specifically, as mentioned above, the <emphasis>trigger</emphasis> is a required property of the PollingConsumer class.
      Therefore, if you omit the <emphasis>poller</emphasis> sub-element for a Polling Consumer endpoint's configuration, an Exception
      may be thrown. The exception will also be thrown if you attempt to configure a poller on the element that is
      connected to a non-pollable channel.
     </para>
     <para>
      It is also possible to create top-level pollers in which case only a <emphasis>ref</emphasis> is required:
     </para>

     <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:poller id="weekdayPoller" cron="*/10 * * * * MON-FRI"/>

<int:transformer input-channel="pollable"
    ref="transformer"
    output-channel="output">
    <int:poller ref="weekdayPoller"/>
</int:transformer>]]></programlisting>

 	<note>
	 	<para>
	 	The <emphasis>ref</emphasis> attribute is only allowed on the inner-poller definitions. Defining this attribute on a top-level
	 	poller will result in a configuration exception thrown during initialization of the Application Context.
	 	</para>
 	</note>

    <para>
 	    <emphasis>Global Default Pollers</emphasis>
    </para>

 	<para>
      In fact, to simplify the configuration even further, you can define a global default poller. A single top-level poller within
      an ApplicationContext may have the <code>default</code> attribute with a value of <emphasis>true</emphasis>. In that case, any
      endpoint with a PollableChannel for its input-channel that is defined within the same ApplicationContext and has
      no explicitly configured <emphasis>poller</emphasis> sub-element will use that default.
    </para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:poller id="defaultPoller" default="true" max-messages-per-poll="5" fixed-rate="3000"/>

<!-- No <poller/> sub-element is necessary since there is a default -->
<int:transformer input-channel="pollable"
                 ref="transformer"
                 output-channel="output"/>]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        <emphasis>Transaction Support</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
      Spring Integration also provides transaction support for the pollers so that each receive-and-forward
      operation can be performed as an atomic unit-of-work. To configure transactions for a poller, simply add the
      <emphasis>&lt;transactional/&gt;</emphasis> sub-element. The attributes for this element should be familiar to anyone who has
      experience with Spring's Transaction management:
    </para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:poller fixed-delay="1000">
    <int:transactional transaction-manager="txManager"
                       propagation="REQUIRED"
                       isolation="REPEATABLE_READ"
                       timeout="10000"
                       read-only="false"/>
</int:poller>]]></programlisting>

    <para>
        For more information please refer to <xref linkend="transaction-poller"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	    <emphasis>AOP Advice chains</emphasis>
	</para>

	<para>
	Since Spring transaction support depends on the Proxy mechanism  with <classname>TransactionInterceptor</classname> (AOP Advice) handling transactional
	behavior of the message flow initiated by the poller, some times there is a need to provide extra Advice(s) to handle other
	cross cutting behavior associated with the poller. For that poller defines an <emphasis>advice-chain</emphasis> element allowing you to add
	more advices - class that  implements <classname>MethodInterceptor</classname> interface.. 
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:service-activator id="advicedSa" input-channel="goodInputWithAdvice" ref="testBean"
		method="good" output-channel="output">
	<int:poller max-messages-per-poll="1" fixed-rate="10000">
		<int:transactional transaction-manager="txManager" />
		 <int:advice-chain>
			<ref bean="adviceA" />
			<beans:bean class="org.bar.SampleAdvice"/>
		</int:advice-chain>
	</int:poller>
</int:service-activator>]]></programlisting>
For more information on how to implement MethodInterceptor please refer to AOP sections of Spring
reference manual (section 8 and 9). Advice chain can also be applied on the poller that does not have
any transaction configuration essentially allowing you to enhance the behavior of the message flow initiated by the poller.
    </para>

    <para>
        <emphasis>TaskExecutor Support</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
      The polling threads may be executed by any instance of Spring's <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename>
      abstraction. This enables concurrency for an endpoint or group of endpoints. As of Spring 3.0, there is a <emphasis>task</emphasis>
      namespace in the core Spring Framework, and its &lt;executor/&gt; element supports the creation of a simple thread
      pool executor. That element accepts attributes for common concurrency settings such as pool-size and queue-capacity.
      Configuring a thread-pooling executor can make a substantial difference in how the endpoint performs under load. These
      settings are available per-endpoint since the performance of an endpoint is one of the major factors to consider
      (the other major factor being the expected volume on the channel to which the endpoint subscribes). To enable
      concurrency for a polling endpoint that is configured with the XML namespace support, provide the <emphasis>task-executor</emphasis>
      reference on its &lt;poller/&gt; element and then provide one or more of the properties shown below:
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:poller task-executor="pool" fixed-rate="1000"/>

<task:executor id="pool"
               pool-size="5-25"
               queue-capacity="20"
               keep-alive="120"/>]]></programlisting>
      If no <emphasis>task-executor</emphasis> is provided, the consumer's handler will be invoked in the caller's thread. Note that the
      <emphasis>caller</emphasis> is usually the default <interfacename>TaskScheduler</interfacename>
      (see <xref linkend="namespace-taskscheduler"/>). Also, keep in mind that the <emphasis>task-executor</emphasis> attribute can
      provide a reference to any implementation of Spring's <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename> interface by
      specifying the bean name. The <emphasis>executor</emphasis> element above is simply provided for convenience.
    </para>
     <para>
    	As mentioned in the background section for Polling Consumers above, you can also configure a Polling Consumer
        in such a way as to emulate event-driven behavior. With a long receive-timeout and a short interval-trigger,
        you can ensure a very timely reaction to arriving messages even on a polled message source. Note that this
        will only apply to sources that have a blocking wait call with a timeout. For example, the File poller does
        not block, each receive() call returns immediately and either contains new files or not. Therefore, even if
        a poller contains a long receive-timeout, that value would never be usable in such a scenario. On the other
        hand when using Spring Integration's own queue-based channels, the timeout value does have a chance to
        participate. The following example demonstrates how a Polling Consumer will receive Messages nearly
        instantaneously.
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:service-activator input-channel="someQueueChannel"
    output-channel="output">
    <int:poller receive-timeout="30000" fixed-rate="10"/>

</int:service-activator>]]></programlisting>
      Using this approach does not carry much overhead since internally it is nothing more then a timed-wait thread
      which does not require nearly as much CPU resource usage as a thrashing, infinite while loop for example.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="polling-consumer-change-polling-rate">
      <title>Change Polling Rate at Runtime</title>
      <para>
         When configuring Pollers with a <code>fixed-delay</code> or
         <code>fixed-rate</code> attribute, the default implementation will use
         a <classname>PeriodicTrigger</classname> instance. The
         <classname>PeriodicTrigger</classname> is part of the Core Spring Framework
         and it accepts the <emphasis>interval</emphasis> as a constructor
         argument, only. Therefore it cannot be changed at runtime.
      </para>
      <para>
         However, you can define your own implementation of the
         <interfacename>org.springframework.scheduling.Trigger</interfacename>
         interface. You could even use the PeriodicTrigger as a starting point.
         Then, you can add a setter for the interval (period), or you could even
         embed your own throttling logic within the trigger itself if desired.
         The <emphasis>period</emphasis> property will be used with each call to
         <emphasis>nextExecutionTime</emphasis> to schedule the next poll.

         To use this custom trigger within pollers, declare the bean defintion of
         the custom Trigger in your application context and inject the dependency
         into your Poller configuration using the <code>trigger</code> attribute,
         which references the custom Trigger bean instance.

         You can now obtain a reference to the Trigger bean and the polling
         interval can be changed between polls.
      </para>
      <para>
         For an example, please see the Spring Integration Samples
         project. It contains a sample called <emphasis>dynamic-poller</emphasis>,
         which uses a custom Trigger and demonstrates the ability to change the polling
         interval at runtime.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><ulink url="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-integration-samples/tree/master/intermediate">
          https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-integration-samples/tree/master/intermediate
          </ulink></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
         The sample provides a custom Trigger which implements the
         <emphasis><ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/current/javadoc-api/org/springframework/scheduling/Trigger.html">org.springframework.scheduling.Trigger</ulink></emphasis>
         interface. The sample's Trigger is based on Spring's <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/current/javadoc-api/org/springframework/scheduling/support/PeriodicTrigger.html">PeriodicTrigger</ulink>
         implementation. However, the fields of the custom trigger are not final
         and the properties have explicit getters and setters, allowing to dynamically
         change the polling period at runtime.
      </para>
      <note><para>
         It is important to note, though, that because the Trigger method is
         <emphasis>nextExecutionTime()</emphasis>, any changes to a dynamic trigger
         will not take effect until the next poll, based on the existing configuration.
         It is not possible to force a trigger to fire before it's currently
         configured next execution time.
      </para></note>
  </section>

  <section id="payload-type-conversion">
    <title>Payload Type Conversion</title>
    <para>
      Throughout the reference manual, you will also see specific configuration and implementation examples of various endpoints
      which can accept a Message or any arbitrary Object as an input parameter. In the case of an Object, such a parameter will
      be mapped to a Message payload or part of the payload or header (when using the Spring Expression Language). However there
      are times when the type of input parameter of the endpoint method does not match the type of the payload or its part.
      In this scenario we need to perform type conversion. Spring Integration provides a convenient way for registering type
      converters (using the Spring 3.x ConversionService) within its own instance of a conversion service bean named
      <emphasis>integrationConversionService</emphasis>.
      That bean is automatically created as soon as the first converter is defined using the Spring Integration infrastructure.

      To register a Converter all you need is to implement
      <interfacename>org.springframework.core.convert.converter.Converter</interfacename>,
		<interfacename>org.springframework.core.convert.converter.GenericConverter</interfacename> or
		<interfacename>org.springframework.core.convert.converter.ConverterFactory</interfacename> and define it via
      convenient namespace support:
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:converter ref="sampleConverter"/>

<bean id="sampleConverter" class="foo.bar.TestConverter"/>]]></programlisting>

      or as an inner bean:
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:converter>
    <bean class="o.s.i.config.xml.ConverterParserTests$TestConverter3"/>
</int:converter>]]></programlisting>
     </para>
	 <para>
		 Starting with <emphasis>Spring Integration 4.0</emphasis>, the above configuration is available using annotations:
		 <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[@Component
@IntegrationConverter
public class TestConverter implements Converter<Boolean, Number> {

	public Number convert(Boolean source) {
		return source ? 1 : 0;
	}

}]]></programlisting>

	or as a <code>@Configuration</code> part:
	<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[@Configuration
@EnableIntegration
public class ContextConfiguration {

	@Bean
	@IntegrationConverter
	public SerializingConverter serializingConverter() {
		return new SerializingConverter();
	}

}]]></programlisting>
	 </para>
     <important>
         <para>
             When configuring an <emphasis>Application Context</emphasis>, the
             Spring Framework allows you to add a <emphasis>conversionService</emphasis> bean
             (see <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/current/spring-framework-reference/html/validation.html#core-convert-Spring-config">
             Configuring a ConversionService</ulink> chapter). This service is used, when needed,
             to perform appropriate conversions during bean creation and configuration.
         </para>
         <para>
             In contrast, the <emphasis>integrationConversionService</emphasis> is used for runtime conversions.
             These uses are quite different; converters that are intended for use when wiring bean
             constructor-args and properties may produce unintended results if used at runtime
             for Spring Integration expression evaluation against
             Messages within Datatype Channels, Payload Type transformers etc.
         </para>
         <para>
             However, if you do want to use the Spring <emphasis>conversionService</emphasis> as
             the Spring Integration <emphasis>integrationConversionService</emphasis>,
             you can configure an <emphasis>alias</emphasis> in the Application Context:
             <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<alias name="conversionService" alias="integrationConversionService"/>]]></programlisting>
             In this case the <emphasis>conversionService</emphasis>'s Converters will be available for Spring Integration
             runtime conversion.
         </para>
	  </important>

  </section>

  <section id="async-polling">
    <title>Asynchronous polling</title>
     <para>
     If you want the polling to be asynchronous, a Poller can optionally specify a <emphasis>task-executor</emphasis> attribute
     pointing to an existing instance of any <classname>TaskExecutor</classname> bean
     (Spring 3.0 provides a convenient namespace configuration via the <code>task</code> namespace). However, there are certain things
     you must understand when configuring a Poller with a TaskExecutor. 
     </para>
     <para>
     The problem is that there are two configurations in place. The <emphasis>Poller</emphasis> and the <emphasis>TaskExecutor</emphasis>,
     and they both have to be in tune with each other otherwise you might end up creating an artificial memory leak.
     </para>
     <para>
     Let's look at the following configuration provided by one of the users on the Spring Integration
     forum (http://forum.springsource.org/showthread.php?t=94519):

      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:service-activator input-channel="publishChannel" ref="myService">
	<int:poller receive-timeout="5000" task-executor="taskExecutor" fixed-rate="50"/>
</int:service-activator>

<task:executor id="taskExecutor" pool-size="20" queue-capacity="20"/>]]></programlisting>

	The above configuration demonstrates one of those out of tune configurations.
     </para>
     <para>
     The poller keeps scheduling new tasks even though all the threads are blocked waiting for either a new message to arrive,
     or the timeout to expire. Given that there are 20 threads executing tasks with a 5 second timeout, they will be executed
     at a rate of 4 per second (5000/20 = 250ms). But, new tasks are being scheduled at a rate of 20 per second, so the internal
     queue in the task executor will grow at a rate of 16 per second (while the process is idle), so we essentially have a memory leak.
     </para>
     <para>
     One of the ways to handle this is to set the <code>queue-capacity</code> attribute of the Task Executor to 0. You can also
     manage it by specifying what to do with messages that can not be queued by setting the <code>rejection-policy</code> attribute
     of the Task Executor (e.g., DISCARD). In other words there are certain details you must understand with regard to configuring
     the TaskExecutor. Please refer to - <emphasis>Section 25 - Task Execution and Scheduling</emphasis> of the Spring reference manual
     for more detail on the subject.
     </para>
  </section>
  <section id="endpoint-inner">
	<title>Endpoint Inner Beans</title>
	<para>
		Many endpoints are composite beans; this includes all consumers and all polled inbound channel adapters. Consumers (polled or event-
		driven) delegate to a <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename>; polled adapters obtain messages by delegating to a
		<interfacename>MessageSource</interfacename>. Often, it is useful to obtain a reference to the delegate bean, perhaps to
		change configuration at runtime, or for testing. These beans can be obtained from the
		<interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename> with well-known names. <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename>s
		are registered with the application context with a bean id <code>someConsumer.handler</code> (where 'consumer' is the endpoint's
		<code>id</code> attribute). <interfacename>MessageSource</interfacename>s are registered with a bean id
		<code>somePolledAdapter.source</code>, again where 'somePolledAdapter' is the id of the adapter.
	</para>
  </section>
</section>
