<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="gemfire"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>GemFire Support</title>
  <para>
    Spring Integration provides support for VMWare vFabric GemFire
  </para>
  <section id="gemfire-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      VMWare vFabric GemFire (GemFire) is a distributed data management platform providing a key-value data grid along with advanced distributed system features such as event processing, continuous querying, and
      remote function execution. This guide assumes
      some familiarity with <ulink url="http://www.vmware.com/support/pubs/vfabric-gemfire.html">GemFire</ulink>
       and its <ulink url="http://www.vmware.com/support/developer/vfabric-gemfire/662-api/index.html">API</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
    Spring integration provides support for GemFire by providing inbound adapters for entry and continuous query events,
    an outbound adapter to write entries to the cache, and <classname>MessageStore</classname> and <classname>MessageGroupStore</classname> implementations.
    Spring integration leverages the
    <ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-gemfire">Spring Gemfire</ulink> project, providing a thin wrapper over its components.
    </para>
    <para>
    To configure the 'int-gfe' namespace, include the following elements within the headers of your XML configuration file:

	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[xmlns:int-gfe="http://www.springframework.org/schema/integration/gemfire"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/integration/gemfire
	http://www.springframework.org/schema/integration/gemfire/spring-integration-gemfire.xsd"]]></programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="gemfire-inbound">
  	<title>Inbound Channel Adapter</title>
  	<para>
  	The <emphasis>inbound-channel-adapter</emphasis> produces messages on a channel triggered by a GemFire <classname>EntryEvent</classname>. GemFire
  	generates events whenever an entry is CREATED, UPDATED, DESTROYED, or INVALIDATED in the associated region. The inbound channel adapter allows you to filter on a subset of these
  	events. For example, you may want to only produce messages in response to an entry being CREATED. In addition, the inbound channel adapter can evaluate a SpEL
  	expression if, for example, you want your message payload to contain an event property such as the new entry value.

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<gfe:cache/>
<gfe:replicated-region id="region"/>
<int-gfe:inbound-channel-adapter id="inputChannel" region="region"
    cache-events="CREATED" expression="newValue"/>]]></programlisting>

	In the above configuration, we are creating a GemFire <classname>Cache</classname> and <classname>Region</classname> using Spring GemFire's 'gfe' namespace.
	The inbound-channel-adapter requires a reference to the GemFire region for which the adapter will be listening for events. Optional attributes include <code>cache-events</code>
	which can contain a comma separated list of event types for which a message will be produced on the input channel. By default CREATED and UPDATED are enabled.
	Note that this adapter conforms to Spring integration conventions.
	If no <code>channel</code> attribute is provided, the channel will be created from the <code>id</code> attribute. This adapter also supports an <code>error-channel</code>.
	The GemFire <ulink url=
	"http://www.gemstone.com/docs/current/product/docs/japi/com/gemstone/gemfire/cache/EntryEvent.html">EntryEvent</ulink>
	is the <code>#root</code> object of the <code>expression</code> evaluation.
	Example:<programlisting><![CDATA[expression="new foo.MyEvent(key, oldValue, newValue)"]]></programlisting>
	If the <code>expression</code> attribute is not provided, the message payload will be the GemFire
	<classname>EntryEvent</classname> itself.
  	</para>
  </section>
   <section id="gemfire-cq">
  	<title>Continuous Query Inbound Channel Adapter</title>
  	<para>
  	The <emphasis>cq-inbound-channel-adapter</emphasis> produces messages a channel triggered by a GemFire continuous query or <classname>CqEvent</classname> event. Spring GemFire introduced
  	continuous query support in release 1.1, including a <classname>ContinuousQueryListenerContainer</classname> which provides a nice abstraction over the GemFire native API. This adapter requires a
  	reference to a ContinuousQueryListenerContainer, and creates a listener for a given <code>query</code> and executes the query. The continuous query acts as an event source that will fire whenever its
  	result set changes state.
  	<note>
  	GemFire queries are written in OQL and are scoped to the entire cache (not just one region). Additionally, continuous queries require a remote (i.e., running in a separate process or remote host)
  	cache server. Please consult the <ulink url="http://www.gemstone.com/docs/6.6.RC/product/docs/html/user_guide/UserGuide_GemFire.html#Continuous%20Querying">GemFire documentation</ulink> for more information on
  	implementing continuous queries.
  	</note>


  <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<gfe:client-cache id="client-cache" pool-name="client-pool"/>

<gfe:pool id="client-pool" subscription-enabled="true" >
    <!--configure server or locator here required to address the cache server -->
</gfe:pool>

<gfe:client-region id="test" cache-ref="client-cache" pool-name="client-pool"/>

<gfe:cq-listener-container id="queryListenerContainer" cache="client-cache"
    pool-name="client-pool"/>

<int-gfe:cq-inbound-channel-adapter id="inputChannel"
    cq-listener-container="queryListenerContainer"
    query="select * from /test"/>]]></programlisting>

	In the above configuration, we are creating a GemFire client cache
	(recall a remote cache server is required for this implementation and its address is configured as a sub-element of the pool), a client region and a <classname>ContinuousQueryListenerContainer</classname>
	using Spring GemFire. 	The continuous query inbound channel adapter requires a <code>cq-listener-container</code> attribute which contains a reference to the <classname>ContinuousQueryListenerContainer</classname>. Optionally,
  	it accepts an <code>expression</code> attribute which uses SpEL to transform the <code>CqEvent</code> or extract an individual property as needed. The cq-inbound-channel-adapter provides a
  	<code>query-events</code> attribute, containing a comma separated list of event types for which a message will be produced on the input channel. Available event types are CREATED, UPDATED, DESTROYED,
  	REGION_DESTROYED, REGION_INVALIDATED. CREATED and UPDATED are enabled by default. Additional optional attributes include, <code>query-name</code> which provides an optional query name, and
	<code>expression</code> which works as described in the above section, and <code>durable</code> - a boolean value indicating if the query is durable (false by default).
	Note that this adapter conforms to Spring integration conventions.
	If no <code>channel</code> attribute is provided, the channel will be created from the <code>id</code> attribute. This adapter also supports an <code>error-channel</code>
  	</para>
  </section>

   <section id="gemfire-outbound">
  	<title>Outbound Channel Adapter</title>
  	<para>
  	The <emphasis>outbound-channel-adapter</emphasis> writes cache entries mapped from the message payload. In its simplest form, it expects a
  	payload of type <classname>java.util.Map</classname> and puts the map entries into its configured region.

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-gfe:outbound-channel-adapter id="cacheChannel" region="region"/>]]></programlisting>

	Given the above configuration, an exception will be thrown if the payload is not a Map. Additionally, the outbound channel adapter can be configured to create a
	map of cache entries using SpEL of course.

	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-gfe:outbound-channel-adapter id="cacheChannel" region="region">
    <int-gfe:cache-entries>
        <entry key="payload.toUpperCase()" value="payload.toLowerCase()"/>
        <entry key="'foo'" value="'bar'"/>
    </int-gfe:cache-entries>
</int-gfe:outbound-channel-adapter>]]></programlisting>
	In the above configuration, the inner element <code>cache-entries</code> is semantically equivalent to Spring 'map' element. The adapter interprets the <code>key</code> and
	<code>value</code> attributes as SpEL expressions with the message as the evaluation context. Note that this contain
	arbitrary cache entries (not only those derived from the message) and that literal values must be enclosed in single quotes. In the above example, if the message sent to
	<code>cacheChannel</code> has a String payload with a value "Hello", two entries <code>[HELLO:hello, foo:bar]</code> will be written (created or updated) in the cache region.
	This adapter also supports the <code>order</code> attribute which may be useful if it is bound to a PublishSubscribeChannel.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="gemfire-message-store">
    <title>Gemfire Message Store</title>

	<para>
    As described in EIP, a <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/MessageStore.html">Message Store</ulink> allows you to persist Messages.
    This can be very useful when dealing with components that have a capability to buffer messages
    (<emphasis>QueueChannel, Aggregator, Resequencer</emphasis>, etc.) if reliability is a concern.
    In Spring Integration, the MessageStore strategy also provides the foundation for the
	<ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/StoreInLibrary.html">ClaimCheck</ulink> pattern, which is described in EIP as well.
	</para>

	<para>
    Spring Integration's Gemfire module provides the <classname>GemfireMessageStore</classname> which is an implementation of both the
    the <classname>MessageStore</classname> strategy (mainly used by the <emphasis>QueueChannel</emphasis> and <emphasis>ClaimCheck</emphasis>
    patterns) and the <classname>MessageGroupStore</classname> strategy (mainly used by the <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>Resequencer</emphasis> patterns).
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="gemfireMessageStore" class="o.s.i.gemfire.store.GemfireMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg ref="myCache"/>
</bean>

<bean id="myCache" class="org.springframework.data.gemfire.CacheFactoryBean"/>

<int:channel id="somePersistentQueueChannel">
    <int:queue message-store="gemfireMessageStore"/>
<int:channel>

<int:aggregator input-channel="inputChannel" output-channel="outputChannel"
    message-store="gemfireMessageStore"/>]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
Above is a sample <classname>GemfireMessageStore</classname> configuration that shows its usage by a <emphasis>QueueChannel</emphasis> and an <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis>. As you can see it is a normal Spring bean configuration. The simplest configuration requires a reference to a <classname>GemFireCache</classname> (created by <classname>CacheFactoryBean</classname>) as a constructor argument. If the cache is standalone, i.e., embedded in the same JVM, the MessageStore will create a message store region named "messageStoreRegion". If your application requires customization of the messageStore region, for example, multiple Gemfire message stores each with its own region, you can configure a region for each message store instance and use the <classname>Region</classname> as the constructor argument:

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="gemfireMessageStore" class="o.s.i.gemfire.store.GemfireMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg ref="myRegion"/>
</bean>

<gfe:cache/>

<gfe:replicated-region id="myRegion"/>]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>
In the above examle, the cache and region are configured using the spring-gemfire namespace (not to be confused with the spring-integration-gemfire namespace). Often it is desirable for the message store to be maintained in one or more remote cache servers in a client-server configuration (See the
<ulink url="http://www.vmware.com/support/pubs/vfabric-gemfire.html">GemFire product documentation</ulink> for more details). In this case, you configure a client cache, client region, and client pool and inject the region into the MessageStore. Here is an example:

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="gemfireMessageStore"
    class="org.springframework.integration.gemfire.store.GemfireMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg ref="myRegion"/>
</bean>

<gfe:client-cache/>

<gfe:client-region id="myRegion" shortcut="PROXY" pool-name="messageStorePool"/>

<gfe:pool id="messageStorePool">
    <gfe:server host="localhost" port="40404" />
</gfe:pool>]]></programlisting>
</para>
<para>
Note the <emphasis>pool</emphasis> element is configured with the address of a cache server (a locator may be substituted here). The region is configured as a 'PROXY' so that no data will be stored locally. The region's id corresponds to a region with the same name configured in the cache server.
</para>
</section>
	<section id="gemfire-lock-registry">
		<title>Gemfire Lock Registry</title>

		<para>
			Starting with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, the <classname>GemfireLockRegistry</classname> is
			available. Certain components (for example aggregator and resequencer) use a lock obtained from
			a <interfacename>LockRegistry</interfacename> instance to ensure
			that only one thread is manipulating a group at a time. The <classname>DefaultLockRegistry</classname>
			performs this function within a single component; you can now configure an external lock registry
			on these components. When used with a shared <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename>,
			the <classname>GemfireLockRegistry</classname> can be use to provide this functionality across
			multiple application instances, such that only one instance can manipulate the group at a time.
			<note>
				One of the <classname>GemfireLockRegistry</classname> constructors requires a <interfacename>Region</interfacename>
				as an argument; it is used to obtain a <interfacename>Lock</interfacename> via the
				<code>getDistributedLock()</code> method. This operation requires <code>GLOBAL</code>
				scope for the <interfacename>Region</interfacename>.
				Another constructor requires <interfacename>Cache</interfacename> and the <interfacename>Region</interfacename>
				will be created with <code>GLOBAL</code> scope and with the name <code>LockRegistry</code>.
			</note>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="gemfire-metadata-store">
		<title>Gemfire Metadata Store</title>
		<para>
			As of <emphasis>Spring Integration 4.0</emphasis>, a new Gemfire-based
			<interfacename>MetadataStore</interfacename>
			(<xref linkend="metadata-store"/>) implementation is available. The <classname>GemfireMetadataStore</classname>
			can be used to maintain metadata state
			across application restarts. This new <interfacename>MetadataStore</interfacename>
			implementation can be used with adapters such as:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><xref linkend="twitter-inbound"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="feed-inbound-channel-adapter"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="file-reading"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ftp-inbound"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="sftp-inbound"/></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			In order to instruct these adapters to use the new <classname>GemfireMetadataStore</classname>,
			simply declare a Spring bean using the bean name <emphasis role="bold">metadataStore</emphasis>.
			The <emphasis>Twitter Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> and the
			<emphasis>Feed Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> will both automatically
			pick up and use the declared <classname>GemfireMetadataStore</classname>.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				The <classname>GemfireMetadataStore</classname> also implements
				<interfacename>ConcurrentMetadataStore</interfacename>, allowing it to be reliably shared across
				multiple application instances where only one instance will be allowed to store or modify a key's value.
				These methods give various levels of concurrency guarantees based on the scope and data policy of the region.
				They are implemented in the peer cache and client/server cache but are disallowed in peer Regions having
				NORMAL or EMPTY data policies.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>
</chapter>
