<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xml:id="jmx" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
	xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title id="jmx.title">JMX Support</title>

	<para>
		Spring Integration provides <emphasis>Channel Adapters</emphasis> for
		receiving and publishing JMX Notifications. There is also an
		<emphasis>Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> for
		polling JMX MBean attribute values, and an <emphasis>Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis>
		for invoking JMX MBean operations.
	</para>

	<section id="jmx-notification-listening-channel-adapter">
		<title>Notification Listening Channel Adapter</title>

		<para>
			The <emphasis>Notification-listening Channel Adapter</emphasis> requires
			a JMX ObjectName for the MBean that publishes notifications to which
			this listener should be registered. A very simple configuration might
			look like this:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-jmx:notification-listening-channel-adapter id="adapter"
    channel="channel"
    object-name="example.domain:name=publisher"/>]]></programlisting>
		<tip>
			The <emphasis>notification-listening-channel-adapter</emphasis>
			registers with an <interfacename>MBeanServer</interfacename> at
			startup, and the default bean name is <emphasis>mbeanServer</emphasis>
			which happens to be the same bean name generated when using
			Spring's <emphasis>&lt;context:mbean-server/&gt;</emphasis> element.
			If you need to use a different name, be sure to include the
			<emphasis>mbean-server</emphasis> attribute.
		</tip>
		<para>
			The adapter can also accept a reference to a
			<interfacename>NotificationFilter</interfacename> and a
			<emphasis>handback</emphasis> Object to provide some context that is
			passed back with each Notification. Both of those attributes are optional.
			Extending the above example to include those attributes as well as an
			explicit <interfacename>MBeanServer</interfacename> bean name would
			produce the following:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-jmx:notification-listening-channel-adapter id="adapter"
    channel="channel"
    mbean-server="someServer"
    object-name="example.domain:name=somePublisher"
    notification-filter="notificationFilter"
    handback="myHandback"/>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			Since the <emphasis>Notification-listening Channel Adapter</emphasis>
			is registered with the <interfacename>MBeanServer</interfacename> directly,
			it is event-driven and does not require any poller configuration.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="jmx-notification-publishing-channel-adapter">
		<title>Notification Publishing Channel Adapter</title>

		<para>
			The <emphasis>Notification-publishing Channel Adapter</emphasis> is
			relatively simple. It only requires a JMX ObjectName in its
			configuration as shown below.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<context:mbean:export/>

<int-jmx:notification-publishing-channel-adapter id="adapter"
    channel="channel"
    object-name="example.domain:name=publisher"/>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			It does also require that an <classname>MBeanExporter</classname> be
			present in the context. That is why the <emphasis>&lt;context:mbean-export/&gt;</emphasis>
			element is shown above as well.
		</para>
		<para>
			When Messages are sent to the channel for this adapter, the
			Notification is created from the Message content. If the payload is a
			String it will be passed as the <emphasis>message</emphasis> text
			for the Notification. Any other payload type will be passed as the
			<emphasis>userData</emphasis> of the Notification.
		</para>
		<para>
			JMX Notifications also have a <emphasis>type</emphasis>, and it should be a
			dot-delimited String. There are two ways to provide the
			<emphasis>type</emphasis>. Precedence will always be given to a
			Message header value associated with the <code>JmxHeaders.NOTIFICATION_TYPE</code>
			key. On the other hand, you can rely on a fallback <emphasis>default-notification-type</emphasis>
			attribute provided in the configuration.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<context:mbean:export/>

<int-jmx:notification-publishing-channel-adapter id="adapter"
    channel="channel"
    object-name="example.domain:name=publisher"
    default-notification-type="some.default.type"/>]]></programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="jmx-attribute-polling-channel-adapter">
		<title>Attribute Polling Channel Adapter</title>

		<para>
			The <emphasis>Attribute Polling Channel Adapter</emphasis> is useful
			when you have a requirement, to periodically check on some value that
			is available through an MBean as a managed attribute. The poller can
			be configured in the same way as any other polling adapter in
			Spring Integration (or it's possible to rely on the default poller).
			The <emphasis>object-name</emphasis> and <emphasis>attribute-name</emphasis>
			are required. An MBeanServer reference is also required, but it will
			automatically check for a bean named <emphasis>mbeanServer</emphasis>
			by default, just like the <emphasis>Notification-listening Channel Adapter</emphasis>
			described above.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-jmx:attribute-polling-channel-adapter id="adapter"
    channel="channel"
    object-name="example.domain:name=someService"
    attribute-name="InvocationCount">
        <int:poller max-messages-per-poll="1" fixed-rate="5000"/>
</int-jmx:attribute-polling-channel-adapter>]]></programlisting>
	</section>

	<section id="jmx-operation-invoking-channel-adapter">
		<title>Operation Invoking Channel Adapter</title>

		<para>
			The <emphasis>operation-invoking-channel-adapter</emphasis> enables
			Message-driven invocation of any managed operation exposed by an MBean.
			Each invocation requires the operation name to be invoked and the
			ObjectName of the target MBean. Both of these must be explicitly provided
			via adapter configuration:
		</para>
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-jmx:operation-invoking-channel-adapter id="adapter"
    object-name="example.domain:name=TestBean"
    operation-name="ping"/>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			Then the adapter only needs to be able to discover the <emphasis>mbeanServer</emphasis>
			bean. If a different bean name is required, then provide the
			<emphasis>mbean-server</emphasis> attribute with a reference.
		</para>
		<para>
			The payload of the Message will be mapped to the parameters of the
			operation, if any. A Map-typed payload with String keys is treated as
			name/value pairs, whereas a List or array would be passed as a simple
			argument list (with no explicit parameter names). If the operation
			requires a single parameter value, then the payload can represent that
			single value, and if the operation requires no parameters, then the
			payload would be ignored.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to expose a channel for a single common operation to be
			invoked by Messages that need not contain headers, then that option
			works well.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="jmx-operation-invoking-outbound-gateway">
		<title>Operation Invoking Outbound Gateway</title>

		<para>
			Similar to the <emphasis>operation-invoking-channel-adapter</emphasis>
			Spring Integration also provides a <emphasis>operation-invoking-outbound-gateway</emphasis>,
			which could be used when dealing with non-void operations and a return
			value is required. Such return value will be sent as message payload
			to the <emphasis>reply-channel</emphasis> specified by this Gateway.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-jmx:operation-invoking-outbound-gateway request-channel="requestChannel"
   reply-channel="replyChannel"
   object-name="o.s.i.jmx.config:type=TestBean,name=testBeanGateway"
   operation-name="testWithReturn"/>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			Another way of providing the <emphasis>reply-channel</emphasis> is by
			setting the <interfacename>MessageHeaders.REPLY_CHANNEL</interfacename>
			Message Header.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="jmx-mbean-exporter">
		<title>MBean Exporter</title>

		<para>
			Spring Integration components themselves may be exposed as MBeans
			when the <classname>IntegrationMBeanExporter</classname> is configured. To
			create an instance of the <classname>IntegrationMBeanExporter</classname>,
			define a bean and provide a reference to an <interfacename>MBeanServer</interfacename>
			and a domain name (if desired). The domain can be left out, in which
			case the default domain is <emphasis>org.springframework.integration</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-jmx:mbean-export default-domain="my.company.domain" server="mbeanServer"/>

<bean id="mbeanServer" class="org.springframework.jmx.support.MBeanServerFactoryBean">
    <property name="locateExistingServerIfPossible" value="true"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			Once the exporter is defined, start up your application with:
		</para>
		<screen>-Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote
    -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.port=6969
    -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.ssl=false
    -Dcom.sun.management.jmxremote.authenticate=false</screen>
		<para>
			Then start JConsole (free with the JDK), and connect to the local process on
			<literal>localhost:6969</literal> to get a look at the management
			endpoints exposed. (The port and client are just examples to get you
			started quickly, there are other JMX clients available and some offer more
			sophisticated features than JConsole.)
		</para>

		<para>
			The MBean exporter is orthogonal to the one provided in Spring core
			- it registers message channels and message handlers, but not itself. You
			can expose the exporter itself, and certain other components in Spring
			Integration, using the standard <literal>&lt;context:mbean-export/&gt;</literal>
			tag. The exporter has a couple of useful metrics attached to it, for
			instance a count of the number of active handlers and the number of
			queued messages (these would both be important if you wanted to
			shutdown the context without losing any messages).
		</para>

		<section id="jmx-mbean-features">
			<title>MBean ObjectNames</title>

			<para>
				All the <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename>,
				<interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> and
				<interfacename>MessageSource</interfacename> instances
				in the application are wrapped by the MBean exporter to provide
				management and monitoring features. The generated JMX object names
				for each component type are listed in the table below:
			</para>

			<table>
				<title />

				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
					<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="3*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry align="center">Component Type</entry>
							<entry align="center">ObjectName</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>MessageChannel</entry>
							<entry>o.s.i:type=MessageChannel,name=&lt;channelName&gt;</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>MessageSource</entry>
							<entry>o.s.i:type=MessageSource,name=&lt;channelName&gt;,bean=&lt;source&gt;</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>MessageHandler</entry>
							<entry>o.s.i:type=MessageSource,name=&lt;channelName&gt;,bean=&lt;source&gt;</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<para>
				The <emphasis>bean</emphasis> attribute in the object names for
				sources and handlers takes one of the values in the table below:
			</para>

			<table>
				<title />

				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
					<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="3*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry align="center">Bean Value</entry>
							<entry align="center">Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>endpoint</entry>
							<entry>The bean name of the enclosing endpoint (e.g.
								&lt;service-activator&gt;) if there is one
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>anonymous</entry>
							<entry>An indication that the enclosing endpoint didn't have a
								user-specified bean name, so the JMX name is the input channel
								name
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>internal</entry>
							<entry>For well-known Spring Integration default
								components
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>handler</entry>
							<entry>None of the above: fallback to the
								<literal>toString()</literal> of the object being monitored
								(handler or source)
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>

		<section id="jmx-channel-features">
			<title>MessageChannel MBean Features</title>

			<para>
				Message channels report metrics according to their concrete type.
				If you are looking at a <classname>DirectChannel</classname> you
				will see statistics for the send operation. If it is a
				<classname>QueueChannel</classname> you will also see statistics for the
				receive operation. In both cases there are some metrics that are simple
				counters (message count and error count), and some that are estimates of
				averages of interesting quantities. The algorithms used to calculate
				these estimates are described briefly in the table below:
			</para>

			<table>
				<title />

				<tgroup cols="3">
					<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
					<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1.5*"/>
					<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="3*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry align="center">Metric Type</entry>
							<entry align="center">Example</entry>
							<entry align="center">Algorithm</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Count</entry>
							<entry>Send Count</entry>
							<entry>Simple incrementer. Increase by one when an event
								occurs.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Duration</entry>
							<entry>Send Duration (method execution time in
								milliseconds)
							</entry>
							<entry>Exponential Moving Average with decay factor 10. Average
								of the method execution time over roughly the last 10
								measurements.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Rate</entry>
							<entry>Send Rate (number of operations per second)</entry>
							<entry>Inverse of Exponential Moving Average of the interval
								between events with decay in time (lapsing over 60 seconds) and
								per measurement (last 10 events).
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Ratio</entry>
							<entry>Send Error Ratio (ratio of errors to total sends)</entry>
							<entry>Estimate the success ratio as the Exponential Moving
								Average of the series composed of values 1 for success and 0 for
								failure (decaying as per the rate measurement over time and
								events). Error ratio is 1 - success ratio.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>

			<para>
				A feature of the time-based average estimates is that they decay
				with time if no new measurements arrive. To help interpret the behaviour
				over time, the time (in seconds) since the last measurement is also
				exposed as a metric.
			</para>

			<para>
				There are two basic exponential models: decay per measurement
				(appropriate for duration and anything where the number of measurements
				is part of the metric), and decay per time unit (more suitable for rate
				measurements where the time in between measurements is part of the
				metric). Both models depend on the fact that
			</para>
			<screen>S(n) = sum(i=0,i=n) w(i) x(i)</screen>
			<para>
				has a special form when <literal>w(i) = r^i</literal>, with
				<literal>r=constant</literal>:
			</para>
			<screen>S(n) = x(n) + r S(n-1)</screen>
			<para>
				(so you only have to store <literal>S(n-1)</literal>, not the whole series
				<literal>x(i)</literal>, to generate a new metric estimate from the last
				measurement). The algorithms used in the duration metrics use
				<literal>r=exp(-1/M)</literal> with <literal>M=10</literal>. The net
				effect is that the estimate <literal>S(n)</literal> is more heavily
				weighted to recent measurements and is composed roughly of the last
				<literal>M</literal> measurements. So <literal>M</literal> is the
				"window" or lapse rate of the estimate In the case of the vanilla moving
				average, <literal>i</literal> is a counter over the number of
				measurements. In the case of the rate we interpret <literal>i</literal>
				as the elapsed time, or a combination of elapsed time and a counter (so
				the metric estimate contains contributions roughly from the last
				<literal>M</literal> measurements and the last <literal>T</literal>
				seconds).
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</section>

