<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="message"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Message</title>
  <para>
    The Spring Integration <interfacename>Message</interfacename> is a generic container for data. Any object can
    be provided as the payload, and each <interfacename>Message</interfacename> also includes headers containing
    user-extensible properties as key-value pairs.
  </para>

  <section id="message-interface">
    <title>The Message Interface</title>
    <para>Here is the definition of the <interfacename>Message</interfacename> interface:
      <programlisting language="java">public interface Message&lt;T&gt; {

    T getPayload();

    MessageHeaders getHeaders();

}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      The <interfacename>Message</interfacename> is obviously a very important part of the API. By encapsulating the
      data in a generic wrapper, the messaging system can pass it around without any knowledge of the data's type. As
      an application evolves to support new types, or when the types themselves are modified and/or extended, the
      messaging system will not be affected by such changes. On the other hand, when some component in the messaging
      system <emphasis>does</emphasis> require access to information about the <interfacename>Message</interfacename>,
      such metadata can typically be stored to and retrieved from the metadata in the Message Headers.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="message-headers">
    <title>Message Headers</title>
  <para>
      Just as Spring Integration allows any Object to be used as the payload of a Message, it also supports any Object
      types as header values. In fact, the <classname>MessageHeaders</classname> class implements the
      <emphasis>java.util.Map</emphasis> interface:
      <programlisting language="java">public final class MessageHeaders implements Map&lt;String, Object&gt;, Serializable {
  ...
}</programlisting>
      <note>
        Even though the MessageHeaders implements Map, it is effectively a read-only implementation. Any attempt to
        <emphasis>put</emphasis> a value in the Map will result in an <classname>UnsupportedOperationException</classname>.
        The same applies for <emphasis>remove</emphasis> and <emphasis>clear</emphasis>. Since Messages may be passed to
        multiple consumers, the structure of the Map cannot be modified. Likewise, the Message's payload Object can not
        be <emphasis>set</emphasis> after the initial creation. However, the mutability of the header values themselves
        (or the payload Object) is intentionally left as a decision for the framework user.
      </note>
    </para>
    <para>
      As an implementation of Map, the headers can obviously be retrieved by calling <methodname>get(..)</methodname>
      with the name of the header. Alternatively, you can provide the expected <emphasis>Class</emphasis> as an
      additional parameter. Even better, when retrieving one of the pre-defined values, convenient getters are
      available. Here is an example of each of these three options:
      <programlisting language="java"> Object someValue = message.getHeaders().get("someKey");

 CustomerId customerId = message.getHeaders().get("customerId", CustomerId.class);

 Long timestamp = message.getHeaders().getTimestamp();
 </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      The following Message headers are pre-defined:
      <table id="message-headers-table">
        <title>Pre-defined Message Headers</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec align="left" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry align="center">Header Name</entry>
              <entry align="center">Header Type</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>ID</entry>
              <entry>java.util.UUID</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>TIMESTAMP</entry>
              <entry>java.lang.Long</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>REPLY_CHANNEL</entry>
              <entry>java.lang.Object (can be a String or MessageChannel)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>ERROR_CHANNEL</entry>
              <entry>java.lang.Object (can be a String or MessageChannel)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
    <para>
      Many inbound and outbound adapter implementations will also provide and/or expect certain headers, and additional
      user-defined headers can also be configured.
    </para>
	  <section id="message-header-accessor">
		  <title>MessageHeaderAccessor API</title>
		  <para>
			  Since Spring Framework 4.0 and Spring Integration 4.0, the core Messaging abstraction has been moved to
			  the <emphasis>spring-messaging</emphasis> module and the new <classname>MessageHeaderAccessor</classname> API
			  has been introduced to provide additional abstraction over Messaging implementations. All Spring
			  Integration specific Message Headers constants are now declared in the
			  <classname>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor</classname>:
			  <table id="integration-message-headers-table">
				  <title>Pre-defined Message Headers</title>
				  <tgroup cols="2">
					  <colspec align="left" />
					  <thead>
						  <row>
							  <entry align="center">Header Name</entry>
							  <entry align="center">Header Type</entry>
						  </row>
					  </thead>
					  <tbody>
						  <row>
							  <entry>CORRELATION_ID</entry>
							  <entry>java.lang.Object</entry>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							  <entry>SEQUENCE_NUMBER</entry>
							  <entry>java.lang.Integer</entry>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							  <entry>SEQUENCE_SIZE</entry>
							  <entry>java.lang.Integer</entry>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							  <entry>EXPIRATION_DATE</entry>
							  <entry>java.lang.Long</entry>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							  <entry>PRIORITY</entry>
							  <entry>java.lang.Integer</entry>
						  </row>
					  </tbody>
				  </tgroup>
			  </table>
		  </para>
		  <para>
			Convenient typed getters for these headers are provided on the
			<classname>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor</classname> class:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor accessor = new IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor(message);
int sequenceNumber = accessor.getSequenceNumber();
Object correlationId = accessor.getCorrelationId();
...]]></programlisting>
		  </para>
	  </section>
    <section id="message-id-generation">
        <title>Message ID Generation</title>
        <para>
          When a message transitions through an application, each time it is
          mutated (e.g. by a transformer) a new message id is assigned. The message id is
          a <code>UUID</code>. Beginning with <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis>,
          the default strategy used for id generation is more efficient than the previous
          <code>java.util.UUID.randomUUID()</code> implementation. It uses simple random
          numbers based on a secure random seed, instead of creating a secure random
          number each time.
        </para>
        <para>
          A different UUID generation strategy can be selected by declaring a bean that implements
          <interfacename>org.springframework.util.IdGenerator</interfacename> in the application context.
        </para>
        <important>
          Only one UUID generation strategy can be used in a classloader. This means that if
          two or more application contexts are running in the same classloader, they will share
          the same strategy. If one of the contexts changes the strategy, it will be used by
          all contexts. If two or more contexts in the same classloader declare a bean of type
          <interfacename>org.springframework.util.IdGenerator</interfacename>, they must all be an instance
          of the same class, otherwise the context attempting to replace a custom strategy will
          fail to initialize. If the strategy is the same, but parameterized, the strategy in the
          first context to initialize will be used.
        </important>
        <para>
          In addition to the default strategy, two additional <interfacename>IdGenerators</interfacename>
          are provided; <classname>org.springframework.util.JdkIdGenerator</classname> uses the previous
          <code>UUID.randomUUID()</code> mechanism;
          <classname>org.springframework.integration.support.IdGenerators.SimpleIncrementingIdGenerator</classname>
          can be used in cases where a UUID is not really needed and a simple incrementing
          value is sufficient.
        </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="message-implementations">
  <title>Message Implementations</title>
    <para>
      The base implementation of the <interfacename>Message</interfacename> interface is
      <classname>GenericMessage&lt;T&gt;</classname>, and it provides two constructors:
      <programlisting language="java">new GenericMessage&lt;T&gt;(T payload);

new GenericMessage&lt;T&gt;(T payload, Map&lt;String, Object&gt; headers)</programlisting>
      When a Message is created, a random unique id will be generated. The constructor that accepts a Map of headers
      will copy the provided headers to the newly created Message.
    </para>
    <para>
    There is also a convenient implementation of <interfacename>Message</interfacename> designed to communicate
    error conditions. This implementation takes <classname>Throwable</classname> object as its payload:
      <programlisting language="java">ErrorMessage message = new ErrorMessage(someThrowable);

Throwable t = message.getPayload();</programlisting>
      Notice that this implementation takes advantage of the fact that the <classname>GenericMessage</classname>
      base class is parameterized. Therefore, as shown in both examples, no casting is necessary when retrieving
      the Message payload Object.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="message-builder">
    <title>The MessageBuilder Helper Class</title>
    <para>
      You may notice that the Message interface defines retrieval methods for its payload and headers but no setters.
      The reason for this is that a Message cannot be modified after its initial creation. Therefore, when a Message
      instance is sent to multiple consumers (e.g. through a Publish Subscribe Channel), if one of those consumers
      needs to send a reply with a different payload type, it will need to create a new Message. As a result, the
      other consumers are not affected by those changes. Keep in mind, that multiple consumers may access the same
      payload instance or header value, and whether such an instance is itself immutable is a decision left to the
      developer. In other words, the contract for Messages is similar to that of an
      <emphasis>unmodifiable Collection</emphasis>, and the MessageHeaders' map further exemplifies that; even though
      the MessageHeaders class implements <interfacename>java.util.Map</interfacename>, any attempt to invoke a
      <emphasis>put</emphasis> operation (or 'remove' or 'clear') on the MessageHeaders will result in an
      <classname>UnsupportedOperationException</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Rather than requiring the creation and population of a Map to pass into the GenericMessage constructor, Spring
      Integration does provide a far more convenient way to construct Messages: <classname>MessageBuilder</classname>.
      The MessageBuilder provides two factory methods for creating Messages from either an existing Message or with a
      payload Object. When building from an existing Message, the headers <emphasis>and payload</emphasis> of that
      Message will be copied to the new Message:
      <programlisting language="java">Message&lt;String&gt; message1 = MessageBuilder.withPayload("test")
        .setHeader("foo", "bar")
        .build();

Message&lt;String&gt; message2 = MessageBuilder.fromMessage(message1).build();

assertEquals("test", message2.getPayload());
assertEquals("bar", message2.getHeaders().get("foo"));</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      If you need to create a Message with a new payload but still want to copy the
      headers from an existing Message, you can use one of the 'copy' methods.
      <programlisting language="java">Message&lt;String&gt; message3 = MessageBuilder.withPayload("test3")
        .copyHeaders(message1.getHeaders())
        .build();

Message&lt;String&gt; message4 = MessageBuilder.withPayload("test4")
        .setHeader("foo", 123)
        .copyHeadersIfAbsent(message1.getHeaders())
        .build();

assertEquals("bar", message3.getHeaders().get("foo"));
assertEquals(123, message4.getHeaders().get("foo"));</programlisting>
      Notice that the <methodname>copyHeadersIfAbsent</methodname> does not overwrite existing values. Also, in the
      second example above, you can see how to set any user-defined header with <methodname>setHeader</methodname>.
      Finally, there are set methods available for the predefined headers as well as a non-destructive method for
      setting any header (MessageHeaders also defines constants for the pre-defined header names).
      <programlisting language="java">Message&lt;Integer&gt; importantMessage = MessageBuilder.withPayload(99)
        .setPriority(5)
        .build();

assertEquals(5, importantMessage.getHeaders().getPriority());

Message&lt;Integer&gt; lessImportantMessage = MessageBuilder.fromMessage(importantMessage)
        .setHeaderIfAbsent(IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.PRIORITY, 2)
        .build();

assertEquals(2, lessImportantMessage.getHeaders().getPriority());
</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      The <code>priority</code> header is only considered when using a <classname>PriorityChannel</classname>
      (as described in the next chapter). It is defined as  <emphasis>java.lang.Integer</emphasis>.
    </para>
  </section>

</section>
