<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="mongodb"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <title>MongoDb Support</title>

  <para>
    As of version 2.1 Spring Integration introduces support for <ulink url="http://www.mongodb.org/">MongoDB</ulink>:
    a <emphasis>"high-performance, open source, document-oriented database"</emphasis>.
    This support comes in the form of a MongoDB-based MessageStore.
  </para>

  <section id="mongodb-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      To download, install, and run MongoDB please refer to the <ulink url="http://www.mongodb.org/downloads">MongoDB documentation</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="mongodb-connection">
    <title>Connecting to MongoDb</title>

    <para>To begin interacting with MongoDB you first need to connect to it. Spring Integration builds on the support provided by another
    Spring project, <ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-data/mongodb">Spring Data MongoDB</ulink>, which provides a factory
    class called <classname>MongoDbFactory</classname> that simplifies integration with the MongoDB Client API.</para>

    <para><emphasis>MongoDbFactory</emphasis> </para>

    <para>
    To connect to MongoDB you can use an implementation of the <classname>MongoDbFactory</classname> interface:

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface MongoDbFactory {

	/**
	 * Creates a default {@link DB} instance.
	 *
	 * @return the DB instance
	 * @throws DataAccessException
	 */
	DB getDb() throws DataAccessException;

	/**
	 * Creates a {@link DB} instance to access the database with the given name.
	 *
	 * @param dbName must not be {@literal null} or empty.
	 *
	 * @return the DB instance
	 * @throws DataAccessException
	 */
	DB getDb(String dbName) throws DataAccessException;
}]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>The example below shows <classname>SimpleMongoDbFactory</classname>, the out-of-the-box implementation:</para>

    <para>In Java:
    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[MongoDbFactory mongoDbFactory = new SimpleMongoDbFactory(new Mongo(), "test");]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>Or in Spring's XML configuration:
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="mongoDbFactory" class="o.s.data.mongodb.core.SimpleMongoDbFactory">
    <constructor-arg>
        <bean class="com.mongodb.Mongo"/>
    </constructor-arg>
    <constructor-arg value="test"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
    As you can see <classname>SimpleMongoDbFactory</classname> takes two arguments: 1) a <classname>Mongo</classname> instance and
    2) a String specifying the name of the database. If you need to configure properties such as <code>host</code>, <code>port</code>, etc,
    you can pass those using one of the constructors provided by the underlying <classname>Mongo</classname> class.
    For more information on how to configure MongoDB, please refer to the
<ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-data/data-document/docs/current/reference/html/">Spring-Data-Document</ulink> reference.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="mongodb-message-store">
    <title>MongoDB Message Store</title>

    <para>
    As described in EIP, a <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/MessageStore.html">Message Store</ulink>  allows you to persist Messages.
    This can be very useful when dealing with components that have a capability to buffer messages
    (<emphasis>QueueChannel, Aggregator, Resequencer</emphasis>, etc.) if reliability is a concern.
    In Spring Integration, the MessageStore strategy also provides the foundation for the
    <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/StoreInLibrary.html">ClaimCheck</ulink> pattern, which is described in EIP as well.
    </para>

    <para>
    Spring Integration's MongoDB module provides the <classname>MongoDbMessageStore</classname> which is an implementation of both
    the <classname>MessageStore</classname> strategy (mainly used by the <emphasis>ClaimCheck</emphasis>pattern)
	and the <classname>MessageGroupStore</classname> strategy (mainly used by the <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>Resequencer</emphasis> patterns).
	</para>

    <para>
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="mongoDbMessageStore" class="o.s.i.mongodb.store.MongoDbMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg ref="mongoDbFactory"/>
</bean>

<int:channel id="somePersistentQueueChannel">
    <int:queue message-store="mongoDbMessageStore"/>
<int:channel>

<int:aggregator input-channel="inputChannel" output-channel="outputChannel"
         message-store="mongoDbMessageStore"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
    Above is a sample <classname>MongoDbMessageStore</classname> configuration that shows its usage by a <emphasis>QueueChannel</emphasis>
    and an <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis>. As you can see it is a simple bean configuration, and it expects a
    <classname>MongoDbFactory</classname> as a constructor argument.
    </para>
	<para>
	  The <classname>MongoDbMessageStore</classname> expands the <interfacename>Message</interfacename> as a Mongo document
	  with all nested properties using the Spring Data Mongo Mapping mechanism. It is useful when you need to have access to
	  the <code>payload</code> or <code>headers</code> for auditing or analytics, for example, against stored messages.
	</para>
	<important>
		<para>
			The <classname>MongoDbMessageStore</classname> uses a custom <classname>MappingMongoConverter</classname> implementation
			to store <interfacename>Message</interfacename>s as MongoDB documents and there are some limitations
			for the properties (<code>payload</code> and <code>header</code> values) of the <interfacename>Message</interfacename>.
			For example, there is no ability to configure custom converters for complex domain <code>payload</code>s or <code>header</code> values.
			Or to provide a custom <classname>MongoTemplate</classname> (or <classname>MappingMongoConverter</classname>).
			To achieve these capabilities, an alternative MongoDB <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename> implementation has been
			introduced; see next paragraph.
		</para>
	</important>
	 <para>
		 <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis> introduced the <classname>ConfigurableMongoDbMessageStore</classname> -
		 <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename> and <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename> implementation.
		 This class can receive, as a constructor argument, a <classname>MongoTemplate</classname>, with which you can
		 configure with a custom <classname>WriteConcern</classname>, for example. Another constructor requires a
		 <classname>MappingMongoConverter</classname>, and a <interfacename>MongoDbFactory</interfacename>,
		 which allows you to provide some custom conversions for <interfacename>Message</interfacename>s and their properties.
		 Note, by default, the <classname>ConfigurableMongoDbMessageStore</classname> uses standard Java serialization
		 to write/read <interfacename>Message</interfacename>s to/from MongoDB and relies on default values for other
		 properties from <classname>MongoTemplate</classname>, which is built from the provided
		 <interfacename>MongoDbFactory</interfacename> and <classname>MappingMongoConverter</classname>.
		 The default name for the collection stored by the <classname>ConfigurableMongoDbMessageStore</classname> is
		 <code>configurableStoreMessages</code>. It is recommended to use this implementation for robust and flexible solutions
		 when messages contain complex data types.
	 </para>
	  <section id="mongodb-priority-channel-message-store">
		  <title>MongodDB Channel Message Store</title>

		  <para>
			  Starting with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, the new <code>MongoDbChannelMessageStore</code>
			  has been introduced; it is an optimized <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename> for use
			  in <classname>QueueChannel</classname>s.
			  With <code>priorityEnabled = true</code>, it can be used in
			  <code>&lt;int:priority-queue&gt;</code>s to achieve <emphasis>priority</emphasis> order polling for
			  persisted messages. The <emphasis>priority</emphasis> MonogDB document field is populated from the
			  <code>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.PRIORITY</code> (<code>priority</code>)
			  message header.
		  </para>
		  <para>
			  In addition, all MongoDB <interfacename>MessageStore</interfacename>s now have a <code>sequence</code>
			  field for MessageGroup
			  documents. The <code>sequence</code> value is the result of an <code>$inc</code> operation for a simple
			  <code>sequence</code>
			  document from the same collection, which is created on demand. The <code>sequence</code> field is used in
			  <code>poll</code> operations to provide first-in-first-out (FIFO) message order
			  (within priority if configured) when messages are stored within the same millisecond.
		  </para>
		  <note>
			  <para>
				  It is not recommended to use the same <classname>MongoDbChannelMessageStore</classname> bean
				  for priority and non-priority, because the <code>priorityEnabled</code> option applies to the entire store.
				  However, the same <code>collection</code> can be used for both
				  <classname>MongoDbChannelMessageStore</classname> types, because message polling from the
				  store is sorted and uses indexes. To configure that scenario, simply extend one message store bean
				  from the other:
			  </para>
		  </note>
		  <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="channelStore" class="o.s.i.mongodb.store.MongoDbChannelMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg name="mongoDbFactory" ref="mongoDbFactory"/>
</bean>

<int:channel id="queueChannel">
    <int:queue message-store="store"/>
</int:channel>

<bean id="priorityStore" parent="channelStore">
    <property name="priorityEnabled" value="true"/>
</bean>

<int:channel id="priorityChannel">
    <int:priority-queue message-store="priorityStore"/>
</int:channel>]]></programlisting>
	  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="mongodb-inbound-channel-adapter">
    <title>MongoDB Inbound Channel Adapter</title>

    <para>
    The <emphasis>MongoDb Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> is a polling consumer that reads data
    from MongoDb and sends it as a Message payload.
    </para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-mongodb:inbound-channel-adapter id="mongoInboundAdapter"
       channel="replyChannel"
       query="{'name' : 'Bob'}"
       entity-class="java.lang.Object"
       auto-startup="false">
		<int:poller fixed-rate="100"/>
</int-mongodb:inbound-channel-adapter>]]></programlisting>

    <para>
    As you can see from the configuration above, you configure a <emphasis>MongoDb Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> using
    the <code>inbound-channel-adapter</code> element, providing values for various attributes such as:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>query</code> or <code>query-expression</code> - a
        JSON query (see <ulink url="http://www.mongodb.org/display/DOCS/Querying">MongoDb Querying</ulink>) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>entity-class</code> - the type of the payload object; if not supplied, a
          <classname>com.mongodb.DBObject</classname> will be returned.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>collection-name</code> or <code>collection-name-expression</code> -
        Identifies the name of the MongoDb collection to use.  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>mongodb-factory</code>  -
        reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.mongodb.MongoDbFactory</classname>  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>mongo-template</code>  -
         reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.mongodb.core.MongoTemplate</classname>
         </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    and other attributes that are common across all other inbound adapters (e.g., 'channel').
    </para>
    <note>
        You cannot set both <code>mongo-template</code> and <code>mongodb-factory</code>.
    </note>
	<para>
	The example above is relatively simple and static since it has a literal value for the <code>query</code> and uses
	the default name for a <code>collection</code>. Sometimes you may need to change those values at runtime, based on some condition.
	To do that, simply use their <code>-expression</code> equivalents (<code>query-expression</code> and
	<code>collection-name-expression</code>) where the provided expression can be any valid SpEL expression.
	</para>
	<para>
	Also, you may wish to do some post-processing to the successfully processed data that was read from the MongoDb.
	For example; you may want to move or remove a document after its been processed.
	You can do this using Transaction Synchronization feature that was added with Spring Integration 2.2.
	</para>
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-mongodb:inbound-channel-adapter id="mongoInboundAdapter"
	   channel="replyChannel"
	   query="{'name' : 'Bob'}"
	   entity-class="java.lang.Object"
	   auto-startup="false">
				<int:poller fixed-rate="200" max-messages-per-poll="1">
				    <int:transactional synchronization-factory="syncFactory"/>
				</int:poller>
</int-mongodb:inbound-channel-adapter>

<int:transaction-synchronization-factory id="syncFactory">
	<int:after-commit expression="@documentCleaner.remove(#mongoTemplate, payload, headers.mongo_collectionName)" channe="someChannel"/>
</int:transaction-synchronization-factory>

<bean id="documentCleaner" class="foo.bar.DocumentCleaner"/>

<bean id="transactionManager" class="o.s.i.transaction.PseudoTransactionManager"/>]]></programlisting>

<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class DocumentCleaner {
		public void remove(MongoOperations mongoOperations, Object target, String collectionName) {
			if (target instanceof List<?>){
				List<?> documents = (List<?>) target;
				for (Object document : documents) {
					mongoOperations.remove(new BasicQuery(JSON.serialize(document)), collectionName);
				}
			}
		}
}]]></programlisting>
   <para>
   As you can see from the above, all you need to do is declare your poller to be transactional with a <code>transactional</code> element.
   This element can reference a real transaction manager (for example if some other part of your flow invokes JDBC).
   If you don't have a 'real' transaction, you can use a
   <classname>org.springframework.integration.transaction.PseudoTransactionManager</classname> which is an implementation
   of Spring's <classname>PlatformTransactionManager</classname> and enables the use of the transaction synchronization
   features of the mongo adapter when there is no actual transaction.
   </para>
   <important>
     This does NOT make MongoDB itself transactional, it simply allows the synchronization of actions to be taken before/after success (commit)
     or after failure (rollback).
   </important>
   <para>
   Once your poller is transactional all you need to do is set an instance of the
   <classname>org.springframework.integration.transaction.TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> on the <code>transactional</code> element.
   <classname>TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> will create an instance of the <classname>TransactioinSynchronization</classname>.
   For your convenience, we've exposed a default SpEL-based <classname>TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> which allows
   you to configure SpEL expressions, with their execution being coordinated (synchronized) with a transaction.
   Expressions for before-commit, after-commit, and after-rollback are supported, together with a channel for each where the
   evaluation result (if any) will be sent. For each sub-element you can specify <code>expression</code> and/or <code>channel</code>
   attributes. If only the <code>channel</code> attribute is present the received Message will be sent there as part of the particular
   synchronization scenario. If only the <code>expression</code> attribute is present and the result of an expression is a non-Null
   value, a Message with the result as the payload will be generated and sent to a default channel (NullChannel) and will appear in the
   logs (DEBUG). If you want the evaluation result to go to a specific channel add a <code>channel</code> attribute. If the result of an
   expression is null or void, no Message will be generated.
   </para>
   <para>
   For more information about transaction synchronization, see <xref linkend="transaction-synchronization"/>.
   </para>
  </section>

   <section id="mongodb-outbound-channel-adapter">
    <title>MongoDB Outbound Channel Adapter</title>

    <para>
    The <emphasis>MongoDb Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> allows you to write the Message payload to a MongoDb document store
    </para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-mongodb:outbound-channel-adapter id="fullConfigWithCollectionExpression"
	collection-name="myCollection"
	mongo-converter="mongoConverter"
	mongodb-factory="mongoDbFactory" />]]></programlisting>

    <para>
    As you can see from the configuration above, you configure a <emphasis>MongoDb Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> using
    the <code>outbound-channel-adapter</code> element, providing values for various attributes such as:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>collection-name</code> or <code>collection-name-expression</code> -
        Identifies the name of the MongoDb collection to use.  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>mongo-converter</code>  -
        reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.mongodb.core.convert.MongoConverter</classname> to assist with
        converting a raw java object to a JSON document representation  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>mongodb-factory</code>  -
        reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.mongodb.MongoDbFactory</classname>  </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>mongo-template</code>  -
         reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.mongodb.core.MongoTemplate</classname>
         (NOTE: you can not have both mongo-template and mongodb-factory set)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    and other attributes that are common across all other inbound adapters (e.g., 'channel').
    </para>
	<para>
	The example above is relatively simple and static since it has a literal value for the <code>collection-name</code>.
	Sometimes you may need to change this value at runtime based on some condition.
	To do that, simply use <code>collection-name-expression</code>
	where the provided expression can be any valid SpEL expression.
	</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
