<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="overview"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Spring Integration Overview</title>

  <section id="overview-background">
    <title>Background</title>
    <para>
      One of the key themes of the Spring Framework is <emphasis>inversion of control</emphasis>. In its broadest
      sense, this means that the framework handles responsibilities on behalf of the components that are managed within
      its context. The components themselves are simplified since they are relieved of those responsibilities. For
      example, <emphasis>dependency injection</emphasis> relieves the components of the responsibility of locating or
      creating their dependencies. Likewise, <emphasis>aspect-oriented programming</emphasis> relieves business
      components of generic cross-cutting concerns by modularizing them into reusable aspects. In each case, the end
      result is a system that is easier to test, understand, maintain, and extend.
    </para>
    <para>
      Furthermore, the Spring framework and portfolio provide a comprehensive programming model for building
      enterprise applications. Developers benefit from the consistency of this model and especially the fact that it is
      based upon well-established best practices such as programming to interfaces and favoring composition over
      inheritance. Spring's simplified abstractions and powerful support libraries boost developer productivity while
      simultaneously increasing the level of testability and portability.
    </para>
    <para>
      Spring Integration is motivated by these same goals and principles. It
      extends the Spring programming model into the messaging domain and builds upon Spring's existing enterprise
      integration support to provide an even higher level of abstraction. It supports message-driven architectures
      where inversion of control applies to runtime concerns, such as <emphasis>when</emphasis> certain business logic
      should execute and <emphasis>where</emphasis> the response should be sent. It supports routing and transformation
      of messages so that different transports and different data formats can be integrated without impacting
      testability. In other words, the messaging and integration concerns are handled by the framework, so business
      components are further isolated from the infrastructure and developers are relieved of complex integration
      responsibilities.
    </para>
    <para>
      As an extension of the Spring programming model, Spring Integration provides a wide variety of configuration
      options including annotations, XML with namespace support, XML with generic "bean" elements, and of course direct
      usage of the underlying API. That API is based upon well-defined strategy interfaces and non-invasive, delegating
      adapters. Spring Integration's design is inspired by the recognition of a strong affinity between common patterns
      within Spring and the well-known <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com">Enterprise Integration Patterns</ulink>
      as described in the book of the same name by Gregor Hohpe and Bobby Woolf (Addison Wesley, 2004). Developers who
      have read that book should be immediately comfortable with the Spring Integration concepts and terminology.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="overview-goalsandprinciples">
    <title>Goals and Principles</title>
    <para>Spring Integration is motivated by the following goals:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Provide a simple model for implementing complex enterprise integration solutions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Facilitate asynchronous, message-driven behavior within a Spring-based application.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Promote intuitive, incremental adoption for existing Spring users.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>Spring Integration is guided by the following principles:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Components should be <emphasis>loosely coupled</emphasis> for modularity and testability.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The framework should enforce <emphasis>separation of concerns</emphasis> between business logic and
          integration logic.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Extension points should be abstract in nature but within well-defined boundaries to promote
          <emphasis>reuse</emphasis> and <emphasis>portability</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="overview-components">
    <title>Main Components</title>
    <para>
      From the <emphasis>vertical</emphasis> perspective, a layered architecture facilitates separation of concerns,
      and interface-based contracts between layers promote loose coupling. Spring-based applications are typically
      designed this way, and the Spring framework and portfolio provide a strong foundation for following this best
      practice for the full-stack of an enterprise application. Message-driven architectures add a
      <emphasis>horizontal</emphasis> perspective, yet these same goals are still relevant. Just as "layered
      architecture" is an extremely generic and abstract paradigm, messaging systems typically follow the similarly
      abstract "pipes-and-filters" model. The "filters" represent any component that is capable of producing and/or
      consuming messages, and the "pipes" transport the messages between filters so that the components themselves
      remain loosely-coupled. It is important to note that these two high-level paradigms are not mutually exclusive.
      The underlying messaging infrastructure that supports the "pipes" should still be encapsulated in a layer whose
      contracts are defined as interfaces. Likewise, the "filters" themselves would typically be managed within a layer
      that is logically above the application's service layer, interacting with those services through interfaces much
      in the same way that a web-tier would.
    </para>

    <section id="overview-components-message">
      <title>Message</title>
      <para>
        In Spring Integration, a Message is a generic wrapper for any Java object combined with metadata used by the
        framework while handling that object. It consists of a payload and headers. The payload can be of any type and
        the headers hold commonly required information such as id, timestamp, correlation id, and return address. Headers
        are also used for passing values to and from connected transports. For example, when creating a Message from a
        received File, the file name may be stored in a header to be accessed by downstream components. Likewise, if a
        Message's content is ultimately going to be sent by an outbound Mail adapter, the various properties (to, from,
        cc, subject, etc.) may be configured as Message header values by an upstream component. Developers can also
        store any arbitrary key-value pairs in the headers.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/message.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/message.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-components-channel">
      <title>Message Channel</title>
      <para>
        A Message Channel represents the "pipe" of a pipes-and-filters architecture. Producers send Messages to
        a channel, and consumers receive Messages from a channel. The Message Channel therefore decouples the
        messaging components, and also provides a convenient point for interception and monitoring of Messages.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/channel.jpg" format="JPG" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" />
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/channel.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        A Message Channel may follow either Point-to-Point or Publish/Subscribe semantics. With a Point-to-Point
        channel, at most one consumer can receive each Message sent to the channel. Publish/Subscribe channels, on the
        other hand, will attempt to broadcast each Message to all of its subscribers. Spring Integration supports
        both of these.
      </para>
      <para>
        Whereas "Point-to-Point" and "Publish/Subscribe" define the two options for <emphasis>how many</emphasis>
        consumers will ultimately receive each Message, there is another important consideration: should the channel
        buffer messages? In Spring Integration, <emphasis>Pollable Channels</emphasis> are capable of buffering
        Messages within a queue. The advantage of buffering is that it allows for throttling the inbound Messages and
        thereby prevents overloading a consumer. However, as the name suggests, this also adds some complexity, since a
        consumer can only receive the Messages from such a channel if a <emphasis>poller</emphasis> is configured. On
        the other hand, a consumer connected to a <emphasis>Subscribable Channel</emphasis> is simply Message-driven.
        The variety of channel implementations available in Spring Integration will be discussed in detail in
        <xref linkend="channel-implementations"/>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-components-endpoint">
      <title>Message Endpoint</title>
      <para>
        One of the primary goals of Spring Integration is to simplify the development of enterprise integration
        solutions through <emphasis>inversion of control</emphasis>. This means that you should not have to implement
        consumers and producers directly, and you should not even have to build Messages and invoke send or receive
        operations on a Message Channel. Instead, you should be able to focus on your specific domain model with an
        implementation based on plain Objects. Then, by providing declarative configuration, you can "connect"
        your domain-specific code to the messaging infrastructure provided by Spring Integration. The components
        responsible for these connections are Message Endpoints. This does not mean that you will necessarily connect
        your existing application code directly. Any real-world enterprise integration solution will require some
        amount of code focused upon integration concerns such as <emphasis>routing</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>transformation</emphasis>. The important thing is to achieve separation of concerns between such
        integration logic and business logic. In other words, as with the Model-View-Controller paradigm for web
        applications, the goal should be to provide a thin but dedicated layer that translates inbound requests into
        service layer invocations, and then translates service layer return values into outbound replies. The next
        section will provide an overview of the Message Endpoint types that handle these responsibilities, and in
        upcoming chapters, you will see how Spring Integration's declarative configuration options provide a
        non-invasive way to use each of these.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="overview-endpoints">
    <title>Message Endpoints</title>
    <para>
      A Message Endpoint represents the "filter" of a pipes-and-filters architecture. As mentioned above, the
      endpoint's primary role is to connect application code to the messaging framework and to do so in a non-invasive
      manner. In other words, the application code should ideally have no awareness of the Message objects or the
      Message Channels. This is similar to the role of a Controller in the MVC paradigm. Just as a Controller handles
      HTTP requests, the Message Endpoint handles Messages. Just as Controllers are mapped to URL patterns, Message
      Endpoints are mapped to Message Channels. The goal is the same in both cases: isolate application code from the
      infrastructure. These concepts are discussed at length along with all of the patterns that follow in the
      <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com">Enterprise Integration Patterns</ulink> book. Here, we provide only a
      high-level description of the main endpoint types supported by Spring Integration and their roles. The chapters
      that follow will elaborate and provide sample code as well as configuration examples.
    </para>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-transformer">
      <title>Transformer</title>
      <para>
        A Message Transformer is responsible for converting a Message's content or structure and returning the modified
        Message. Probably the most common type of transformer is one that converts the payload of the Message from one
        format to another (e.g. from XML Document to java.lang.String). Similarly, a transformer may be used to add,
        remove, or modify the Message's header values.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-filter">
      <title>Filter</title>
      <para>
        A Message Filter determines whether a Message should be passed to an output channel at all. This simply
        requires a boolean test method that may check for a particular payload content type, a property value, the
        presence of a header, etc. If the Message is accepted, it is sent to the output channel, but if not it will be
        dropped (or for a more severe implementation, an Exception could be thrown). Message Filters are often used in
        conjunction with a Publish Subscribe channel, where multiple consumers may receive the same Message and use the
        filter to narrow down the set of Messages to be processed based on some criteria.
        <note>
          Be careful not to confuse the generic use of "filter" within the Pipes-and-Filters architectural pattern with
          this specific endpoint type that selectively narrows down the Messages flowing between two channels. The
          Pipes-and-Filters concept of "filter" matches more closely with Spring Integration's Message Endpoint: any
          component that can be connected to Message Channel(s) in order to send and/or receive Messages.
        </note>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-router">
      <title>Router</title>
      <para>
        A Message Router is responsible for deciding what channel or channels should receive the Message next (if any).
        Typically the decision is based upon the Message's content and/or metadata available in the Message Headers.
        A Message Router is often used as a dynamic alternative to a statically configured output channel on
        a Service Activator or other endpoint capable of sending reply Messages. Likewise, a Message Router provides a
        proactive alternative to the reactive Message Filters used by multiple subscribers as described above.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/router.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/router.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-splitter">
      <title>Splitter</title>
      <para>
        A Splitter is another type of Message Endpoint whose responsibility is to accept a Message from its input
        channel, split that Message into multiple Messages, and then send each of those to its output channel. This
        is typically used for dividing a "composite" payload object into a group of Messages containing the
        sub-divided payloads.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-aggregator">
      <title>Aggregator</title>
      <para>
        Basically a mirror-image of the Splitter, the Aggregator is a type of Message Endpoint that receives multiple
        Messages and combines them into a single Message. In fact, Aggregators are often downstream consumers in a
        pipeline that includes a Splitter. Technically, the Aggregator is more complex than a Splitter, because it
        is required to maintain state (the Messages to-be-aggregated), to decide when the complete group of Messages
        is available, and to timeout if necessary. Furthermore, in case of a timeout, the Aggregator needs to know
        whether to send the partial results or to discard them to a separate channel. Spring Integration provides
        a <interfacename>CompletionStrategy</interfacename> as well as configurable settings for timeout, whether
        to send partial results upon timeout, and the discard channel.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-service-activator">
      <title>Service Activator</title>
      <para>
        A Service Activator is a generic endpoint for connecting a service instance to the messaging system. The
        input Message Channel must be configured, and if the service method to be invoked is capable of returning a
        value, an output Message Channel may also be provided.
        <note>
          The output channel is optional, since each Message may also provide its own 'Return Address' header. This
          same rule applies for all consumer endpoints.
        </note>
        The Service Activator invokes an operation on some service object to process the request Message, extracting
        the request Message's payload and converting if necessary (if the method does not expect a Message-typed
        parameter). Whenever the service object's method returns a value, that return value will likewise be converted
        to a reply Message if necessary (if it's not already a Message). That reply Message is sent to the output
        channel. If no output channel has been configured, then the reply will be sent to the channel specified in the
        Message's "return address" if available.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/handler-endpoint.jpg" format="JPG" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/handler-endpoint.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>
            A request-reply "Service Activator" endpoint connects a target object's method to input and output
            Message Channels.
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="overview-endpoints-channeladapter">
      <title>Channel Adapter</title>
      <para>
        A Channel Adapter is an endpoint that connects a Message Channel to some other system or transport. Channel
        Adapters may be either inbound or outbound. Typically, the Channel Adapter will do some mapping between the
        Message and whatever object or resource is received-from or sent-to the other system (File, HTTP Request, JMS
        Message, etc). Depending on the transport, the Channel Adapter may also populate or extract Message header
        values. Spring Integration provides a number of Channel Adapters, and they will be described in upcoming
        chapters.
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/source-endpoint.jpg" format="JPG" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/source-endpoint.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>An inbound "Channel Adapter" endpoint connects a source system to a MessageChannel.</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="images/target-endpoint.jpg" format="JPG" align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/target-endpoint.jpg" format="JPG" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
          <caption>An outbound "Channel Adapter" endpoint connects a MessageChannel to a target system.</caption>
        </mediaobject>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      Throughout this document you will see references to XML namespace support for declaring elements in a Spring
      Integration flow. This support is provided by a series of namespace parsers that generate appropriate
      bean definitions to implement a particular component. For example, many endpoints consist of a
      <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> bean and a <classname>ConsumerEndpointFactoryBean</classname>
      into which the handler and an input channel name are injected.
    </para>
    <para>
      The first time a Spring Integration namespace element is encountered, the framework automatically declares
      a number of beans that are used to support the runtime environment (task scheduler,
      implicit channel creator, etc).
    </para>
    <para id="enable-integration">
      Starting with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, these support beans can also be defined when using
      <code>@Configuration</code> classes, by adding a new annotation <code>@EnableIntegration</code>.
      This is useful when declaring a simple Spring Integration flow using purely Java Configuration.
      For example; you can declare an endpoint with a <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> <code>@Bean</code>
      as well as a <classname>ConsumerEndpointFactoryBean</classname> <code>@Bean</code>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>@EnableIntegration</code> is also useful when you have a parent context with no Spring Integration
      components and 2 or more child contexts that do use Spring Integration. It would enable these common
      components to be declared once only, in the parent context.
    </para>
	<para>
		The <code>@IntegrationComponentScan</code> annotation has also been introduced to permit classpath
		scanning. This annotation plays a similar role as the standard Spring Framework <code>@ComponentScan</code> annotation,
		but it is restricted just to Spring Integration specific components and annotations,
		which aren't reachable by the standard Spring Framework component scan mechanism.
		For example <xref linkend="messaging-gateway-annotation"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		The <code>@EnablePublisher</code> annotation has been introduced to register a
		<classname>PublisherAnnotationBeanPostProcessor</classname> bean and configure the <code>default-publisher-channel</code>
		for those <classname>@Publisher</classname> annotations which are provided without a <code>channel</code> attribute.
		If more than one <code>@EnablePublisher</code> annotation is found, they must all have the same value
		for the default channel.
		See <xref linkend="publisher-annotation"/> for more information.
	</para>
	<para>
		The <classname>@GlobalChannelInterceptor</classname> annotation has been introduced to
		mark <interfacename>ChannelInterceptor</interfacename> beans for global channel interception.
		This annotation is an analogue of the <code>&lt;int:channel-interceptor&gt;</code> xml element
		(see <xref linkend="global-channel-configuration-interceptors"/>). <code>@GlobalChannelInterceptor</code> annotations
		can be placed at the class level (with a <classname>@Component</classname> stereotype annotation), or
		on <classname>@Bean</classname> methods within <classname>@Configuration</classname> classes. In either case,
		the bean <emphasis role="bold">must</emphasis> be a <interfacename>ChannelInterceptor</interfacename>.
	</para>
	<para>
		The <classname>@IntegrationConverter</classname> annotation has been introduced to
		mark <interfacename>Converter</interfacename>, <interfacename>GenericConverter</interfacename> or
		<interfacename>ConverterFactory</interfacename> beans as candidate converters for <code>integrationConversionService</code>.
		This annotation is an analogue of the <code>&lt;int:converter&gt;</code> xml element
		(see <xref linkend="payload-type-conversion"/>). <code>@IntegrationConverter</code> annotations
		can be placed at the class level (with a <classname>@Component</classname> stereotype annotation), or
		on <classname>@Bean</classname> methods within <classname>@Configuration</classname> classes.
	</para>
  </section>
  <section id="programming-considerations">
	<title>Programming Considerations</title>
	<para>
		It is generally recommended that you use plain old java objects (POJOs) whenever possible and only
		expose the framework in your code when absolutely necessary.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you do expose the framework to your classes,
		there are some considerations that need to be taken into account, especially during application startup; some of
		these are listed here.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			If your component is <interfacename>ApplicationContextAware</interfacename>, you should generally not "use"
			the <interfacename>ApplicationContext</interfacename> in the <code>setApplicationContext()</code> method;
			just store a reference and defer such uses until later in the context lifecycle.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			If your component is an <interfacename>InitializingBean</interfacename> or uses <code>@PostConstruct</code>
			methods, do not send any messages from these initialization methods - the application context is not
			yet initialized when these methods are called, and sending such messages will likely fail.
			If you need to send a messages during startup, implement <interfacename>ApplicationListener</interfacename>
			and wait for the <classname>ContextRefreshedEvent</classname>. Alternatively, implement
			<interfacename>SmartLifecycle</interfacename>, put your bean in a late phase, and send the messages
			from the <code>start()</code> method.
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

  </section>
</chapter>
