<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="redis"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <title>Redis Support</title>

  <para>
    Since version 2.1 Spring Integration introduces support for <ulink url="http://redis.io/">Redis</ulink>:
    <emphasis>"an open source advanced key-value store". </emphasis>
    This support comes in the form of a Redis-based MessageStore as well as Publish-Subscribe Messaging adapters that
    are supported by Redis via its <ulink url="http://redis.io/topics/pubsub">PUBLISH, SUBSCRIBE and UNSUBSCRIBE</ulink> commands.
  </para>

  <section id="redis-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      To download, install and run Redis please refer to the <ulink url="http://redis.io/download">Redis documentation</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-connection">
    <title>Connecting to Redis</title>

    <para>To begin interacting with Redis you first need to connect to it. Spring Integration uses support provided by another Spring project,
    <ulink url="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-redis">Spring Data Redis</ulink>, which provides typical Spring constructs:
    <classname>ConnectionFactory</classname> and <classname>Template</classname>. Those abstractions
    simplify integration with several Redis-client Java APIs. Currently Spring-Data-Redis supports
    <ulink url="https://github.com/xetorthio/jedis">jedis</ulink>, <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/jredis/">jredis</ulink> and <ulink url="https://github.com/e-mzungu/rjc">rjc</ulink></para>

    <para><emphasis>RedisConnectionFactory</emphasis> </para>

    <para>
    To connect to Redis you would use one of the implementations of the <classname>RedisConnectionFactory</classname> interface:

      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface RedisConnectionFactory extends PersistenceExceptionTranslator {

	/**
	 * Provides a suitable connection for interacting with Redis.
	 *
	 * @return connection for interacting with Redis.
	 */
	RedisConnection getConnection();
}]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>The example below shows how to create a <classname>JedisConnectionFactory</classname>.</para>

    <para>In Java:
    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[JedisConnectionFactory jcf = new JedisConnectionFactory();
jcf.afterPropertiesSet();]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>Or in Spring's XML configuration:
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisConnectionFactory"
    class="o.s.data.redis.connection.jedis.JedisConnectionFactory">
    <property name="port" value="7379" />
</bean>]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
    The implementations of RedisConnectionFactory provide a set of properties such as port and host that can be set if needed.
    Once an instance of RedisConnectionFactory is created, you can create an instance of RedisTemplate and inject it with the RedisConnectionFactory.
    </para>

    <para><emphasis>RedisTemplate</emphasis> </para>

    <para>
    As with other template classes in Spring (e.g., <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, <classname>JmsTemplate</classname>)
    <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> is a helper class that simplifies Redis data access code.
    For more information about <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> and its variations (e.g., <classname>StringRedisTemplate</classname>)
    please refer to the <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-data/data-redis/docs/current/reference/">Spring-Data-Redis documentation</ulink>
    </para>

    <para>The code below shows how to create an instance of <classname>RedisTemplate</classname>:</para>

    <para>In Java:
    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[RedisTemplate rt = new RedisTemplate<String, Object>();
rt.setConnectionFactory(redisConnectionFactory);]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>Or in Spring's XML configuration::
    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisTemplate" class="org.springframework.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate">
	<property name="connectionFactory" ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-messages">
    <title>Messaging with Redis</title>

    <para>
    As mentioned in the introduction Redis provides support for Publish-Subscribe messaging via its PUBLISH, SUBSCRIBE and UNSUBSCRIBE
    commands. As with JMS and AMQP, Spring Integration provides Message Channels and adapters for sending and receiving messages via Redis.
    </para>

    <section id="redis-pub-sub-channel">
      <title>Redis Publish/Subscribe channel</title>

      <para>
      Similar to the JMS there are cases where both the producer and consumer are intended to be part of the same application, running
      within the same process. This could be accomplished by using a pair of inbound and outbound Channel Adapters,
      however just like with Spring Integration's JMS support, there is a simpler approach to address this use case.
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:publish-subscribe-channel id="redisChannel" topic-name="si.test.topic"/>]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>
      The publish-subscribe-channel (above) will behave much like a normal <code>&lt;publish-subscribe-channel/&gt;</code> element from the
      main Spring Integration namespace. It can be referenced by both <code>input-channel</code> and <code>output-channel</code> attributes of
      any endpoint. The difference is that this channel is backed by a Redis topic name - a String value specified by the <code>topic-name</code>
      attribute. However unlike JMS this topic doesn't have to be created in advance or even auto-created by Redis. In Redis topics are simple
      String values that play the role of an address, and all the producer and consumer need to do to communicate is use the same String value
      as their topic name. A simple subscription to this channel means that asynchronous pub-sub messaging is possible between the producing and
      consuming endpoints, but unlike the asynchronous Message Channels created by adding a <code> &lt;queue/&gt;</code> sub-element within
      a simple Spring Integration <code>&lt;channel/&gt;</code> element, the Messages are not just stored in an in-memory queue. Instead those
      Messages are passed through Redis allowing you to rely on its support for persistence and clustering as well as its interoperability with
      other non-java platforms.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="redis-inbound-channel-adapter">
      <title>Redis Inbound Channel Adapter</title>
      <para>
      The Redis-based Inbound Channel Adapter adapts incoming Redis messages into Spring Integration Messages in the same way as other
      inbound adapters. It receives platform-specific messages (Redis in this case) and converts them to Spring Integration Messages using
      a <classname>MessageConverter</classname> strategy.

      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:inbound-channel-adapter id="redisAdapter"
       topics="foo, bar"
       channel="receiveChannel"
       error-channel="testErrorChannel"
       message-converter="testConverter" />

<bean id="redisConnectionFactory"
    class="o.s.data.redis.connection.jedis.JedisConnectionFactory">
    <property name="port" value="7379" />
</bean>

<bean id="testConverter" class="foo.bar.SampleMessageConverter" />]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>
      Above is a simple but complete configuration of a Redis Inbound Channel Adapter. Note that the above configuration relies on the
      familiar Spring paradigm of auto-discovering certain beans. In this case the <code>redisConnectionFactory</code> is implicitly
      injected into the adapter. You can of course specify it explicitly using the <code>connection-factory</code> attribute instead.
      </para>

      <para>
      Also, note that the above configuration injects the adapter with a custom <code>MessageConverter</code>.
      The approach is similar to JMS where <code>MessageConverters</code> are used to convert between
      Redis Messages and the Spring Integration Message payloads. The default is a <code>SimpleMessageConverter</code>.
      </para>

      <para>
       Inbound adapters can subscribe to multiple topic names hence the comma-delimited set of values in the
       <code>topics</code> attribute.
	  </para>
      <para>
        Since <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis>, the Inbound Adapter, in addition to the existing <code>topics</code> attribute,
        now has the <code>topic-patterns</code> attribute. This attribute contains a comma-delimited set of Redis topic patterns.
        For more information regarding Redis publish/subscribe, see <ulink url="http://redis.io/topics/pubsub">Redis Pub/Sub</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
         Inbound adapters can use a <classname>RedisSerializer</classname> to deserialize the body of Redis Messages.
         The <code>serializer</code> attribute of the <code>&lt;int-redis:inbound-channel-adapter&gt;</code> can be set to an
         empty string, which results in a <code>null</code> value for the <classname>RedisSerializer</classname> property.
         In this case the raw <code>byte[]</code> bodies of Redis Messages are provided as the message payloads.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="redis-outbound-channel-adapter">
      <title>Redis Outbound Channel Adapter</title>
      <para>
      The Redis-based Outbound Channel Adapter adapts outgoing Spring Integration messages into Redis messages in the same way as
      other outbound adapters. It receives Spring Integration messages and converts them to platform-specific messages (Redis in this case)
      using a <classname>MessageConverter</classname> strategy.

     <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:outbound-channel-adapter id="outboundAdapter"
    channel="sendChannel"
    topic="foo"
    message-converter="testConverter"/>

<bean id="redisConnectionFactory"
    class="o.s.data.redis.connection.jedis.JedisConnectionFactory">
    <property name="port" value="7379"/>
</bean>

<bean id="testConverter" class="foo.bar.SampleMessageConverter" />]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
      As you can see the configuration is similar to the Redis Inbound Channel Adapter. The adapter is implicitly injected with
      a <classname>RedisConnectionFactory</classname> which was defined with '<code>redisConnectionFactory</code>' as its bean name.
      This example also includes the optional, custom <classname>MessageConverter</classname> (the '<code>testConverter</code>' bean).
      </para>
      <para>
         Since <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis>, the <code>&lt;int-redis:outbound-channel-adapter&gt;</code>,
         as an alternative to the <code>topic</code> attribute, has the <code>topic-expression</code> attribute to determine
         the Redis topic against the Message at runtime. These attributes are mutually exclusive.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="redis-queue-inbound-channel-adapter">
       <title>Redis Queue Inbound Channel Adapter</title>
       <para>
          Since <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis>, a Queue Inbound Channel Adapter
		  is available to 'right pop' messages from a Redis List.
		  The adapter is message-driven using an internal listener thread and does not use a poller.
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:queue-inbound-channel-adapter id="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-id"/><![CDATA[
                    channel="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-channel"/><![CDATA[
                    auto-startup="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-autoStartup"/><![CDATA[
                    phase="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-phase"/><![CDATA[
                    connection-factory="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-connectionFactory"/><![CDATA[
                    queue="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-queue"/><![CDATA[
                    error-channel="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-errorChannel"/><![CDATA[
                    serializer="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-serializer"/><![CDATA[
                    receive-timeout="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-receiveTimeout"/><![CDATA[
                    recovery-interval="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-recoveryInterval"/><![CDATA[
                    expect-message="" ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-expectMessage"/><![CDATA[
                    task-executor=""/> ]]><co id="redis-m-d-c-a-task-executor"/>
		</programlisting>
		<calloutlist>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-id">
				<para>
				   The component bean name. If the <code>channel</code> attribute isn't provided a <classname>DirectChannel</classname>
                   is created and registered with application context with this <code>id</code> attribute as the bean name.
				   In this case, the endpoint itself is registered with the bean name <code>id + '.adapter'</code>.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-channel">
				<para>
					The <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> to which to send <interfacename>Message</interfacename>s from this Endpoint.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-autoStartup">
				<para>
					A <interfacename>SmartLifecycle</interfacename> attribute to specify whether this Endpoint should start automatically after
					the application context start or not. Default is <code>true</code>.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-phase">
				<para>
					A <interfacename>SmartLifecycle</interfacename> attribute to specify the <emphasis>phase</emphasis> in which
					this Endpoint will be started. Default is <code>0</code>.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-connectionFactory">
				<para>
				   A reference to a <interfacename>RedisConnectionFactory</interfacename> bean. Defaults to
				   <code>redisConnectionFactory</code>.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-queue">
				<para>
				   The name of the Redis List on which the queue-based 'right pop' operation is performed to get Redis messages.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-errorChannel">
				<para>
					The <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> to which to send <interfacename>ErrorMessage</interfacename>s with
					<interfacename>Exception</interfacename>s from the listening task of the Endpoint. By default
					the underlying <classname>MessagePublishingErrorHandler</classname> uses the
					default <code>errorChannel</code> from the application context.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-serializer">
				<para>
				   The <interfacename>RedisSerializer</interfacename> bean reference. Can be an empty string, which means 'no serializer'.
				   In this case the raw <code>byte[]</code> from the inbound Redis message is sent to the <code>channel</code> as the
				   <interfacename>Message</interfacename> payload. By default it is a <classname>JdkSerializationRedisSerializer</classname>.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-receiveTimeout">
				<para>
					The timeout in milliseconds for 'right pop' operation to wait for a Redis message from the queue. Default is 1 second.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-recoveryInterval">
				<para>
					The time in milliseconds for which the listener task should sleep after exceptions on the 'right pop' operation,
					before restarting the listener task.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-expectMessage">
				<para>
				   Specify if this Endpoint expects data from the Redis queue to contain entire <interfacename>Message</interfacename>s.
				   If this attribute is set to <code>true</code>, the <code>serializer</code> can't be an empty string because messages
				   require some form of deserialization (JDK serialization by default).
				   Default is <code>false</code>.
				</para>
			</callout>
			<callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-task-executor">
				<para>
				   A reference to a Spring <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename> (or standard JDK 1.5+ <interfacename>Executor</interfacename>)
				   bean. It is used for the underlying listening task. By default a <classname>SimpleAsyncTaskExecutor</classname>
				   is used.
				</para>
			</callout>
		</calloutlist>
		</para>
    </section>
     <section id="redis-queue-outbound-channel-adapter">
		  <title>Redis Queue Outbound Channel Adapter</title>
		  <para>
			  Since <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis>, a Queue Outbound Channel Adapter
			   is available to 'left push' to a Redis List from Spring Integration messages:
			  <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:queue-outbound-channel-adapter id="" ]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-id"/><![CDATA[
                    channel="" ]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-channel"/><![CDATA[
                    connection-factory="" ]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-connectionFactory"/><![CDATA[
                    queue="" ]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-queue"/><![CDATA[
                    queue-expression="" ]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-queueExpression"/><![CDATA[
                    serializer="" ]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-serializer"/><![CDATA[
                    extract-payload="" />]]><co id="redis-q-u-c-a-extractPayload"/>
			  </programlisting>
			  <calloutlist>
				  <callout arearefs="redis-q-u-c-a-id">
					  <para>
						  The component bean name. If the <code>channel</code> attribute isn't provided, a <classname>DirectChannel</classname>
						  is created and registered with the application context with this <code>id</code> attribute as the bean name.
						  In this case, the endpoint is registered with the bean name <code>id + '.adapter'</code>.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
				  <callout arearefs="redis-q-u-c-a-channel">
					  <para>
						  The <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> from which this Endpoint receives <interfacename>Message</interfacename>s.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
				  <callout arearefs="redis-q-u-c-a-connectionFactory">
					  <para>
						   A reference to a <interfacename>RedisConnectionFactory</interfacename> bean. Defaults to
						   <code>redisConnectionFactory</code>.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
				  <callout arearefs="redis-q-u-c-a-queue">
					  <para>
						  The name of the Redis List on which the queue-based 'left push' operation is performed to send Redis messages.
						  This attribute is mutually exclusive with <code>queue-expression</code>.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
				  <callout arearefs="redis-q-u-c-a-queueExpression">
					  <para>
						  A SpEL <interfacename>Expression</interfacename> to determine the name of the Redis List
						  using the incoming <interfacename>Message</interfacename> at runtime as the <code>#root</code> variable.
						  This attribute is mutually exclusive with <code>queue</code>.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
				  <callout arearefs="redis-m-d-c-a-serializer">
					  <para>
						  A <interfacename>RedisSerializer</interfacename> bean reference.
						  By default it is a <classname>JdkSerializationRedisSerializer</classname>.
						  However, for <classname>String</classname> payloads, a <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>
						  is used, if a <code>serializer</code> reference isn't provided.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
				 <callout arearefs="redis-q-u-c-a-extractPayload">
					  <para>
						  Specify if this Endpoint should send just the <emphasis>payload</emphasis> to the Redis queue,
						  or the entire <interfacename>Message</interfacename>.
						  Default is <code>true
					  </code>.
					  </para>
				  </callout>
			  </calloutlist>
		  </para>
	  </section>
	  <section id="redis-application-events">
		  <title>Redis Application Events</title>
		  <para>
			  Since <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis>, the Redis module provides an implementation
			  of <classname>IntegrationEvent</classname> - which, in turn, is a
			  <interfacename>org.springframework.context.ApplicationEvent</interfacename>. The <classname>RedisExceptionEvent</classname>
			  encapsulates an <classname>Exception</classname>s from Redis operations (with the Endpoint being the <code>source</code>
			  of the event). For example, the <code>&lt;int-redis:queue-inbound-channel-adapter/&gt;</code>
			  emits those events after catching <classname>Exception</classname>s from the <code>BoundListOperations.rightPop</code>
			  operation.
			  The exception may be any generic <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.RedisSystemException</classname> or
			  a <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.RedisConnectionFailureException</classname>.
			  Handling these events using an <code>&lt;int-event:inbound-channel-adapter/&gt;</code> can be useful to determine
			  problems with background Redis tasks and to take administrative actions.
		  </para>
	  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-message-store">
    <title>Redis Message Store</title>

	<para>
    As described in EIP, a <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/MessageStore.html">Message Store</ulink> allows you to persist Messages.
    This can be very useful when dealing with components that have a capability to buffer messages
    (<emphasis>Aggregator, Resequencer</emphasis>, etc.) if reliability is a concern.
    In Spring Integration, the MessageStore strategy also provides the foundation for the
	<ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/StoreInLibrary.html">ClaimCheck</ulink> pattern, which is described in EIP as well.
	</para>

	<para>
    Spring Integration's Redis module provides the <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname>.
    </para>

	<para>
	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisMessageStore" class="o.s.i.redis.store.RedisMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
</bean>

<int:aggregator input-channel="inputChannel" output-channel="outputChannel"
         message-store="redisMessageStore"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
    Above is a sample <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname> configuration that shows its usage by
    an <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis>. As you can see it is a simple bean configuration, and it expects a
    <classname>RedisConnectionFactory</classname> as a constructor argument.
    </para>

    <para>By default the <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname> will use Java serialization to serialize the Message.
    However if you want to use a different serialization technique (e.g., JSON), you can provide your own serializer via
    the <code>valueSerializer</code> property of the <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname>.
    </para>
	<section id="redis-cms">
		<title>Redis Channel Message Stores</title>
		<para>
			The <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname> above maintains each group as a value under a single key
			(the group id). While this can be used to back a <classname>QueueChannel</classname> for persistence,
			a specialized <classname>RedisChannelMessageStore</classname> is provided for that purpose (since
			<emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>). This store uses a <code>LIST</code> for each channel and
			<code>LPUSH</code> when sending and <code>RPOP</code> when receiving messages. This store also
			uses JDK serialization by default, but the value serializer can be modified as described above.
		</para>
		<para>
			It is recommended that this store is used for backing channels, instead of the general
			<classname>RedisMessageStore</classname>.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisMessageStore" class="o.s.i.redis.store.RedisChannelMessageStore">
	<constructor-arg ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
</bean>

<int:channel id="somePersistentQueueChannel">
	<int:queue message-store="redisMessageStore"/>
<int:channel>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			The keys that are used to store the data have the form <code>&lt;storeBeanName&gt;:&lt;channelId&gt;</code>
			(in the above example, <code>redisMessageStore:somePersistentQueueChannel</code>).
		</para>
		<para>
			In addition, a subclass <classname>RedisChannelPriorityMessageStore</classname> is also provided.
			When this is used with a <classname>QueueChannel</classname>, the messages are received in
			(FIFO within) priority order. It uses the standard <classname
			>IntegrationMessageHeaderAccessor.PRIORITY</classname> header and supports priority values
			<code>0 - 9</code>; messages with other priorities (and messages with no priority) are retrieved
			in FIFO order after any messages with priority.
		</para>
		<important>
			These stores implement only <interfacename>BasicMessageGroupStore</interfacename> and
			do not implement <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename>; they
			can only be used for situations such as backing a <classname>QueueChannel</classname>.
		</important>
	</section>
  </section>
	<section id="redis-metadata-store">
		<title>Redis Metadata Store</title>
		<para>
			As of <emphasis>Spring Integration 3.0</emphasis> a new Redis-based
			<interfacename><ulink url="http://docs.spring.io/spring-integration/docs/latest-ga/api/org/springframework/integration/metadata/MetadataStore.html">MetadataStore</ulink></interfacename>
			(<xref linkend="metadata-store"/>) implementation is available. The <classname>RedisMetadataStore</classname> can
			be used to maintain state of a <interfacename>MetadataStore</interfacename>
			across application restarts. This new <interfacename>MetadataStore</interfacename>
			implementation can be used with adapters such as:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><xref linkend="twitter-inbound"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="feed-inbound-channel-adapter"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="file-reading"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ftp-inbound"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="sftp-inbound"/></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			In order to instruct these adapters to use the new <classname>RedisMetadataStore</classname>
			simply declare a Spring bean using the bean name <emphasis role="bold">metadataStore</emphasis>.
			The <emphasis>Twitter Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> and the
			<emphasis>Feed Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> will both automatically
			pick up and use the declared <classname>RedisMetadataStore</classname>.
		</para>
		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean name="metadataStore" class="o.s.i.redis.store.metadata.RedisMetadataStore">
    <constructor-arg name="connectionFactory" ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			The <classname>RedisMetadataStore</classname> is backed by
			<ulink url="http://docs.spring.io/spring-data/data-redis/docs/current/api/org/springframework/data/redis/support/collections/RedisProperties.html"
			><classname>RedisProperties</classname></ulink> and interaction with it uses
			<ulink url="http://docs.spring.io/spring-data/data-redis/docs/current/api/org/springframework/data/redis/core/BoundHashOperations.html"
			><classname>BoundHashOperations</classname></ulink>, which, in turn, requires a <code>key</code> for the entire
			<classname>Properties</classname> store. In the case of the <interfacename>MetadataStore</interfacename>, this
			<code>key</code> plays the role of a <emphasis>region</emphasis>, which is useful in distributed environment,
			when several applications use the same Redis server. By default this <code>key</code> has the value <code>MetaData</code>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Starting with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, this store now implements <interfacename
			>ConcurrentMetadataStore</interfacename>, allowing it to be reliably shared across multiple
			application instances where only one instance will be allowed to store or modify a key's value.
		</para>
	</section>
  <section id="redis-store-inbound-channel-adapter">
        <title>RedisStore Inbound Channel Adapter</title>

        <para>
        The <emphasis>RedisStore Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> is a polling consumer that reads data
        from a Redis collection and sends it as a Message payload.
        </para>

        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter id="listAdapter"
    connection-factory="redisConnectionFactory"
    key="myCollection"
    channel="redisChannel"
    collection-type="LIST" >
    <int:poller fixed-rate="2000" max-messages-per-poll="10"/>
</int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
        As you can see from the configuration above you configure a <emphasis>Redis Store Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> using
        the <code>store-inbound-channel-adapter</code> element, providing values for various attributes such as:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
          <listitem><code>key</code> or <code>key-expression</code> - The name of the key for the collection being used.</listitem>
          <listitem><code>collection-type</code> - enumeration of the Collection types supported by this adapter. Supported Collections are: LIST, SET, ZSET, PROPERTIES, MAP</listitem>
          <listitem><code>connection-factory</code> - reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.redis.connection.RedisConnectionFactory</classname></listitem>
          <listitem><code>redis-template</code> - reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate</classname></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
        and other attributes that are common across all other inbound adapters (e.g., 'channel').
        </para>
        <note>
          You cannot set both <code>redis-template</code> and <code>connection-factory</code>.
        </note>
        <important>
          By default, the adapter uses a <classname>StringRedisTemplate</classname>; this uses
          <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>s for keys, values, hash keys and hash values. If your
          Redis store contains objects that are serialized with other techniques, you must supply a
          <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> configured with appropriate serializers.
          For example, if the store is written to using a RedisStore Outbound Adapter that has its
          <code>extract-payload-elements</code> set to false, you must provide a
          <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> configured thus:
          <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisTemplate" class="org.springframework.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate">
    <property name="connectionFactory" ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
    <property name="keySerializer">
        <bean class="org.springframework.data.redis.serializer.StringRedisSerializer"/>
    </property>
    <property name="hashKeySerializer">
        <bean class="org.springframework.data.redis.serializer.StringRedisSerializer"/>
    </property>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          This uses String serializers for keys and hash keys and the default JDK Serialization serializers for
          values and hash values.
        </para>
        </important>
        <para>
        The example above is relatively simple and static since it has a literal value for the <code>key</code>.
        Sometimes, you may need to change the value of the key at runtime based on some condition.
        To do that, simply use <code>key-expression</code> instead, where the provided expression can be any valid SpEL expression.
        </para>
        <para>
        Also, you may wish to perform some post-processing to the successfully processed data that was read from the Redis collection.
        For example; you may want to move or remove the value after its been processed.
        You can do this using the Transaction Synchronization feature that was added with Spring Integration 2.2.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter id="zsetAdapterWithSingleScoreAndSynchronization"
        connection-factory="redisConnectionFactory"
        key-expression="'presidents'"
        channel="otherRedisChannel"
        auto-startup="false"
        collection-type="ZSET">
            <int:poller fixed-rate="1000" max-messages-per-poll="2">
                <int:transactional synchronization-factory="syncFactory"/>
            </int:poller>
</int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter>

<int:transaction-synchronization-factory id="syncFactory">
	<int:after-commit expression="payload.removeByScore(18, 18)"/>
</int:transaction-synchronization-factory>

<bean id="transactionManager" class="o.s.i.transaction.PseudoTransactionManager"/>]]></programlisting>


       <para>
       As you can see from the above all, you need to do is declare your poller to be transactional with a <code>transactional</code> element.
       This element can reference a real transaction manager (for example if some other part of your flow invokes JDBC).
       If you don't have a 'real' transaction, you can use a
       <classname>o.s.i.transaction.PseudoTransactionManager</classname> which is an implementation
       of Spring's <classname>PlatformTransactionManager</classname> and enables the use of the transaction synchronization
       features of the redis adapter when there is no actual transaction.
       </para>
       <important>
         This does NOT make the Redis activities themselves transactional, it simply allows the synchronization of actions to be taken before/after success (commit)
         or after failure (rollback).
       </important>
       <para>
       Once your poller is transactional all you need to do is set an instance of the
       <classname>org.springframework.integration.transaction.TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> on the <code>transactional</code> element.
       <classname>TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> will create an instance of the <classname>TransactionSynchronization</classname>.
       For your convenience we've exposed a default SpEL-based <classname>TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> which allows
       you to configure SpEL expressions, with their execution being coordinated (synchronized) with a transaction.
       Expressions for before-commit, after-commit, and after-rollback are supported, together with a channel for each where the
       evaluation result  (if any) will be sent. For each sub-element you can specify <code>expression</code> and/or <code>channel</code>
       attributes. If only the <code>channel</code> attribute is present the received Message will be sent there as part of the particular
       synchronization scenario. If only the <code>expression</code> attribute is present and the result of an expression is a non-Null
       value, a Message with the result as the payload will be generated and sent to a default channel (NullChannel) and will appear in the
       logs (DEBUG). If you want the evaluation result to go to a specific channel add a <code>channel</code> attribute. If the result of an
       expression is null or void, no Message will be generated.
       </para>
       <para>
       For more information about transaction synchronization, see <xref linkend="transaction-synchronization"/>.
       </para>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-store-outbound-channel-adapter">
        <title>RedisStore Outbound Channel Adapter</title>

        <para>
        The <emphasis>RedisStore Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> allows you to write a Message payload to a Redis collection
        </para>

        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:store-outbound-channel-adapter id="redisListAdapter"
          collection-type="LIST"
          channel="requestChannel"
          key="myCollection" />]]></programlisting>

        <para>
        As you can see from the configuration above, you configure a <emphasis>Redis Store Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> using
        the <code>store-inbound-channel-adapter</code> element, providing values for various attributes such as:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><code>key</code> or <code>key-expression</code> - The name of the key for the collection being used.</listitem>
          <listitem><code>extract-payload-elements</code> - If set to <code>true</code> (Default) and the payload is an instance of a "multi-
     value" object (i.e., Collection or Map) it will be stored using addAll/
     putAll semantics. Otherwise, if set to <code>false</code> the payload will be stored
     as a single entry regardless of its type. If the payload is not an instance
     of a "multi-value" object, the value of this attribute is ignored and the
     payload will always be stored as a single entry.</listitem>
          <listitem><code>collection-type</code> - enumeration of the Collection types supported by this adapter. Supported Collections are: LIST, SET, ZSET, PROPERTIES, MAP</listitem>
          <listitem><code>map-key-expression</code> - SpEL expression that returns the name of the key for entry being
     stored. Only applies if the <code>collection-type</code> is MAP or PROPERTIES and
     'extract-payload-elements' is false.</listitem>
          <listitem><code>connection-factory</code> - reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.redis.connection.RedisConnectionFactory</classname></listitem>
          <listitem><code>redis-template</code> - reference to an instance of <classname>o.s.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate</classname></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
        and other attributes that are common across all other inbound adapters (e.g., 'channel').
        </para>
        <note>
          You cannot set both <code>redis-template</code> and <code>connection-factory</code>.
        </note>

        <important>
          By default, the adapter uses a <classname>StringRedisTemplate</classname>; this uses
          <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>s for keys, values, hash keys and hash values. However, if
          <code>extract-payload-elements</code> is set to false, a <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> using
          <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>s for keys and hash keys, and
          <classname>JdkSerializationRedisSerializer</classname>s for values and hash values will be used. With the JDK serializer, it is important
          to understand that java serialization is used for all values, regardless of whether the value
          is actually a collection or not. If you need more control over
the serialization of values, you may want to consider providing your own
<classname>RedisTemplate</classname> rather than relying upon these defaults.
        </important>
    <para>
    The example above is relatively simple and static since it has a literal values for the <code>key</code> and other attributes.
    Sometimes you may need to change the values dynamically at runtime based on some condition.
    To do that simply use their <code>-expression</code> equivalents (<code>key-expression</code>, <code>map-key-expression</code> etc.) where
    the provided expression can be any valid SpEL expression.
    </para>
  </section>

	<section id="redis-outbound-gateway">
	<title>Redis Outbound Command Gateway</title>
		<para>
			Since <emphasis>Spring Integration 4.0</emphasis>, the Redis Command Gateway is available to
			perform any standard Redis command using generic
			<code>RedisConnection#execute</code>
			method:
			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:outbound-gateway
		request-channel="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-request-channel"/><![CDATA[
		reply-channel="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-reply-channel"/><![CDATA[
		requires-reply="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-requires-reply"/><![CDATA[
		reply-timeout="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-reply-timeout"/><![CDATA[
		connection-factory="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-connectionFactory"/><![CDATA[
		redis-template="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-template"/><![CDATA[
		arguments-serializer="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-arguments-serializer"/><![CDATA[
		command-expression="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-command-expression"/><![CDATA[
		argument-expressions="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-argument-expressions"/><![CDATA[
		use-command-variable="" ]]><co id="redis-o-g-use-command-variable"/><![CDATA[
		arguments-strategy="" />]]><co id="redis-o-g-arguments-strategy"/>
			</programlisting>
			<calloutlist>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-request-channel">
					<para>
						The <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> from which this Endpoint receives<interfacename>Message</interfacename>s.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-reply-channel">
					<para>
						The <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> where this Endpoint sends reply<interfacename>Message</interfacename>s.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-requires-reply">
					<para>
						Specify whether this outbound gateway must return a non-null value. This value is
						<code>false</code> by default, otherwise a ReplyRequiredException will be thrown when
						the Redis returns a <code>null</code> value.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-reply-timeout">
					<para>
						The timeout in milliseconds to wait until the reply message will be sent or not. Typically is
						applied for queue-based limited reply-channels.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-connectionFactory">
					<para>
						A reference to a <interfacename>RedisConnectionFactory</interfacename>bean.
						Defaults to <code>redisConnectionFactory</code>. Mutually exclusive with 'redis-template' attribute.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-template">
					<para>
						A reference to a <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> bean.
						Mutually exclusive with 'connection-factory' attribute.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-arguments-serializer">
					<para>
						Reference to an instance of<interfacename>org.springframework.data.redis.serializer.RedisSerializer</interfacename>.
						Used to serialize each command argument to byte[] if necessary.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-command-expression">
					<para>
						The SpEL expression that returns the command key. Default is the <code>redis_command</code> message header.
						Must not evaluate to <code>null</code>.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-argument-expressions">
					<para>
						Comma-separate SpEL expressions that will be evaluated as command arguments.
						Mutually exclusive with the <code>arguments-strategy</code> attribute. If neither of them is provided
						the <code>payload</code> is used as the command argument(s).
						Argument expressions may evaluate to 'null', to support a variable number of arguments.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-use-command-variable">
					<para>
						A <code>boolean</code> flag to specify if the evaluated Redis command string will be
						made available as the <code>#cmd</code> variable
						in the expression evaluation context in the
						<classname>org.springframework.integration.redis.outbound.ExpressionArgumentsStrategy</classname>
						when <code>argument-expressions</code> is configured, otherwise this attribute is ignored.
					</para>
				</callout>
				<callout arearefs="redis-o-g-arguments-strategy">
					<para>
						Reference to an instance of <interfacename>org.springframework.integration.redis.outbound.ArgumentsStrategy</interfacename>.
						Mutually exclusive with <code>argument-expressions</code> attribute. If neither of them is provided
						the <code>payload</code> is used as the command argument(s).
					</para>
				</callout>
			</calloutlist>
		</para>
		<para>
		   The <code>&lt;int-redis:outbound-gateway&gt;</code> can be used as a common component to perform any desired
		   Redis operation. For example to get incremented value from Redis Atomic Number:
			<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:outbound-gateway request-channel="requestChannel"
	reply-channel="replyChannel"
	command-expression="'INCR'"/>]]></programlisting>
			where the Message <code>payload</code> should be a name of <code>redisCounter</code>, which may be provided
			by <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.support.atomic.RedisAtomicInteger</classname> bean definition.
		</para>
		<para>
		  The <code>RedisConnection#execute</code> has a generic <classname>Object</classname> as return type and real
		  result depends on command type, for example <code>MGET</code> returns a <code>List&lt;byte[]&gt;</code>.
			For more information about commands, their arguments and result type see
		  <ulink url="http://redis.io/commands">Redis Specification</ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="redis-lock-registry">
		<title>Redis Lock Registry</title>
		<para>
			Starting with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, the <classname>RedisLockRegistry</classname> is
			available. Certain components (for example aggregator and resequencer) use a lock obtained from
			a <interfacename>LockRegistry</interfacename> instance to ensure
			that only one thread is manipulating a group at a time. The <classname>DefaultLockRegistry</classname>
			performs this function within a single component; you can now configure an external lock registry
			on these components. When used with a shared <interfacename>MessageGroupStore</interfacename>,
			the <classname>RedisLockRegistry</classname> can be use to provide this functionality across
			multiple application instances, such that only one instance can manipulate the group at a time.
		</para>
		<para>
			When a lock is released by a local thread, another local thread will generally be able to acquire the
			lock immediately. If a lock is released by a thread using a different registry instance, it can take up to
			100ms to acquire the lock.
		</para>
		<para>
			To avoid "hung" locks (when a server fails), the locks in this registry are expired after a default
			60 seconds, but this can be configured on the registry. Locks are normally held for a much smaller
			time.
		</para>
		<important>
			Because the keys can expire, an attempt to unlock an expired lock will result in an exception
			being thrown. However, be aware that the resources protected by such a lock may have been
			compromised so such exceptions should be considered severe. The expiry should be set at
			a large enough value to prevent this condition, while small enough that the lock can
			be recovered after a server failure in a reasonable amount of time.
		</important>
	</section>
</chapter>
