<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="redis"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <title>Redis Support</title>

  <para>
    Since version 2.1 Spring Integration introduces support for <ulink url="http://redis.io/">Redis</ulink>:
    <emphasis>"an open source advanced key-value store". </emphasis>
    This support comes in the form of a Redis-based MessageStore as well as Publish-Subscribe Messaging adapters that
    are supported by Redis via its <ulink url="http://redis.io/topics/pubsub">PUBLISH, SUBSCRIBE and UNSUBSCRIBE</ulink> commands.
  </para>

  <section id="redis-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      To download, install and run Redis please refer to the <ulink url="http://redis.io/download">Redis documentation</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-connection">
    <title>Connecting to Redis</title>
    
    <para>To begin interacting with Redis you first need to connect to it. Spring Integration uses support provided by another Spring project,
    <ulink url="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-redis">Spring Data Redis</ulink>, which provides typical Spring constructs:
    <classname>ConnectionFactory</classname> and <classname>Template</classname>. Those abstractions
    simplify integration with several Redis-client Java APIs. Currently Spring-Data-Redis supports 
    <ulink url="https://github.com/xetorthio/jedis">jedis</ulink>, <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/jredis/">jredis</ulink> and <ulink url="https://github.com/e-mzungu/rjc">rjc</ulink></para>
  
    <para><emphasis>RedisConnectionFactory</emphasis> </para>

    <para>
    To connect to Redis you would use one of the implementations of the <classname>RedisConnectionFactory</classname> interface:

      <programlisting lang="java"><![CDATA[public interface RedisConnectionFactory extends PersistenceExceptionTranslator {

	/**
	 * Provides a suitable connection for interacting with Redis.
	 *
	 * @return connection for interacting with Redis.
	 */
	RedisConnection getConnection();
}]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>The example below shows how to create a <classname>JedisConnectionFactory</classname>.</para>
    
    <para>In Java:
    <programlisting lang="java"><![CDATA[JedisConnectionFactory jcf = new JedisConnectionFactory();
jcf.afterPropertiesSet();]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>Or in Spring's XML configuration:
    <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisConnectionFactory" class="org.springframework.data.redis.connection.jedis.JedisConnectionFactory">
	<property name="port" value="7379" />
</bean>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>
    The implementations of RedisConnectionFactory provide a set of properties such as port and host that can be set if needed.
    Once an instance of RedisConnectionFactory is created, you can create an instance of RedisTemplate and inject it with the RedisConnectionFactory.
    </para>

    <para><emphasis>RedisTemplate</emphasis> </para>
     
    <para>
    As with other template classes in Spring (e.g., <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, <classname>JmsTemplate</classname>)
    <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> is a helper class that simplifies Redis data access code.
    For more information about <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> and its variations (e.g., <classname>StringRedisTemplate</classname>)
    please refer to the <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-data/data-redis/docs/current/reference/">Spring-Data-Redis documentation</ulink>
    </para>

    <para>The code below shows how to create an instance of <classname>RedisTemplate</classname>:</para>

    <para>In Java:
    <programlisting lang="java"><![CDATA[RedisTemplate rt = new RedisTemplate<String, Object>();
rt.setConnectionFactory(redisConnectionFactory);]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>Or in Spring's XML configuration::
    <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisTemplate" class="org.springframework.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate">
	<property name="connectionFactory" ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-messages">
    <title>Messaging with Redis</title>

    <para>
    As mentioned in the introduction Redis provides support for Publish-Subscribe messaging via its PUBLISH, SUBSCRIBE and UNSUBSCRIBE 
    commands. As with JMS and AMQP, Spring Integration provides Message Channels and adapters for sending and receiving messages via Redis.
    </para>

    <section id="redis-pub-sub-channel">
      <title>Redis Publish/Subscribe channel</title>

      <para>
      Similar to the JMS there are cases where both the producer and consumer are intended to be part of the same application, running 
      within the same process. This could be accomplished by using a pair of inbound and outbound Channel Adapters, 
      however just like with Spring Integration's JMS support, there is a simpler approach to address this use case.
      <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:publish-subscribe-channel id="redisChannel" topic-name="si.test.topic"/>]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>
      The publish-subscribe-channel (above) will behave much like a normal <code>&lt;publish-subscribe-channel/&gt;</code> element from the 
      main Spring Integration namespace. It can be referenced by both <code>input-channel</code> and <code>output-channel</code> attributes of
      any endpoint. The difference is that this channel is backed by a Redis topic name - a String value specified by the <code>topic-name</code>
      attribute. However unlike JMS this topic doesn't have to be created in advance or even auto-created by Redis. In Redis topics are simple
      String values that play the role of an address, and all the producer and consumer need to do to communicate is use the same String value
      as their topic name. A simple subscription to this channel means that asynchronous pub-sub messaging is possible between the producing and
      consuming endpoints, but unlike the asynchronous Message Channels created by adding a <code> &lt;queue/&gt;</code> sub-element within
      a simple Spring Integration <code>&lt;channel/&gt;</code> element, the Messages are not just stored in an in-memory queue. Instead those
      Messages are passed through Redis allowing you to rely on its support for persistence and clustering as well as its interoperability with
      other non-java platforms.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="redis-inbound-channel-adapter">
      <title>Redis Inbound Channel Adapter</title>
      <para>
      The Redis-based Inbound Channel Adapter adapts incoming Redis messages into Spring Integration Messages in the same way as other
      inbound adapters. It receives platform-specific messages (Redis in this case) and converts them to Spring Integration Messages using  
      a <classname>MessageConverter</classname> strategy.

      <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:inbound-channel-adapter id="redisAdapter"
       topics="foo, bar"
       channel="receiveChannel"
       error-channel="testErrorChannel"
       message-converter="testConverter" />

<bean id="redisConnectionFactory" class="org.springframework.data.redis.connection.jedis.JedisConnectionFactory">
    <property name="port" value="7379" />
</bean>

<bean id="testConverter" class="foo.bar.SampleMessageConverter" />]]></programlisting>
      </para>

      <para>
      Above is a simple but complete configuration of a Redis Inbound Channel Adapter. Note that the above configuration relies on the 
      familiar Spring paradigm of auto-discovering certain beans. In this case the <code>redisConnectionFactory</code> is implicitly
      injected into the adapter. You can of course specify it explicitly using the <code>connection-factory</code> attribute instead.
      </para>

      <para>
      Also, note that the above configuration injects the adapter with a custom <code>MessageConverter</code>.
      The approach is similar to JMS where <code>MessageConverters</code> are used to convert between 
      Redis Messages and the Spring Integration Message payloads. The default is a <code>SimpleMessageConverter</code>.
      </para>

      <para>Inbound adapters can subscribe to multiple topic names hence the comma-delimited set of values in the
      <code>topics</code> attribute.</para>
    </section>
 
    <section id="redis-outbound-channel-adapter">
      <title>Redis Outbound Channel Adapter</title>
      <para>
      The Redis-based Outbound Channel Adapter adapts outgoing Spring Integration messages into Redis messages in the same way as 
      other outbound adapters. It receives Spring Integration messages and converts them to platform-specific messages (Redis in this case)
      using a <classname>MessageConverter</classname> strategy.

     <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:outbound-channel-adapter id="outboundAdapter"
			channel="sendChannel"
			topic="foo"
			message-converter="testConverter"/>

<bean id="redisConnectionFactory" class="org.springframework.data.redis.connection.jedis.JedisConnectionFactory">
	<property name="port" value="7379"/>
</bean>

<bean id="testConverter" class="foo.bar.SampleMessageConverter" />]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
      As you can see the configuration is similar to the Redis Inbound Channel Adapter. The adapter is implicitly injected with
      a <classname>RedisConnectionFactory</classname> which was defined with '<code>redisConnectionFactory</code>' as its bean name.
      This example also includes the optional, custom <classname>MessageConverter</classname> (the '<code>testConverter</code>' bean). 
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="redis-message-store">
    <title>Redis Message Store</title>
	
	<para>
    As described in EIP, a <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/MessageStore.html">Message Store</ulink> allows you to persist Messages.
    This can be very useful when dealing with components that have a capability to buffer messages
    (<emphasis>QueueChannel, Aggregator, Resequencer</emphasis>, etc.) if reliability is a concern.
    In Spring Integration, the MessageStore strategy also provides the foundation for the 
	<ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/StoreInLibrary.html">ClaimCheck</ulink> pattern, which is described in EIP as well.
	</para>

	<para>
    Spring Integration's Redis module provides the <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname> which is an implementation of both the
    the <classname>MessageStore</classname> strategy (mainly used by the <emphasis>QueueChannel</emphasis> and <emphasis>ClaimCheck</emphasis>
    patterns) and the <classname>MessageGroupStore</classname> strategy (mainly used by the <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>Resequencer</emphasis> patterns).
    </para>

	<para>
	<programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="redisMessageStore" class="org.springframework.integration.redis.store.RedisMessageStore">
    <constructor-arg ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
</bean>

<int:channel id="somePersistentQueueChannel">
    <int:queue message-store="redisMessageStore"/>
<int:channel>

<int:aggregator input-channel="inputChannel" output-channel="outputChannel"
         message-store="redisMessageStore"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
    Above is a sample <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname> configuration that shows its usage by a <emphasis>QueueChannel</emphasis>
    and an <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis>. As you can see it is a simple bean configuration, and it expects a
    <classname>RedisConnectionFactory</classname> as a constructor argument.
    </para>

    <para>By default the <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname> will use Java serialization to serialize the Message.
    However if you want to use a different serialization technique (e.g., JSON), you can provide your own serializer via
    the <code>valueSerializer</code> property of the <classname>RedisMessageStore</classname>.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="redis-store-inbound-channel-adapter">
        <title>RedisStore Inbound Channel Adapter</title>

        <para>
        The <emphasis>RedisStore Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> is a polling consumer that reads data
        from a Redis collection and sends it as a Message payload.
        </para>

        <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter id="listAdapter"
		connection-factory="redisConnectionFactory"
		key="myCollection"
		channel="redisChannel"
		collection-type="LIST" >
			<int:poller fixed-rate="2000" max-messages-per-poll="10"/>
</int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter>]]></programlisting>	

        <para>
        As you can see from the configuration above you configure a <emphasis>Redis Store Inbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> using
        the <code>store-inbound-channel-adapter</code> element, providing values for various attributes such as: 
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>key</code> or <code>key-expression</code> - The name of the key for the collection being used. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>collection-type</code> - enumeration of the Collection types supported by this adapter. Supported Collections are:     LIST, SET, ZSET, PROPERTIES, MAP  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>connection-factory</code>  - 
            reference to an instance of <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.connection.RedisConnectionFactory</classname>  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>redis-template</code>  - 
             reference to an instance of <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate</classname>
             </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        and other attributes that are common across all other inbound adapters (e.g., 'channel').  
        </para>
        <note>
          You cannot set both <code>redis-template</code> and <code>connection-factory</code>.
        </note>
        <important>
          By default, the adapter uses a <classname>StringRedisTemplate</classname>; this uses
          <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>s for keys, values, hash keys and hash values. If your
          Redis store contains objects that are serialized with other techniques, you must supply a
          <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> configured with appropriate serializers.
          For example, if the store is written to using a RedisStore Outbound Adapter that has its
          <code>extract-payload-elements</code> set to false, you must provide a
          <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> configured thus:
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="redisTemplate" class="org.springframework.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate">
	<property name="connectionFactory" ref="redisConnectionFactory"/>
	<property name="keySerializer">
		<bean class="org.springframework.data.redis.serializer.StringRedisSerializer"/>
	</property>
	<property name="hashKeySerializer">
		<bean class="org.springframework.data.redis.serializer.StringRedisSerializer"/>
	</property>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
          This uses String serializers for keys and hash keys and the default JDK Serialization serializers for
          values and hash values.
        </para>
        </important>
        <para>
        The example above is relatively simple and static since it has a literal value for the <code>key</code>.
        Sometimes, you may need to change the value of the key at runtime based on some condition.
        To do that, simply use <code>key-expression</code> instead, where the provided expression can be any valid SpEL expression.
        </para>
        <para>
        Also, you may wish to perform some post-processing to the successfully processed data that was read from the Redis collection.
        For example; you may want to move or remove the value after its been processed.
        You can do this using the Transaction Synchronization feature that was added with Spring Integration 2.2. 
        </para>
        <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter id="zsetAdapterWithSingleScoreAndSynchronization"
        connection-factory="redisConnectionFactory"
        key-expression="'presidents'"
        channel="otherRedisChannel"
        auto-startup="false"
        collection-type="ZSET">
            <int:poller fixed-rate="1000" max-messages-per-poll="2">
                <int:transactional synchronization-factory="syncFactory"/>
            </int:poller>
</int-redis:store-inbound-channel-adapter>

<int:transaction-synchronization-factory id="syncFactory">
	<int:after-commit expression="payload.removeByScore(18, 18)"/>
</int:transaction-synchronization-factory>

<bean id="transactionManager" class="org.springframework.integration.transaction.PseudoTransactionManager"/>]]></programlisting>


       <para>
       As you can see from the above all, you need to do is declare your poller to be transactional with a <code>transactional</code> element.
       This element can reference a real transaction manager (for example if some other part of your flow invokes JDBC).
       If you don't have a 'real' transaction, you can use a
       <classname>org.springframework.integration.transaction.PseudoTransactionManager</classname> which is an implementation
       of Spring's <classname>PlatformTransactionManager</classname> and enables the use of the transaction synchronization
       features of the redis adapter when there is no actual transaction.
       </para>
       <important>
         This does NOT make the Redis activities themselves transactional, it simply allows the synchronization of actions to be taken before/after success (commit)
         or after failure (rollback).
       </important>
       <para>
       Once your poller is transactional all you need to do is set an instance of the
       <classname>org.springframework.integration.transaction.TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> on the <code>transactional</code> element. 
       <classname>TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> will create an instance of the <classname>TransactionSynchronization</classname>.
       For your convenience we've exposed a default SpEL-based <classname>TransactionSynchronizationFactory</classname> which allows
       you to configure SpEL expressions, with their execution being coordinated (synchronized) with a transaction.
       Expressions for before-commit, after-commit, and after-rollback are supported, together with a channel for each where the
       evaluation result  (if any) will be sent. For each sub-element you can specify <code>expression</code> and/or <code>channel</code>
       attributes. If only the <code>channel</code> attribute is present the received Message will be sent there as part of the particular
       synchronization scenario. If only the <code>expression</code> attribute is present and the result of an expression is a non-Null
       value, a Message with the result as the payload will be generated and sent to a default channel (NullChannel) and will appear in the
       logs (DEBUG). If you want the evaluation result to go to a specific channel add a <code>channel</code> attribute. If the result of an
       expression is null or void, no Message will be generated.
       </para>
       <para>
       For more information about transaction synchronization, see <xref linkend="transaction-synchronization"/>.
       </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="redis-store-outbound-channel-adapter">
        <title>RedisStore Outbound Channel Adapter</title>

        <para>
        The <emphasis>RedisStore Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> allows you to write a Message payload to a Redis collection
        </para>

        <programlisting lang="xml"><![CDATA[<int-redis:store-outbound-channel-adapter id="redisListAdapter"
          collection-type="LIST"
          channel="requestChannel"
          key="myCollection" />]]></programlisting>    

        <para>
        As you can see from the configuration above, you configure a <emphasis>Redis Store Outbound Channel Adapter</emphasis> using
        the <code>store-inbound-channel-adapter</code> element, providing values for various attributes such as: 
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>key</code> or <code>key-expression</code> - The name of the key for the collection being used. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>extract-payload-elements</code>  - If set to <code>true</code> (Default) and the payload is an instance of a "multi-
     value" object (i.e., Collection or Map) it will be stored using addAll/
     putAll semantics. Otherwise, if set to <code>false</code> the payload will be stored 
     as a single entry regardless of its type. If the payload is not an instance 
     of a "multi-value" object, the value of this attribute is ignored and the 
     payload will always be stored as a single entry.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>collection-type</code> - enumeration of the Collection types supported by this adapter. Supported Collections are: LIST, SET, ZSET, PROPERTIES, MAP  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>map-key-expression</code>  - SpEL expression that returns the name of the key for entry being
     stored. Only applies if the <code>collection-type</code> is MAP or PROPERTIES and
     'extract-payload-elements' is false. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>connection-factory</code>  -
            reference to an instance of <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.connection.RedisConnectionFactory</classname>  </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>redis-template</code>  -
             reference to an instance of <classname>org.springframework.data.redis.core.RedisTemplate</classname></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        and other attributes that are common across all other inbound adapters (e.g., 'channel').
        <note>
          You cannot set both <code>redis-template</code> and <code>connection-factory</code>.
        </note>
        </para>
        <important>
          By default, the adapter uses a <classname>StringRedisTemplate</classname>; this uses
          <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>s for keys, values, hash keys and hash values. However, if
          <code>extract-payload-elements</code> is set to false, a <classname>RedisTemplate</classname> using
          <classname>StringRedisSerializer</classname>s for keys and hash keys, and
          <classname>JdkSerializationRedisSerializer</classname>s for values and hash values will be used. With the JDK serializer, it is important
          to understand that java serialization is used for all values, regardless of whether the value
          is actually a collection or not. If you need more control over
the serialization of values, you may want to consider providing your own
<classname>RedisTemplate</classname> rather than relying upon these defaults.
        </important>
    <para>
    The example above is relatively simple and static since it has a literal values for the <code>key</code> and other attributes.
    Sometimes you may need to change the values dynamically at runtime based on some condition.
    To do that simply use their <code>-expression</code> equivalents (<code>key-expression</code>, <code>map-key-expression</code> etc.) where
    the provided expression can be any valid SpEL expression.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>