<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="transformer"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Transformer</title>

  <section id="transformer-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Message Transformers play a very important role in enabling the loose-coupling of Message Producers and Message
      Consumers. Rather than requiring every Message-producing component to know what type is expected by the next
      consumer, Transformers can be added between those components. Generic transformers, such as one that converts a
      String to an XML Document, are also highly reusable.
    </para>
    <para>
      For some systems, it may be best to provide a
      <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/CanonicalDataModel.html">Canonical Data Model</ulink>, but Spring
      Integration's general philosophy is not to require any particular format. Rather, for maximum flexibility, Spring
      Integration aims to provide the simplest possible model for extension. As with the other endpoint types, the use
      of declarative configuration in XML and/or Annotations enables simple POJOs to be adapted for the role of Message
      Transformers. These configuration options will be described below.
      <note>
        For the same reason of maximizing flexibility, Spring does not require XML-based Message payloads.
        Nevertheless, the framework does provide some convenient Transformers for dealing with XML-based payloads if
        that is indeed the right choice for your application. For more information on those transformers, see
        <xref linkend="xml"/>.
      </note>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="transformer-config">
  	<title>Configuring Transformer</title>


  	 <section id="transformer-namespace">
    <title>Configuring Transformer with XML</title>
    <para>
    The &lt;transformer&gt; element is used to create a Message-transforming endpoint. In addition to "input-channel"
      and "output-channel" attributes, it requires a "ref". The "ref" may either point to an Object that contains the
      @Transformer annotation on a single method (see below) or it may be combined with an explicit method name value
      provided via the "method" attribute.
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:transformer id="testTransformer" ref="testTransformerBean" input-channel="inChannel"
             method="transform" output-channel="outChannel"/>
<beans:bean id="testTransformerBean" class="org.foo.TestTransformer" />]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      Using a "ref" attribute is generally recommended if the custom transformer handler implementation can be reused in
      other <code>&lt;transformer&gt;</code> definitions. However if the custom transformer handler implementation should
      be scoped to a single definition of the <code>&lt;transformer&gt;</code>, you can define an inner bean definition:
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:transformer id="testTransformer" input-channel="inChannel" method="transform"
                output-channel="outChannel">
  <beans:bean class="org.foo.TestTransformer"/>
</transformer>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Using both the "ref" attribute and an inner handler definition in the same <code>&lt;transformer&gt;</code>
        configuration is not allowed, as it creates an ambiguous condition and will result in an Exception being thrown.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      The method that is used for transformation may expect either the <interfacename>Message</interfacename> type or
      the payload type of inbound Messages. It may also accept Message header values either individually or as a full
      map by using the <code>@Header</code> and <code>@Headers</code> parameter annotations respectively. The return value of the method can be
      any type. If the return value is itself a <interfacename>Message</interfacename>, that will be passed along to
      the transformer's output channel.
    </para>
    <para>
    As of Spring Integration 2.0, a Message Transformer's transformation method can no longer return <code>null</code>.
    Returning <code>null</code> will result in an exception since a Message Transformer should always be expected to
    transform each source Message into a valid target Message. In other words, a Message Transformer should not be used
    as a Message Filter since there is a dedicated &lt;filter&gt; option for that. However, if you do need this type of
    behavior (where a component might return NULL and that should not be considered an error), a
    <emphasis>service-activator</emphasis> could be used. Its <code>requires-reply</code> value is FALSE by default,
    but that can be set to TRUE in order to have Exceptions thrown for NULL return values as with the transformer.
    </para>

    <para>
    	<emphasis>Transformers and Spring Expression Language (SpEL)</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>
    Just like Routers, Aggregators and other components, as of Spring Integration 2.0 Transformers can also benefit from SpEL support
    (http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/expressions.html)
    whenever transformation logic is relatively simple.

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:transformer input-channel="inChannel"
	output-channel="outChannel"
	expression="payload.toUpperCase() + '- [' + T(java.lang.System).currentTimeMillis() + ']'"/>]]></programlisting>

	In the above configuration we are achieving a simple transformation of the <emphasis>payload</emphasis> with a simple SpEL
	expression and without writing a custom transformer. Our <emphasis>payload</emphasis> (assuming String) will be
	upper-cased and concatenated with the current timestamp with some simple formatting.
    </para>

    <para>
    	<emphasis>Common Transformers</emphasis>
    </para>
  <para>
    There are also a few Transformer implementations available out of the box. Because, it is fairly common
    to use the <methodname>toString()</methodname> representation of an Object, Spring Integration provides an
    <classname>ObjectToStringTransformer</classname> whose output is a Message with a String payload. That String
    is the result of invoking the toString() operation on the inbound Message's payload.

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:object-to-string-transformer input-channel="in" output-channel="out"/>]]></programlisting>

    A potential example for this would be sending some arbitrary object to the 'outbound-channel-adapter' in the
    <emphasis>file</emphasis> namespace. Whereas that Channel Adapter only supports String, byte-array, or
    <classname>java.io.File</classname> payloads by default, adding this transformer immediately before the
    adapter will handle the necessary conversion. Of course, that works fine as long as the result of the
    <methodname>toString()</methodname> call is what you want to be written to the File. Otherwise, you can
    just provide a custom POJO-based Transformer via the generic 'transformer' element shown previously.
    <tip>
      When debugging, this transformer is not typically necessary since the 'logging-channel-adapter' is capable
      of logging the Message payload. Refer to <xref linkend="channel-wiretap"/> for more detail.
    </tip>
    <note>
      <para>
        The <emphasis>object-to-string-transformer</emphasis> is very simple; it invokes <code>toString()</code>
        on the inbound payload. There are two exceptions to this (since 3.0): if the payload is a <code>char[]</code>,
        it invokes <code>new String(payload)</code>; if the payload is a <code>byte[]</code>, it invokes
        <code>new String(payload, charset)</code>, where <code>charset</code> is "UTF-8" by default. The
        <code>charset</code> can be modified by supplying the <emphasis>charset</emphasis> attribute on
        the transformer.
      </para>
      <para>
        For more sophistication (such as selection of the charset dynamically, at runtime), you can use
        a SpEL expression-based transformer instead; for example:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:transformer input-channel="in" output-channel="out"
		 expression="new java.lang.String(payload, headers['myCharset']" />]]></programlisting>
    </note>
  </para>
  <para>
    If you need to serialize an Object to a byte array or deserialize a byte array back into an Object,
    Spring Integration provides symmetrical serialization transformers. These will use standard Java serialization
    by default, but you can provide an implementation of Spring 3.0's Serializer or Deserializer strategies via the
    'serializer' and 'deserializer' attributes, respectively.

      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:payload-serializing-transformer input-channel="objectsIn" output-channel="bytesOut"/>

<int:payload-deserializing-transformer input-channel="bytesIn" output-channel="objectsOut"/>]]></programlisting>
  </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Object-to-Map Transformer</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    Spring Integration also provides <emphasis>Object-to-Map</emphasis> and <emphasis>Map-to-Object</emphasis> transformers which
    utilize the Spring Expression Language (SpEL) to serialize and de-serialize the object graphs. The object hierarchy is introspected
    to the most primitive types (String, int, etc.). The path to this type is described via SpEL, which becomes the <emphasis>key</emphasis> in the
    transformed Map. The primitive type becomes the value.
    </para>
    <para>
    For example:
    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class Parent{
    private Child child;
    private String name; 
    // setters and getters are omitted
}

public class Child{
   private String name; 
   private List<String> nickNames;
   // setters and getters are omitted
}]]></programlisting>
... will be transformed to a Map which looks like this:
<code>{person.name=George, person.child.name=Jenna, person.child.nickNames[0]=Bimbo . . . etc}</code>
    </para>
    <para>
    The SpEL-based Map allows you to describe the object structure without sharing the actual types allowing
    you to restore/rebuild the object graph into a differently typed Object graph as long as you maintain the structure.
    </para>
    <para>
    For example:
    The above structure could be easily restored back to the following Object graph via the Map-to-Object transformer:
<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class Father {
    private Kid child;
    private String name; 
    // setters and getters are omitted
}

public class Kid {
   private String name; 
   private List<String> nickNames;
   // setters and getters are omitted
}]]></programlisting>
    </para>
	<para>
	If you need to create a "structured" map, you can provide the 'flatten' attribute. The default value for this
	attribute is 'true' meaning the default behavior; if you provide a 'false' value, then the structure will be a
	map of maps.
	</para>
	<para>
	For example:
	<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class Parent {
	private Child child;
	private String name;
	// setters and getters are omitted
}

public class Child {
	private String name;
	private List<String> nickNames;
	// setters and getters are omitted
}]]></programlisting>
	... will be transformed to a Map which looks like this:
	<code>{name=George, child={name=Jenna, nickNames=[Bimbo, ...]}}</code>
	</para>
    <para>
    To configure these transformers, Spring Integration provides namespace support
    Object-to-Map:
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:object-to-map-transformer input-channel="directInput" output-channel="output"/>]]></programlisting>
  or
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:object-to-map-transformer input-channel="directInput" output-channel="output" flatten="false"/>]]></programlisting>
    Map-to-Object
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:map-to-object-transformer input-channel="input" 
                         output-channel="output" 
                          type="org.foo.Person"/>]]></programlisting>
  or
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:map-to-object-transformer input-channel="inputA" 
                                output-channel="outputA" 
                                ref="person"/>
<bean id="person" class="org.foo.Person" scope="prototype"/>
]]></programlisting>

    </para>
    <note>
    NOTE: 'ref' and 'type' attributes are mutually exclusive. You can only use one.
    Also, if using the 'ref' attribute, you must point to a 'prototype' scoped bean, otherwise
    a BeanCreationException will be thrown. 
    </note>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">JSON Transformers</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis>Object to JSON</emphasis> and <emphasis>JSON to Object</emphasis> transformers are provided.
    </para>
    <para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:object-to-json-transformer input-channel="objectMapperInput"/>]]></programlisting>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:json-to-object-transformer input-channel="objectMapperInput"
    type="foo.MyDomainObject"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
        These use a vanilla Jackson ObjectMapper by default. If you wish to customize the ObjectMapper (for example,
        to configure the 'ALLOW_COMMENTS' feature when parsing JSON), you can supply a reference to your custom ObjectMapper bean using
        the object-mapper attribute.
    </para>
    <para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:json-to-object-transformer input-channel="objectMapperInput"
    type="foo.MyDomainObject" object-mapper="customObjectMapper"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Beginning with version 3.0, the <code>object-mapper</code> attribute references an instance of a new
        strategy interface <interfacename>JsonObjectMapper</interfacename>. This abstraction allows multiple
        implementations of json mappers to be used. Implementations that wrap
        <ulink url="http://jackson.codehaus.org">Jackson 1.x</ulink>  and
        <ulink url="https://github.com/FasterXML">Jackson 2</ulink>  are
        provided, with the version being detected on the classpath. These classes are
        <classname>JacksonJsonObjectMapper</classname> and <classname>Jackson2JsonObjectMapper</classname>.
      </para>
      <para>
        For backward compatibility, a simple Jackson 1.x <classname>ObjectMapper</classname> can be provided
        instead of a <interfacename>JsonObjectMapper</interfacename>. This will be removed in a future release.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
		<important>
			If there are requirements to use both Jackson libraries in the same application, keep in mind that
			before version 3.0, the JSON transformers used only Jackson 1.x and, from 3.0 on, the framework will
			select Jackson 2 by default, if both are on the classpath.
			So, to avoid unexpected issues with Jackson's mapping features, when using annotations, there may be
			a need to apply annotations from both Jacksons on domain classes:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[@org.codehaus.jackson.annotate.JsonIgnoreProperties(ignoreUnknown=true)
@com.fasterxml.jackson.annotation.JsonIgnoreProperties(ignoreUnknown=true)
public class Foo {

        @org.codehaus.jackson.annotate.JsonProperty("fooBar")
        @com.fasterxml.jackson.annotation.JsonProperty("fooBar")
        public Object bar;

}]]></programlisting>
		</important>
    </para>
    <para>
        You may wish to consider using a <interfacename>FactoryBean</interfacename> or simple factory
        method to create the <classname>JsonObjectMapper</classname> with
        the required characteristics.
    </para>
    <para>
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class ObjectMapperFactory {

    public static Jackson2JsonObjectMapper getMapper() {
        ObjectMapper mapper = new ObjectMapper();
        mapper.configure(JsonParser.Feature.ALLOW_COMMENTS, true);
        return new Jackson2JsonObjectMapper(mapper);
    }
}]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<bean id="customObjectMapper" class="foo.ObjectMapperFactory"
            factory-method="getMapper"/>]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <important>
     <para>
      Beginning with <emphasis>version 2.2</emphasis>, the <code>object-to-json-transformer</code> sets the <emphasis>content-type</emphasis>
      header to <code>application/json</code>, by default, if the input message does not already have that header
      present.
     </para>
     <para>
      It you wish to set the <emphasis>content type</emphasis> header to some other value, or explicitly overwrite any existing header
      with some value (including <code>application/json</code>), use the <code>content-type</code>
      attribute. If you wish to suppress the setting of the header, set the <code>content-type</code>
      attribute to an empty string (<code>""</code>). This will result in a message with no <code>content-type</code>
      header, unless such a header was present on the input message.
     </para>
    </important>
    <para>
      Beginning with <emphasis>version 3.0</emphasis>, the <classname>ObjectToJsonTransformer</classname> adds headers,
      reflecting the source type, to the message. Similarly, the <classname>JsonToObjectTransformer</classname> can
      use those type headers when converting the JSON to an object. These headers are mapped in the AMQP adapters so that
      they are entirely compatible with the Spring-AMQP
      <ulink url="http://docs.spring.io/spring-amqp/api/">JsonMessageConverter</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      This enables the following flows to work without any special configuration...
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>...->amqp-outbound-adapter----></code>
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>---->amqp-inbound-adapter->json-to-object-transformer->...</code>
    </para>
    <para>
       Where the outbound adapter is configured with a <classname>JsonMessageConverter</classname> and the
       inbound adapter uses the default <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>...->object-to-json-transformer->amqp-outbound-adapter----></code>
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>---->amqp-inbound-adapter->...</code>
    </para>
    <para>
       Where the outbound adapter is configured with a <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname> and the
       inbound adapter uses the default <classname>JsonMessageConverter</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>...->object-to-json-transformer->amqp-outbound-adapter----></code>
    </para>
    <para>
      <code>---->amqp-inbound-adapter->json-to-object-transformer-></code>
    </para>
    <para>
       Where both adapters are configured with a <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname>.
    </para>
    <note>
      When using the headers to determine the type, you should <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> provide
      a <code>class</code> attribute, because it takes precedence over the headers.
    </note>
    <para>
      In addition to JSON Transformers, Spring Integration provides a built-in <emphasis>#jsonPath</emphasis>
      SpEL function for use in expressions. For more information see <xref linkend="spel"/>.
    </para>
    <para id="transformer-xpath-spel-function">
        <emphasis role="bold">#xpath SpEL Function</emphasis>
    </para>
	<para>
	 Since version <emphasis>3.0</emphasis>, Spring Integration also provides a built-in <emphasis>#xpath</emphasis>
	 SpEL function for use in expressions. For more information see <xref linkend="xpath-spel-function"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		Beginning with <emphasis>version 4.0</emphasis>, the <classname>ObjectToJsonTransformer</classname>
		supports the <code>resultType</code> property, to specify the <emphasis>node</emphasis> JSON representation.
		The result node tree representation depends on the implementation of the provided <interfacename>JsonObjectMapper</interfacename>.
		By default, the <classname>ObjectToJsonTransformer</classname> uses a <classname>Jackson2JsonObjectMapper</classname>
		and delegates the conversion of the object to the node tree to the <classname>ObjectMapper#valueToTree</classname> method.
		The node JSON representation provides efficiency for using the <classname>JsonPropertyAccessor</classname>, when the
		downstream message flow uses SpEL expressions with access to the properties of the JSON data. See
		<xref linkend="spel-property-accessors"/>.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="transformer-annotation">
    <title>Configuring a Transformer with Annotations</title>
    <para>
      The <interfacename>@Transformer</interfacename> annotation can also be added to methods that expect either the
      <interfacename>Message</interfacename> type or the message payload type. The return value will be handled in the
      exact same way as described above in the section describing the &lt;transformer&gt; element.
      <programlisting language="java">@Transformer
Order generateOrder(String productId) {
    return new Order(productId);
}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      Transformer methods may also accept the @Header and @Headers annotations that is documented in <xref linkend="annotations"/>
        <programlisting language="java">@Transformer
Order generateOrder(String productId, @Header("customerName") String customer) {
    return new Order(productId, customer);
}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
        Also see <xref linkend="advising-with-annotations"/>.
    </para>
  </section>

  </section>


  <section id="header-filter">
  	<title>Header Filter</title>

  	Some times your transformation use case might be as simple as removing a few headers.
  	For such a use case, Spring Integration provides a <emphasis>Header Filter</emphasis> which allows you to specify certain header names
    that should be removed from the output Message (e.g. for security reasons or a value that was only needed temporarily).
  	Basically the <emphasis>Header Filter</emphasis> is the opposite  of the <emphasis>Header Enricher</emphasis>.
  	The latter is discussed in <xref linkend="header-enricher"/>

	    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:header-filter input-channel="inputChannel"
		output-channel="outputChannel" header-names="lastName, state"/>]]></programlisting>

	As you can see, configuration of a <emphasis>Header Filter</emphasis> is quite simple. It is a typical endpoint with input/output channels
	and a <code>header-names</code> attribute. That attribute accepts the names of the header(s) (delimited by commas if there are multiple)
	that need to be removed. So, in the above example the headers named 'lastName' and 'state' will not be present on the outbound Message.
  </section>

</section>
