<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="aggregator">
  <title>Aggregator</title>

  <section id="aggregator-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Basically a mirror-image of the Splitter, the Aggregator is a type
    of Message Handler that receives multiple Messages and combines them into
    a single Message. In fact, Aggregators are often downstream consumers in a
    pipeline that includes a Splitter.</para>

    <para>Technically, the Aggregator is more complex than a Splitter, because
    it is required to maintain state (the Messages to-be-aggregated), to
    decide when the complete group of Messages is available, and to timeout if
    necessary. Furthermore, in case of a timeout, the Aggregator needs to know
    whether to send the partial results or to discard them to a separate
    channel.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-functionality">
    <title>Functionality</title>

    <para>The Aggregator combines a group of related messages, by correlating
    and storing them, until the group is deemed complete. At that point, the
    Aggregator will create a single message by processing the whole group, and
    will send that aggregated message as output.</para>

    <para>As messages might arrive with a certain delay (or certain messages
    from the group might not arrive at all), the Aggregator can specify a
    timeout (counted from the moment when the first message in the group has
    arrived), and whether, in the case of a timeout, the group should be
    discarded, or the Aggregator should merely attempt to create a single
    message out of what has arrived so far. An important aspect of
    implementing an Aggregator is providing the logic that has to be executed
    when the aggregation (creation of a single message out of many) takes
    place.</para>

    <para>In Spring Integration, the grouping of the messages for aggregation
    is done by default based on their CORRELATION_ID message header (i.e. the
    messages with the same CORRELATION_ID will be grouped together). However,
    this can be customized, and the users can opt for other ways of
    specifying how the messages should be grouped together, by using a
    CorrelationStrategy (see below).</para>

    <para>An important concern with respect to the timeout is, what happens if
    late messages arrive after the aggregation has taken place? In this case,
    a configuration option allows the user to decide whether they should be
    discarded or not.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-api">
    <title>Programming model</title>

    <para>The Aggregation API consists of a number of classes:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The base class <code>AbstractMessageAggregator </code>and its
        subclass <code>MethodInvokingMessageAggregator</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <code>CompletionStrategy</code> interface and its default
        implementation <code>SequenceSizeCompletionStrategy</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <code>CorrelationStrategy</code> interface and its default
        implementation <code>HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>AbstractMessageAggregator</title>

      <para>The <code>AbstractMessageAggregator</code> is a
      <code>MessageHandler</code> implementation, encapsulating the common
      functionalities of an Aggregator, which are:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>correlating messages into a group to be aggregated</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>maintaining those messages until the group is complete</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>deciding when the group is in fact complete</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>processing the completed group into a single aggregated message</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>recognizing and responding to a timed-out completion attempt</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The responsibility of deciding how the messages should be grouped together
      is delegated to a <code>CorrelationStrategy</code> instance. The responsibility
      of deciding whether the message group is complete is delegated to a
      <code>CompletionStrategy</code> instance.</para>

      <para>Here is a brief highlight of the base
      <code>AbstractMessageAggregator</code> (the responsibility of
      implementing the aggregateMessages method is left to the
      developer):</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public abstract class AbstractMessageAggregator 
              extends AbstractMessageBarrierHandler {

  private volatile CompletionStrategy completionStrategy
                            = new SequenceSizeCompletionStrategy();
  ....

  protected abstract Message&lt;?&gt; aggregateMessages(List&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt; messages);

}</programlisting>
      It also inherits the following default CorrelationStrategy:
      <programlisting language="java">private volatile CorrelationStrategy correlationStrategy =
          new HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy(MessageHeaders.CORRELATION_ID);</programlisting>

      <para>When appropriate, the simplest option is the <code>DefaultMessageAggregator</code>.
      It creates a single Message whose payload is a List of the payloads received
      for a given group. It uses the default <code>CorrelationStrategy</code> and
      <code>CompletionStrategy</code> as shown above. This works well for simple
      Scatter Gather implementations with either a Splitter, Publish Subscribe Channel,
      or Recipient List Router upstream.</para>

      <note>
	    <para>When using a Publish Subscribe Channel or Recipient List Router in this
        type of scenario, be sure to enable the flag to <emphasis>apply sequence</emphasis>.
        That will add the necessary headers (correlation id, sequence number and sequence
        size). That behavior is enabled by default for Splitters in Spring Integration,
        but it is not enabled for the Publish Subscribe Channel or Recipient List
        Router because those components may be used in a variety of contexts where
        those headers are not necessary.</para>
      </note>
	
      <para>When implementing a specific aggregator object for an application,
      a developer can extend <code>AbstractMessageAggregator </code>and
      implement the <code>aggregateMessages</code> method. However, there are
      better suited (which reads, less coupled to the API) solutions for
      implementing the aggregation logic, which can be configured easily
      either through XML or through annotations.</para>

      <para>In general, any ordinary Java class (i.e. POJO) can implement the
      aggregation algorithm. For doing so, it must provide a method that
      accepts as an argument a single java.util.List (parametrized lists are
      supported as well). This method will be invoked for aggregating
      messages, as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a parametrized java.util.List, and the
          parameter type is assignable to Message, then the whole list of
          messages accumulated for aggregation will be sent to the
          aggregator</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a non-parametrized java.util.List or the
          parameter type is not assignable to Message, then the method will
          receive the payloads of the accumulated messages</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if the return type is not assignable to Message, then it will
          be treated as the payload for a Message that will be created
          automatically by the framework.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>In the interest of code simplicity, and promoting best practices
        such as low coupling, testability, etc., the preferred way of
        implementing the aggregation logic is through a POJO, and using the
        XML or annotation support for setting it up in the application.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CompletionStrategy</title>

      <para>The <code>CompletionStrategy</code> interface is defined as
      follows:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public interface CompletionStrategy {

  boolean isComplete(List&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt; messages);

}</programlisting>

      <para>In general, any ordinary Java class (i.e. POJO) can implement the
      completion decision mechanism. For doing so, it must provide a method
      that accepts as an argument a single java.util.List (parametrized lists
      are supported as well), and returns a boolean value. This method will be
      invoked after the arrival of a new message, to decide whether the group
      is complete or not, as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a parametrized java.util.List, and the
          parameter type is assignable to Message, then the whole list of
          messages accumulated in the group will be sent to the method</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>if the argument is a non-parametrized java.util.List or the
          parameter type is not assignable to Message, then the method will
          receive the payloads of the accumulated messages</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the method must return true if the message group is complete
          and ready for aggregation, and false otherwise.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Spring Integration provides an out-of-the box implementation for
      <code>CompletionStrategy</code>, the
      <code>SequenceSizeCompletionStrategy</code>. This implementation uses
      the SEQUENCE_NUMBER and SEQUENCE_SIZE of the arriving messages for
      deciding when a message group is complete and ready to be
      aggregated. As shown above, it is also the default strategy.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CorrelationStrategy</title>

      <para>The <code>CorrelationStrategy</code> interface is defined as
      follows:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public interface CorrelationStrategy {

  Object getCorrelationKey(Message&lt;?&gt; message);

}</programlisting>

      <para>The method shall return an Object which represents the correlation
      key used for grouping messages together. The key must satisfy the
      criteria used for a key in a Map with respect to the implementation of
      equals() and hashCode().</para>

      <para>In general, any ordinary Java class (i.e. POJO) can implement the
      correlation decision mechanism, and the rules for mapping a message to
      a method's argument (or arguments) are the same as for a
      <code>ServiceActivator</code> (including support for @Header
      annotations). The method must return a value, and the value must not be
      <code>null</code>.</para>

      <para>Spring Integration provides an out-of-the box implementation for
      <code>CorrelationStrategy</code>, the
      <code>HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy</code>. This implementation
      returns the value of one of the message headers (whose name is specified
      by a constructor argument) as the correlation key. By default, the
      correlation strategy is a HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy returning
      the value of the CORRELATION_ID header attribute.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-xml">
    <title>Configuring an Aggregator with XML</title>

    <para>Spring Integration supports the configuration of an aggregator via
	XML through the &lt;aggregator/&gt; element. Below you can see an example of 
	an aggregator with all optional parameters defined.</para>

    <programlisting lang="xml">&lt;channel id="inputChannel"/&gt;

&lt;aggregator id="completelyDefinedAggregator" <co id="aggxml1" />
    input-channel="inputChannel" <co id="aggxml2" />
    output-channel="outputChannel"  <co id="aggxml3" />
    discard-channel="discardChannel"  <co id="aggxml4" />
    ref="aggregatorBean" <co id="aggxml5" />
    method="add" <co id="aggxml6" />
    completion-strategy="completionStrategyBean"  <co id="aggxml7" />
    completion-strategy-method="checkCompleteness" <co id="aggxml8" />
    correlation-strategy="correlationStrategyBean" <co
        id="aggxmlCorrelationStrategy" />
    correlation-strategy-method="groupNumbersByLastDigit" <co
        id="aggxmlCorrelationStrategyMethod" />
    timeout="42" <co id="aggxml9" />
    send-partial-result-on-timeout="true" <co id="aggxml10" />
    reaper-interval="135" <co id="aggxml11" />
    tracked-correlation-id-capacity="99" <co id="aggxml12" />
    send-timeout="86420000" <co id="aggxml13" /> /&gt; 

&lt;channel id="outputChannel"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="aggregatorBean" class="sample.PojoAggregator"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="completionStrategyBean" class="sample.PojoCompletionStrategy"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="correlationStrategyBean" class="sample.PojoCorrelationStrategy"/&gt;</programlisting>

    <calloutlist>
      <callout arearefs="aggxml1">
        <para>The id of the aggregator is
        <emphasis>optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml2">
        <para>The input channel of the aggregator.
        <emphasis>Required</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml3">
        <para>The channel where the aggregator will send the aggregation
        results. <emphasis>Optional (because incoming messages can specify a
        reply channel themselves)</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml4">
        <para>The channel where the aggregator will send the messages that
        timed out (if <code>send-partial-results-on-timeout</code> is
        <emphasis>false</emphasis>). <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml5">
        <para>A reference to a bean defined in the application context. The
        bean must implement the aggregation logic as described above.
        <emphasis>Required</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml6">
        <para>A method defined on the bean referenced by <code>ref</code>,
        <emphasis>that implements the message aggregation
        algorithm.</emphasis> <emphasis>Optional, with restrictions (see
        above).</emphasis></para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml7">
        <para>A reference to a bean that implements the decision algorithm as
        to whether a given message group is complete. The bean can be an
        implementation of the CompletionStrategy interface or a POJO. In the
        latter case the completion-strategy-method attribute must be defined
        as well. <emphasis>Optional (by default, the aggregator will use
        sequence size) </emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml8">
        <para>A method defined on the bean referenced by
        <code>completion-strategy</code>, <emphasis>that implements the
        completion decision algorithm.</emphasis> <emphasis>Optional, with
        restrictions (requires <code>completion-strategy</code> to be
        present).</emphasis></para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxmlCorrelationStrategy">
        <para>A reference to a bean that implements the correlation strategy.
        The bean can be an implementation of the CorrelationStrategy interface
        or a POJO. In the latter case the correlation-strategy-method
        attribute must be defined as well. <emphasis>Optional (by default, the
        aggregator will use the correlation id header attribute)
        </emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxmlCorrelationStrategyMethod">
        <para>A method defined on the bean referenced by
        <code>correlation-strategy</code>, <emphasis>that implements the
        correlation key algorithm.</emphasis> <emphasis>Optional, with
        restrictions (requires <code>correlation-strategy</code> to be
        present).</emphasis></para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml9">
        <para>The timeout (in milliseconds) for aggregating messages (counted
        from the arrival of the first message). <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.
        </para>
      </callout>

      <callout arch="" arearefs="aggxml10">
        <para>Whether upon the expiration of the timeout, the aggregator shall
        try to aggregate the messages that have already arrived. <emphasis>Optional
        (false by default)</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml11" condition="">
        <para>The interval (in milliseconds) at which a reaper task is
        executed, checking if there are any timed out groups.
        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml12">
        <para>The capacity of the correlation id tracker. Remembers the
        already processed correlation ids, preventing the formation of new
        groups for messages that arrive after their group has been already
        processed (aggregated or discarded). Set this value to 0 if you
        do not want the messages to be discarded in such a scenario.
        <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="aggxml13">
        <para>The timeout for sending the aggregated messages to the
        output or reply channel. <emphasis>Optional</emphasis>.</para>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

    <para>Using a "ref" attribute is generally recommended if a custom aggregator handler
    implementation can be reused in other <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code> definitions.
    However if a custom aggregator handler implementation should be scoped to a concrete
    definition of the <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code>, you can use an inner bean definition
    (starting with version 1.0.3) for custom aggregator handlers within the
    <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code> element:
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<aggregator input-channel="input" method="sum" output-channel="output">
    <beans:bean class="org.foo.ExampleAggregator"/>
</aggregator>]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>Using both a "ref" attribute and an inner bean definition in the same
      <code>&lt;aggregator&gt;</code> configuration is not allowed, as it creates an
      ambiguous condition. In such cases, an Exception will be thrown.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>An example implementation of the aggregator bean looks as follows:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">public class PojoAggregator {

  public Long add(List&lt;Long&gt; results) {
    long total = 0l;
    for (long partialResult: results) {
      total += partialResult;
    }
    return total;
  }

}</programlisting>

    <para>An implementation of the completion strategy bean for the example
    above may be as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting language="java">public class PojoCompletionStrategy {
...
  public boolean checkCompleteness(List&lt;Long&gt; numbers) {
    int sum = 0;
    for (long number: numbers) {
      sum += number;
    }
    return sum &gt;= maxValue;
  }
}</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>Wherever it makes sense, the completion strategy method and
        the aggregator method can be combined in a single bean.</para>
      </note>
    </para>

    <para>An implementation of the correlation strategy bean for the example
    above may be as follows:</para>

    <para><programlisting language="java">public class PojoCorrelationStrategy {
...
  public Long groupNumbersByLastDigit(Long number) {
    return number % 10;
  }
}</programlisting></para>

    <para>For example, this aggregator would group numbers by some criterion
    (in our case the remainder after dividing by 10) and will hold the group
    until the sum of the numbers which represents the payload exceeds a
    certain value.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Wherever it makes sense, the completion strategy method, correlation
      strategy method and the aggregator method can be combined in a single bean
      (all of them or any two).</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="aggregator-annotations">
    <title>Configuring an Aggregator with Annotations</title>

    <para>An aggregator configured using annotations can look like
    this.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">public class Waiter {
  ... 

  @Aggregator <co id="aggann" /> 
  public Delivery aggregatingMethod(List&lt;OrderItem&gt; items) {
    ...
  }

  @CompletionStrategy <co id="agganncs" />
  public boolean completionChecker(List&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt; messages) {
    ...
  }

  @CorrelationStrategy <co id="agganncorrs" />
  public String correlateBy(OrderItem item) {
    ...
  }

}</programlisting>

    <calloutlist>
      <callout arearefs="aggann">
        <para>An annotation indicating that this method shall be used as an
        aggregator. Must be specified if this class will be used as an
        aggregator.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="agganncs">
        <para id="aggann2">An annotation indicating that this method shall be
        used as the completion strategy of an aggregator. If not present on
        any method, the aggregator will use the
        SequenceSizeCompletionStrategy.</para>
      </callout>

      <callout arearefs="agganncorrs">
        <para id="agann3">An annotation indicating that this method shall be
        used as the correlation strategy of an aggregator. If no correlation
        strategy is indicated, the aggregator will use the
        HeaderAttributeCorrelationStrategy based on CORRELATION_ID.</para>
      </callout>
    </calloutlist>

    <para>All of the configuration options provided by the xml element are also
    available for the @Aggregator annotation.</para>

    <para>The aggregator can be either referenced explicitly from XML or, if
    the @MessageEndpoint is defined on the class, detected automatically
    through classpath scanning.</para>

  </section>
</chapter>
