<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="channel">
  <title>Message Channels</title>
  <para>
    While the <interfacename>Message</interfacename> plays the crucial role of encapsulating data, it is the
    <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> that decouples message producers from message consumers.
  </para>

  <section id="channel-interfaces">
    <title>The MessageChannel Interface</title>
    <para>
      Spring Integration's top-level <interfacename>MessageChannel</interfacename> interface is defined as follows.
      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface MessageChannel {

    String getName();

    boolean send(Message message);

    boolean send(Message message, long timeout);
}]]></programlisting>
      When sending a message, the return value will be <emphasis>true</emphasis> if the message is sent successfully.
      If the send call times out or is interrupted, then it will return <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <section id="channel-interfaces-pollablechannel">
      <title>PollableChannel</title>
      <para>
        Since Message Channels may or may not buffer Messages (as discussed in the overview), there are two
        sub-interfaces defining the buffering (pollable) and non-buffering (subscribable) channel behavior. Here is the
        definition of <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename>.
        <programlisting language="java">public interface PollableChannel extends MessageChannel {

    Message&lt;?&gt; receive();

    Message&lt;?&gt; receive(long timeout);

    List&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt; clear();

    List&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt; purge(MessageSelector selector);

}</programlisting>
        Similar to the send methods, when receiving a message, the return value will be <emphasis>null</emphasis> in the
        case of a timeout or interrupt.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="channel-interfaces-subscribablechannel">
      <title>SubscribableChannel</title>
      <para>
        The <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename> base interface is implemented by channels that send
        Messages directly to their subscribed <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename>s. Therefore, they do not
        provide receive methods for polling, but instead define methods for managing those subscribers:
        <programlisting language="java">public interface SubscribableChannel extends MessageChannel {

    boolean subscribe(MessageHandler handler);

    boolean unsubscribe(MessageHandler handler);

}</programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="channel-implementations">
    <title>Message Channel Implementations</title>
    <para>
      Spring Integration provides several different Message Channel implementations. Each is briefly described in the
      sections below.
    </para>
    <section id="channel-implementations-publishsubscribechannel">
      <title>PublishSubscribeChannel</title>
      <para>
        The <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname> implementation broadcasts any Message
        sent to it to all of its subscribed handlers. This is most often used for sending
        <emphasis>Event Messages</emphasis> whose primary role is notification as opposed to
        <emphasis>Document Messages</emphasis> which are generally intended to be processed by
        a single handler. Note that the <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname> is
        intended for sending only. Since it broadcasts to its subscribers directly when its
        <methodname>send(Message)</methodname> method is invoked, consumers cannot poll for
        Messages (it does not implement <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename> and
        therefore has no <methodname>receive()</methodname> method). Instead, any subscriber
        must be a <interfacename>MessageHandler</interfacename> itself, and the subscriber's
        <methodname>handleMessage(Message)</methodname> method will be invoked in turn.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-implementations-queuechannel">
      <title>QueueChannel</title>
      <para>
        The <classname>QueueChannel</classname> implementation wraps a queue. Unlike the
        <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname>, the <classname>QueueChannel</classname> has point-to-point
        semantics. In other words, even if the channel has multiple consumers, only one of them should receive any
        Message sent to that channel. It provides a default no-argument constructor (providing an essentially unbounded
        capacity of <code>Integer.MAX_VALUE</code>) as well as a constructor that accepts the queue capacity:
        <programlisting language="java">public QueueChannel(int capacity)</programlisting>
        A channel that has not reached its capacity limit will store messages in its internal queue, and the
        <methodname>send()</methodname> method will return immediately even if no receiver is ready to handle the
        message. If the queue has reached capacity, then the sender will block until room is available. Or, if using
        the send call that accepts a timeout, it will block until either room is available or the timeout period
        elapses, whichever occurs first. Likewise, a receive call will return immediately if a message is available
        on the queue, but if the queue is empty, then a receive call may block until either a message is available
        or the timeout elapses. In either case, it is possible to force an immediate return regardless of the
        queue's state by passing a timeout value of 0. Note however, that calls to the no-arg versions of
        <methodname>send()</methodname> and <methodname>receive()</methodname> will block indefinitely.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-implementations-prioritychannel">
      <title>PriorityChannel</title>
      <para>
        Whereas the <classname>QueueChannel</classname> enforces first-in/first-out (FIFO) ordering, the
        <classname>PriorityChannel</classname> is an alternative implementation that allows for messages
        to be ordered within the channel based upon a priority. By default the priority is determined by the
        '<literal>priority</literal>' header within each message. However, for custom priority determination
        logic, a comparator of type <classname>Comparator&lt;Message&lt;?&gt;&gt;</classname> can be provided
        to the <classname>PriorityChannel</classname>'s constructor.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-implementations-rendezvouschannel">
      <title>RendezvousChannel</title>
      <para>
        The <classname>RendezvousChannel</classname> enables a "direct-handoff" scenario where a sender will block
        until another party invokes the channel's <methodname>receive()</methodname> method or vice-versa. Internally,
        this implementation is quite similar to the <classname>QueueChannel</classname> except that it uses a
        <classname>SynchronousQueue</classname> (a zero-capacity implementation of
        <interfacename>BlockingQueue</interfacename>). This works well in situations where the sender and receiver are
        operating in different threads but simply dropping the message in a queue asynchronously is not appropriate.
        In other words, with a <classname>RendezvousChannel</classname> at least the sender knows that some receiver
        has accepted the message, whereas with a <classname>QueueChannel</classname>, the message would have been
        stored to the internal queue and potentially never received.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <para>
          Keep in mind that all of these queue-based channels are storing messages in-memory only. When persistence
          is required, you can either invoke a database operation within a handler or use Spring Integration's
          support for JMS-based Channel Adapters. The latter option allows you to take advantage of any JMS provider's
          implementation for message persistence, and it will be discussed in <xref linkend="jms"/>. However, when
          buffering in a queue is not necessary, the simplest approach is to rely upon the
          <classname>DirectChannel</classname> discussed next.
        </para>
      </tip>
      <para>
        The <classname>RendezvousChannel</classname> is also useful for implementing request-reply
        operations. The sender can create a temporary, anonymous instance of <classname>RendezvousChannel</classname>
        which it then sets as the 'replyChannel' header when building a Message. After sending that Message, the sender
        can immediately call receive (optionally providing a timeout value) in order to block while waiting for a reply
        Message. This is very similar to the implementation used internally by many of Spring Integration's
        request-reply components.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-implementations-directchannel">
      <title>DirectChannel</title>
      <para>
        The <classname>DirectChannel</classname> has point-to-point semantics but otherwise is more similar to the
        <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname> than any of the queue-based channel implementations described
        above. It implements the <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename> interface instead of the
        <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename> interface, so it dispatches Messages directly to a subscriber.
        As a point-to-point channel, however, it differs from the <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname> in
        that it will only send each Message to a <emphasis>single</emphasis> subscribed
        <classname>MessageHandler</classname>.
      </para>
      <para>
        In addition to being the simplest point-to-point channel option, one of its most important features is that
        it enables a single thread to perform the operations on "both sides" of the channel. For example, if a handler
        is subscribed to a <classname>DirectChannel</classname>, then sending a Message to that channel will trigger
        invocation of that handler's <methodname>handleMessage(Message)</methodname> method <emphasis>directly in the
        sender's thread</emphasis>, before the send() method invocation can return.
      </para>
      <para>
        The key motivation for providing a channel implementation with this behavior is to support transactions that
        must span across the channel while still benefiting from the abstraction and loose coupling that the channel
        provides. If the send call is invoked within the scope of a transaction, then the outcome of the handler's
        invocation (e.g. updating a database record) will play a role in determining the ultimate result of that
        transaction (commit or rollback).
        <note>
          Since the <classname>DirectChannel</classname> is the simplest option and does not add any additional
          overhead that would be required for scheduling and managing the threads of a poller, it is the default
          channel type within Spring Integration. The general idea is to define the channels for an application and
          then to consider which of those need to provide buffering or to throttle input, and then modify those to
          be queue-based <interfacename>PollableChannels</interfacename>. Likewise, if a channel needs to broadcast
          messages, it should not be a <classname>DirectChannel</classname> but rather a
          <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname>. Below you will see how each of these can be configured.
        </note>
      </para>
      <para>
        The <classname>DirectChannel</classname> internally delegates to a Message Dispatcher to invoke its
        subscribed Message Handlers, and that dispatcher can have a load-balancing strategy. The load-balancer
        determines how invocations will be ordered in the case that there are multiple handlers subscribed to the
        same channel. When using the namespace support described below, the default strategy is
        "round-robin" which essentially load-balances across the handlers in rotation.
        <note>
          The "round-robin" strategy is currently the only implementation available out-of-the-box in Spring
          Integration. Other strategy implementations may be added in future versions.
        </note>
      </para>
      <para>
        The load-balancer also works in combination with a boolean <emphasis>failover</emphasis> property.
        If the "failover" value is true (the default), then the dispatcher will fall back to any subsequent
        handlers as necessary when preceding handlers throw Exceptions. The order is determined by an optional
        order value defined on the handlers themselves or, if no such value exists, the order in which the
        handlers are subscribed.
      </para>
      <para>
        If a certain situation requires that the dispatcher always try to invoke the first handler, then
        fallback in the same fixed order sequence every time an error occurs, no load-balancing strategy should
        be provided. In other words, the dispatcher still supports the failover boolean property even when no
        load-balancing is enabled. Without load-balancing, however, the invocation of handlers will always begin
        with the first according to their order. For example, this approach works well when there is a clear
        definition of primary, secondary, tertiary, and so on. When using the namespace support, the "order"
        attribute on any endpoint will determine that order.
      </para>
      <note>
          Keep in mind that load-balancing and failover only apply when a channel has more than one
          subscribed Message Handler. When using the namespace support, this means that more than one
          endpoint shares the same channel reference in the "input-channel" attribute.
       </note>
    </section>
    <section id="executor-channel">
      <title>ExecutorChannel</title>
      <para>
        The <classname>ExecutorChannel</classname> is a point-to-point channel that supports
        the same dispatcher configuration as <classname>DirectChannel</classname> (load-balancing strategy
        and the failover boolean property). The key difference between these two dispatching channel types
        is that the <classname>ExecutorChannel</classname> delegates to an instance of
        <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename> to perform the dispatch. This means that the send method
        typically will not block, but it also means that the handler invocation may not occur in the sender's
        thread. It therefore <emphasis>does not support transactions spanning the sender and receiving
        handler</emphasis>.
        <tip>
	      Note that there are occasions where the sender may block. For example, when using a
	      TaskExecutor with a rejection-policy that throttles back on the client (such as the
          <code>ThreadPoolExecutor.CallerRunsPolicy</code>), the sender's thread will execute
          the method directly anytime the thread pool is at its maximum capacity and the
          executor's work queue is full. Since that situation would only occur in a non-predictable
          way, that obviously cannot be relied upon for transactions.
        </tip>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-implementations-threadlocalchannel">
      <title>ThreadLocalChannel</title>
      <para>
        The final channel implementation type is <classname>ThreadLocalChannel</classname>. This channel also delegates
        to a queue internally, but the queue is bound to the current thread. That way the thread that sends to the
        channel will later be able to receive those same Messages, but no other thread would be able to access them.
        While probably the least common type of channel, this is useful for situations where
        <classname>DirectChannels</classname> are being used to enforce a single thread of operation but any reply
        Messages should be sent to a "terminal" channel. If that terminal channel is a
        <classname>ThreadLocalChannel</classname>, the original sending thread can collect its replies from it.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="channel-interceptors">
    <title>Channel Interceptors</title>
    <para>
      One of the advantages of a messaging architecture is the ability to provide common behavior and capture
      meaningful information about the messages passing through the system in a non-invasive way. Since the
      <interfacename>Messages</interfacename> are being sent to and received from
      <interfacename>MessageChannels</interfacename>, those channels provide an opportunity for intercepting
      the send and receive operations. The <interfacename>ChannelInterceptor</interfacename> strategy interface
      provides methods for each of those operations:
      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface ChannelInterceptor {

    Message<?> preSend(Message<?> message, MessageChannel channel);

    void postSend(Message<?> message, MessageChannel channel, boolean sent);

    boolean preReceive(MessageChannel channel);

    Message<?> postReceive(Message<?> message, MessageChannel channel);
}]]></programlisting>
      After implementing the interface, registering the interceptor with a channel is just a matter of calling:
      <programlisting language="java">channel.addInterceptor(someChannelInterceptor);</programlisting>
      The methods that return a Message instance can be used for transforming the Message or can return 'null'
      to prevent further processing (of course, any of the methods can throw a RuntimeException). Also, the
      <methodname>preReceive</methodname> method can return '<literal>false</literal>' to prevent the receive
      operation from proceeding.
      <note>
        Keep in mind that <methodname>receive()</methodname> calls are only relevant for
        <interfacename>PollableChannels</interfacename>. In fact the
        <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename> interface does not even define a
        <methodname>receive()</methodname> method. The reason for this is that when a Message is sent to a
        <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename> it will be sent directly to one or more subscribers
        depending on the type of channel (e.g. a PublishSubscribeChannel sends to all of its subscribers). Therefore,
        the <methodname>preReceive(..)</methodname> and <methodname>postReceive(..)</methodname> interceptor methods
        are only invoked when the interceptor is applied to a <interfacename>PollableChannel</interfacename>.
      </note>
      Spring Integration also provides an implementation of the
      <ulink url="http://eaipatterns.com/WireTap.html">Wire Tap</ulink> pattern.
      It is a simple interceptor that sends the Message to another channel without otherwise altering the
      existing flow. It can be very useful for debugging and monitoring. An example is shown in
      <xref linkend="channel-wiretap"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Because it is rarely necessary to implement all of the interceptor methods, a
      <classname>ChannelInterceptorAdapter</classname> class is also available for sub-classing. It provides no-op
      methods (the <literal>void</literal> method is empty, the <classname>Message</classname> returning methods
      return the Message as-is, and the <literal>boolean</literal> method returns <literal>true</literal>).
      Therefore, it is often easiest to extend that class and just implement the method(s) that you need as in the
      following example.
      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class CountingChannelInterceptor extends ChannelInterceptorAdapter {

    private final AtomicInteger sendCount = new AtomicInteger();

    @Override
    public Message<?> preSend(Message<?> message, MessageChannel channel) {
        sendCount.incrementAndGet();
        return message;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
      <tip>
        The order of invocation for the interceptor methods depends on the type of channel. As described above,
        the queue-based channels are the only ones where the receive method is intercepted in the first place.
        Additionally, the relationship between send and receive interception depends on the timing of separate
        sender and receiver threads. For example, if a receiver is already blocked while waiting for a message
        the order could be: preSend, preReceive, postReceive, postSend. However, if a receiver polls after the
        sender has placed a message on the channel and already returned, the order would be: preSend, postSend,
        (some-time-elapses) preReceive, postReceive. The time that elapses in such a case depends on a number
        of factors and is therefore generally unpredictable (in fact, the receive may never happen!).
        Obviously, the type of queue also plays a role (e.g. rendezvous vs. priority). The bottom line is that
        you cannot rely on the order beyond the fact that preSend will precede postSend and preReceive will
        precede postReceive.
      </tip>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="channel-template">
    <title>MessageChannelTemplate</title>
    <para>
      As you will see when the endpoints and their various configuration options are introduced, Spring Integration
      provides a foundation for messaging components that enables non-invasive invocation of your application code
      <emphasis>from the messaging system</emphasis>. However, sometimes it is necessary to invoke the messaging system
      <emphasis>from your application code</emphasis>. For convenience when implementing such use-cases, Spring
      Integration provides a <classname>MessageChannelTemplate</classname> that supports a variety of operations across
      the Message Channels, including request/reply scenarios. For example, it is possible to send a request
      and wait for a reply.
      <programlisting language="java">MessageChannelTemplate template = new MessageChannelTemplate();

Message reply = template.sendAndReceive(new StringMessage("test"), someChannel);</programlisting>
      In that example, a temporary anonymous channel would be created internally by the template. The
      'sendTimeout' and 'receiveTimeout' properties may also be set on the template, and other exchange
      types are also supported.
      <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public boolean send(final Message<?> message, final MessageChannel channel) { ... }

public Message<?> sendAndReceive(final Message<?> request, final MessageChannel channel) { .. }

public Message<?> receive(final PollableChannel<?> channel) { ... }]]></programlisting>
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        A less invasive approach that allows you to invoke simple interfaces with payload and/or header
        values instead of Message instances is described in <xref linkend="gateway-proxy"/>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="channel-configuration">
    <title>Configuring Message Channels</title>
    <para>
      To create a Message Channel instance, you can use the 'channel' element:
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;channel id="exampleChannel"/&gt;</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      The default channel type is <emphasis>Point to Point</emphasis>. To create a
      <emphasis>Publish Subscribe</emphasis> channel, use the "publish-subscribe-channel" element:
      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;publish-subscribe-channel id="exampleChannel"/&gt;</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      To create a <ulink url="http://www.eaipatterns.com/DatatypeChannel.html">Datatype Channel</ulink> that only
      accepts messages containing a certain payload type, provide the fully-qualified class name in the
      channel element's <literal>datatype</literal> attribute:
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="numberChannel" datatype="java.lang.Number"/>]]></programlisting>
      Note that the type check passes for any type that is <emphasis>assignable</emphasis> to the channel's
      datatype. In other words, the "numberChannel" above would accept messages whose payload is
      <classname>java.lang.Integer</classname> or <classname>java.lang.Double</classname>. Multiple types can be
      provided as a comma-delimited list:
      <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="stringOrNumberChannel" datatype="java.lang.String,java.lang.Number"/>]]></programlisting> 
    </para>
    <para>
      When using the "channel" element without any sub-elements, it will create a <classname>DirectChannel</classname>
      instance (a <interfacename>SubscribableChannel</interfacename>).
    </para>
    <para>
      However, you can alternatively provide a variety of "queue" sub-elements to create any of
      the pollable channel types (as described in
      <xref linkend="channel-implementations"/>). Examples of each are shown below.
    </para>
    <section id="channel-configuration-directchannel">
      <title>DirectChannel Configuration</title>
      <para>
        As mentioned above, <classname>DirectChannel</classname> is the default type.
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="directChannel"/>]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        A default channel will have a <emphasis>round-robin</emphasis> load-balancer and will also have
        failover enabled (See the discussion in <xref linkend="channel-implementations-directchannel"/>
        for more detail). To disable one or both of these, add a &lt;dispatcher/&gt; sub-element and
        configure the attributes:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="failFastChannel">
    <dispatcher failover="false"/>
</channel>

<channel id="channelWithFixedOrderSequenceFailover">
    <dispatcher load-balancer="none"/>
</channel>
]]></programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-configuration-queuechannel">
      <title>QueueChannel Configuration</title>
      <para>
        To create a <classname>QueueChannel</classname>, use the "queue" sub-element.
        You may specify the channel's capacity:
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;channel id="queueChannel"&gt;
    &lt;queue capacity="25"/&gt;
&lt;/channel&gt;</programlisting>
        <note>
          If you do not provide a value for the 'capacity' attribute on this &lt;queue/&gt; sub-element,
          the resulting queue will be unbounded. To avoid issues such as OutOfMemoryErrors, it is highly
          recommended to set an explicit value for a bounded queue.
        </note>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-configuration-pubsubchannel">
      <title>PublishSubscribeChannel Configuration</title>
      <para>
        To create a <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname>, use the "publish-subscribe-channel" element.
        When using this element, you can also specify the "task-executor" used for publishing
        Messages (if none is specified it simply publishes in the sender's thread): 
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;publish-subscribe-channel id="pubsubChannel" task-executor="someExecutor"/&gt;</programlisting>
        If you are providing a <emphasis>Resequencer</emphasis> or <emphasis>Aggregator</emphasis> downstream
        from a <classname>PublishSubscribeChannel</classname>, then you can set the 'apply-sequence' property
        on the channel to <code>true</code>. That will indicate that the channel should set the sequence-size
        and sequence-number Message headers as well as the correlation id prior to passing the Messages along.
        For example, if there are 5 subscribers, the sequence-size would be set to 5, and the Messages would
        have sequence-number header values ranging from 1 to 5.
        <programlisting language="xml">&lt;publish-subscribe-channel id="pubsubChannel" apply-sequence="true"/&gt;</programlisting>
        <note>
          The 'apply-sequence' value is <code>false</code> by default so that a Publish Subscribe Channel
          can send the exact same Message instances to multiple outbound channels. Since Spring Integration
          enforces immutability of the payload and header references, the channel creates new Message
          instances with the same payload reference but different header values when the flag is set to
          <code>true</code>. 
        </note>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-configuration-executorchannel">
      <title>ExecutorChannel</title>
      <para>
        To create an <classname>ExecutorChannel</classname>, add the &lt;dispatcher&gt; sub-element along
        with a 'task-executor' attribute. Its value can reference any <interfacename>TaskExecutor</interfacename>
        within the context. For example, this enables configuration of a thread-pool for dispatching messages
        to subscribed handlers. As mentioned above, this does break the "single-threaded" execution context
        between sender and receiver so that any active transaction context will not be shared by the invocation
        of the handler (i.e. the handler may throw an Exception, but the send invocation has already returned
        successfully).
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="executorChannel">
    <dispatcher task-executor="someExecutor"/>
</channel>]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <note>
        The "load-balancer" and "failover" options are also both available on the dispatcher sub-element
        as described above in <xref linkend="channel-configuration-directchannel"/>. The same defaults
        apply as well. So, the channel will have a round-robin load-balancing strategy with failover
        enabled unless explicit configuration is provided for one or both of those attributes.
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="executorChannelWithoutFailover">
    <dispatcher task-executor="someExecutor" failover="false"/>
</channel>]]></programlisting>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-configuration-prioritychannel">
      <title>PriorityChannel Configuration</title>
      <para>
        To create a <classname>PriorityChannel</classname>, use the "priority-queue" sub-element:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="priorityChannel">
    <priority-queue capacity="20"/>
</channel>]]></programlisting>
        By default, the channel will consult the <classname>MessagePriority</classname> header of the 
        message. However, a custom <interfacename>Comparator</interfacename> reference may be
        provided instead. Also, note that the <classname>PriorityChannel</classname> (like the other types)
        does support the "datatype" attribute. As with the QueueChannel, it also supports a "capacity" attribute.
        The following example demonstrates all of these:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="priorityChannel" datatype="example.Widget">
    <priority-queue comparator="widgetComparator"
                    capacity="10"/>
</channel>
]]></programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-configuration-rendezvouschannel">
      <title>RendezvousChannel Configuration</title>
      <para>
        A <classname>RendezvousChannel</classname> is created when the queue sub-element is
        a &lt;rendezvous-queue&gt;. It does not provide any additional configuration options to
        those described above, and its queue does not accept any capacity value since it is a
        0-capacity direct handoff queue.
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="rendezvousChannel"/>
    <rendezvous-queue/>
</channel>
]]></programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="channel-configuration-threadlocalchannel">
      <title>ThreadLocalChannel Configuration</title>
      <para>
        The <classname>ThreadLocalChannel</classname> does not provide any additional configuration options.
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<thread-local-channel id="threadLocalChannel"/>]]></programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="channel-configuration-interceptors">
	  <title>Channel Interceptor Configuration</title>
      <para>
        Message channels may also have interceptors as described in <xref linkend="channel-interceptors"/>. The
        &lt;interceptors&gt; sub-element can be added within &lt;channel&gt; (or the more specific element
        types). Provide the "ref" attribute to reference any Spring-managed object that implements the
        <interfacename>ChannelInterceptor</interfacename> interface:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<channel id="exampleChannel">
    ]]><emphasis><![CDATA[<interceptors>
        <ref bean="trafficMonitoringInterceptor"/>
    </interceptors>]]></emphasis><![CDATA[
</channel>]]></programlisting>
        In general, it is a good idea to define the interceptor implementations in a separate location since they
        usually provide common behavior that can be reused across multiple channels.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="global-channel-configuration-interceptors">
	  <title>Global Channel Interceptor Configuration</title>
      <para>
        Channel Interceptors allow you for a clean and concise way of applying cross-cutting behavior per individual channel. 
        But what if the same behavior should be applied on multiple channels, configuring the same set of interceptors for 
        each channel <emphasis>would not be</emphasis> the most efficient way. The better way would be to configure interceptors globally and apply 
        them on multiple channels in one shot. Spring Integration provides capabilities to configure <emphasis>Global Interceptor Chains</emphasis> 
        and apply them on multiple channels.
		Look at the example below:
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:channel-interceptor-chain channel-name-pattern="input*, bar*, foo" order="3">
    <bean class="foo.barSampleInterceptor"/>
    <ref bean="someOtherInterceptor"/>
</int:channel-interceptor-chain>]]></programlisting>
        &lt;channel-interceptor-chain&gt; element will assemble the chain of interceptors and will apply them on all the 
        channels defined in the &lt;channel-name-patter&gt; attribute. In the above case the two interceptors that are defined 
        within the chain are going to be applied on 'foo' channel and all other channels that begin with 'bar' and 'input'. 
        The &lt;order&gt; attribute allows you to manage the place where this interceptor chain will be injected. 
        For example, channel 'inputChannel' could have individual interceptors configured locally (see below):
        <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<int:channel id="inputChannel"> 
	<int:interceptors>
		<int:wire-tap channel="logger"/> 
	</int:interceptors>
</int:channel>]]></programlisting>
	The reasonable question would be where interceptors defined by <emphasis>channel-interceptor-cahin</emphasis> should be injected
	in relation to the existing one(s) (configured locally or through other global chains)? Current implementation provides 
	a very simple and clever mechanism of handling this. Positive number in the <emphasis>order</emphasis> attribute will ensure interceptor injection 
	after existing interceptors and negative number will ensure that such interceptors injected before. 
	This means that in the above example interceptors configured in global interceptor chain would be injected after 
	'wire-tap' interceptor configured locally. If there was another global chain with matching <emphasis>channel-name-pattern</emphasis> the 
	order between the interceptors defined in two chains would be determined based on who's got the higher or lower 
	value in <emphasis>order</emphasis> attribute.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="channel-wiretap">
	  <title>Wire Tap</title>
      <para>
		As mentioned above, Spring Integration provides a simple <emphasis>Wire Tap</emphasis> interceptor out of
		the box. You can configure a <emphasis>Wire Tap</emphasis> on any channel within an 'interceptors' element.
        This is especially useful for debugging, and can be used in conjunction with Spring Integration's logging
		Channel Adapter as follows: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[ <channel id="in">
     <interceptors>
         <wire-tap channel="logger"/>
     </interceptors>
 </channel>

 <logging-channel-adapter id="logger" level="DEBUG"/>]]></programlisting>
        <tip>
			The 'logging-channel-adapter' also accepts a boolean attribute: <emphasis>'log-full-message'</emphasis>.
			That is <emphasis>false</emphasis> by default so that only the payload is logged. Setting that to
			<emphasis>true</emphasis> enables logging of all headers in addition to the payload.
	    </tip>
      </para>
	</section>

    <note>
      <para>
        If namespace support is enabled, there are also two special channels defined within the context by default:
        <code>errorChannel</code> and <code>nullChannel</code>. The 'nullChannel' acts like <code>/dev/null</code>,
        simply logging any Message sent to it at DEBUG level and returning immediately. Any time you face channel
        resolution errors for a reply that you don't care about, you can set the affected component's 'output-channel'
        to reference 'nullChannel' (the name 'nullChannel' is reserved within the context). The 'errorChannel' is
        used internally for sending error messages, and it can be overridden with a custom configuration. It is
        discussed in greater detail in <xref linkend="namespace-errorhandler"/>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

</chapter>